[
    {
      "question": "Is it possible for an object to be immersed in fluid flow and have no stagnation points on its surface?",
      "answer": "No, any object fully immersed in fluid flow will have at least one stagnation point on its surface where the flow velocity is zero. It is possible for there to be more than one stagnation point on such an object, but it is impossible for there to be none.",
      "explanation": "",
      "reference":""
    },
    {
      "question": "When solving for the velocity of a chaotic fast-moving fluid close to a wall would it be valid to employ Bernoulli’s equation?",
      "answer": "In this case using Bernoulli’s equation would be invalid. Bernoulli’s equation can only validly be used when the flow is steady, incompressible, and inviscid. The word chaotic indicates the fluid is turbulent, not steady. The fact that it is close to a wall indicates there would be non-negligible friction effects acting on the fluid.",
      "explanation": "",
      "reference":""
    },
    {
      "question": "What differentiates the Navier-Stokes equations from Euler’s equations?",
      "answer": "Euler’s equations are derived from an application of Newton’s Second Law to inviscid flow. The Navier-Stokes equations take the viscosity terms into account.",
      "explanation": "",
      "reference":""
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the relationship between viscosity and shear stress?",
      "answer": "Viscosity is the proportionality coefficient that when multiplied by velocity gradient yields shear stress.",
      "explanation": "",
      "reference": "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shear_stress"
    },
    {
      "question": "Can M ever not be equal to 1 at the throat of a channel?",
      "answer": "Yes. In the case that the change in velocity with respect to distance is equal to zero, acceleration is zero through the channel, and M can be not equal to 1 at the throat.",
      "explanation": "",
      "reference":""
    },
    {
      "question": "Is Fanno flow an appropriate model for a steady, compressible flow through a long pipe with friction, and loses heat to the pipe through convective heat transfer?",
      "answer": "No. Although the Fanno flow model is valid for steady, compressible flow with friction through long pipes, the flow must also be adiabatic (Q=0) for Fanno flow to be an applicable model. The presence of convective heat transfer indicates that heat Q is non-zero and therefore the flow is not adiabatic. One must also confirm that the area of the duct is constant and assume flow is one-dimensional before applying the Fanno flow model.",
      "explanation": "",
      "reference":""
    },
    {
      "question": "Is it possible for an oblique shock or a detached shock to form at the same turning angle?",
      "answer": "Yes. It is possible for an oblique shock or a detached shock to form at a concave corner of the same turning angle given different flow Mach numbers. Flows at lower Mach numbers have lower maximum turning angles, so a lower velocity flow can produce a detached shock going over the same corner that a higher velocity flow would produce an oblique shock going over.",
      "explanation": "",
      "reference":""
    },
    {
      "question": "What differentiates Poiseuille flow from Couette flow and what is an example of a situation in which each one could be useful?",
      "answer": "Poiseuille flow is constant pressure gradient driven flow between two stationary plates. One example of a situation in which it could be useful for modeling axisymmetric flow through pipes. In contrast, Couette flow is velocity driven flow between a stationary and a moving plate. It could be useful for modeling for example bearing lubrication.",
      "explanation": "",
      "reference":""
    },
    {
      "question": "If one puts a backspinning cylinder in transverse flow, what direction will the resulting lift force be in?",
      "answer": "Due to the Magnus effect, the resulting lift force will be in the upwards direction normal to the flow. This can be seen in the similarity of the pressure gradient and the shape of the streamlines around a cylinder to those of an airfoil with a positive angle of attack.",
      "explanation": "",
      "reference": "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magnus_effect"
    },
    {
      "question": "Water having a density of 999 kg/m^3 travels along a curved streamline with a normal acceleration of -5 m/s^2. At a point when the local radius of curvature is 10 m, what is the component of the flows velocity tangent to the streamline and what is the pressure gradient across the streamline?",
      "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n    \nrho = 999 # Density (kg/m^3)\na_n = -5 # Normal Acceleration (m/s^2)\nR = 10 # Local Radius of Curvature (m)\n    \n# Rearrange acceleration normal to streamline equation\nv_s = np.sqrt((- a_n) * R)\n    \n# Formula for pressure gradient normal to a streamline\ndpdn = rho * (-a_n)\n    \nprint('Velocity tangent to streamline:', v_s, 'm/s. Pressure gradient accross the streamline:', dpdn, 'Pa/m.')\n",
      "explanation": "This code utilizes the formula for acceleration normal to a streamline and for pressure gradient normal to a streamline. These two formulas can be expressed as a_n = - v_s^2 / R and dp/dn = rho * v_s^2 / R, where 'a_n' is the normal acceleration, 'v_s' is the tangential velocity, 'R' is the local radius of curvature, and 'dp/dn' is the pressure gradient, respectively.",
      "reference": ""
    },
    {
      "question": "A fluid (gasoline) of density 680 kg/m^3, a kinematic viscosity of 4.6E-7 m^2/s, and a mass flow rate 0.2 kg/s flows through a pipe. Calculate the pressure loss over 10 km of 0.5 m diameter pipe owing to friction.",
      "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n    \nrho = 680 # Density (kg/m^3)\nnu = 4.6 * (10 ** (-7)) # Kinematic Viscosity (m^2/s)\nmdot = 0.2 # Mass Flow Rate (kg/s)\nL = 10000 # Length of Pipe (m)\nD = 0.5 # Diameter of Pipe (m)\n    \n# Determine dynamic viscosity\nmu = nu * rho\n    \n# Determine volumetric flow rate\nQ = mdot/rho\n    \n# Apply Hagen-Poiseuille equation\ndelta_p = (8 * mu * Q * L)/(np.pi * ((D/2)**4))\n    \nprint('Pressure loss:', delta_p, 'Pa')\n",
      "explanation": "This code first takes kinematic viscosity and mass flow rate, and uses density to calculated dynamic viscosity and volumetric flow rate from them. Next it applies the Hagen-Poiseuille formula delta_p = (8 * mu * Q * L)/(pi * R^4) where 'delta_p' is the pressure loss, 'mu' is dynamic viscosity, 'Q' is volumetric flow rate, 'L' is the length of pipe, and 'R' is the radius of the pipe, respectively. Using this equation it determines the pressure loss over the given length of pipe.",
      "reference": "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hagen-Poiseuille_equation"
    },
    {
      "question": "A plate 2 m in length and 5 m in width is submerged in a fluid (water) with a density of 999 kg/m^3, and it is tilted down in such a way that the length edge is at a 20 degree angle with the surface of the fluid. What this the vertical force acting upon the plate. The acceleration due to gravity can be assumed to be 9.8 m/s^2.",
      "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n    \nrho = 999 # Density (kg/m^3)\nL = 2 # Length of plate (m)\nw = 5 # Width of plate (m)\nalpha = 20 # Angle of plate from surface (degrees)\ng = 9.8 # Acceleration due to gravity (m/s^2)\n    \n# The vertical force acting upon the plate is equivalent to the weight of the volume of the fluid above the plate\nF_v = 0.5 * (L**2) * np.cos(alpha * np.pi / 180) * np.sin(alpha * np.pi / 180) * w * rho * g\n    \nprint('The vertical force acting on the plate is:', F_v, 'N')\n",
      "explanation": "This code calculates the vertical force acting on a plate submerged in fluid at an angle with the surface of the fluid. It does this by calculating the weight of the fluid above the plate, which is equivalent to the vertical force acting upon the plate. This can be found by multiplying together volume, density, and gravity, or equivalently using the following formula F_v = 0.5 * L * cos(alpha) * L * sin(alpha) * w * rho * g, where 'L' is length of plat, 'w' is width of plate, 'rho' is density of the fluid, and 'g' is acceleration due to gravity.",
      "reference": ""
    },
    {
      "question": "Calculate the mass flow rate through a convergent nozzle given an inlet stagnation pressure of 1 bar, an inlet stagnation temperature of 300K, a fluid (air) with an isobaric specific heat capacity of 1005 J/kgK, a flow velocity of at Mach 1.5, and a cross section nozzle area of 3 m^2. Assume gamma to be 1.4.",
      "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n    \np0 = 1 # Inlet stagnation pressure (bar)\nT0 = 300 # Inlet stagnation temperature (K)\ncp = 1005 # Isobaric specific heat capacity (J/kgK)\nM = 1.5 # Mach number\ngamma = 1.4 # Heat capacity ratio\nA = 3 # Area (m^2)\n    \n# Convert inlet stagnation pressure from units of bar to Pascal\np0 = 100000 * p0\n    \n# Determine the flow capacity (non-dimensional mass flow)\nfmdot = (gamma / np.sqrt(gamma - 1)) * M * ((1 + (((gamma - 1) / 2) * (M**2)))**(-0.5 * (gamma + 1) / (gamma - 1)))\n    \n# Based on the flow capacity, determine the mass flow rate\nmdot = fmdot * A * p0 / np.sqrt(cp * T0)\n    \nprint('The mass flow rate is:', mdot, 'kg/s')\n",
      "explanation": "This code determines the flow capacity using the following formula (gamma/sqrt(gamma-1))*M*((1+(((gamma-1)/2)* (M^2)))^(-0.5*(gamma+1)/(gamma-1))), where 'M' represents Mach number and 'gamma' represents heat capacity ratio respectively. Then it calculates the mass flow rate based on the determined flow capacity, recognizing that flow capacity is equal to mdot*sqrt(cp*T0)/(A*p0), where 'mdot' is mass flow rate, 'cp' is isobaric specific heat capacity, 'T0' is inlet stagnation temperature, 'A' is area, and 'p0' is inlet stagnation pressure, respectively.",
      "reference": ""
    },
    {
      "question": "A compressible, viscous flow enters a 4 meter diameter pipe at a mach number of 3. The skin friction coefficient is 0.002. What is the length of pipe necessary to choke the flow?",
      "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n    \nD = 4 # Diameter (m)\nM = 3 # Mach number\ngamma = 1.4 # Heat capacity ratio\ncf = 0.002 # Skin Friction coefficient\n    \n# Determine Lmax\nLmax = (D/(4 * cf)) * (((1 - (M ** 2))/(gamma * (M ** 2)))+(((gamma + 1)/(2 * gamma)) * np.log((((gamma + 1)/2) * (M ** 2))/(1 + (((gamma - 1)/2) * (M ** 2))))))\n    \nprint('The length of pipe necessary to choke the flow is:', Lmax, 'm')\n",
      "explanation": "This code uses the formula relating Mach number to 4 * cf * Lmax / D (where 'cf' is skin friction coefficient, 'Lmax' is length from input Mach number required to choke the flow, and 'D' is pipe diameter, respectively) to determine Lmax.",
      "reference": ""
    },
    {
      "question": "A fluid (water) with a constant density of 999 kg/m^3 flows steadily through a pipe. The initial height is 10 m greater than the final height, and the initial velocity is 5 m/s. There is no pressure change, and acceleration due to gravity can be assumed to be 9.81 m/s^2. Assume not flow friction or viscous effects. What is the velocity at the final condition?",
      "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n    \nrho = 999 # Density (kg/m^3)\ndelta_z = 10 # Change in height (z) between the initial and final condition (m)\nv1 = 5 # Initial Velocity (m/s)\ndelta_p = 0 # Change in pressue (p) between the initial and final condition (Pa)\ng = 9.81 # Acceleration due to gravity (m/s^2)\n    \n# Apply Bernoulli's principle\nv2 = np.sqrt(2 * (delta_p + (rho * g * delta_z) + (0.5 * rho * (v1**2)))/rho)\n    \nprint('The velocity at the final condition is:', v2, 'm/s')\n",
      "explanation": "This code applies Bernoulli's equation, which states that p + (rho * g * z) + (0.5 * rho * v^2) = constant, where 'p' is pressure, 'rho' is density, 'g' is acceleration due to gravity, and 'v' is velocity, respectively, to determine the final velocity in the pipe. Bernoulli's equation can be validly applied because the flow is steady, incompressible and inviscid.",
      "reference": "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernoullis_principle"
    },
    {
      "question": "Calculate the momentum flux of a fluid with density 400 kg/m^3 flowing through a pipe with velocity profile v(r) = V0 * (1 - (2 * (r/R)^3))  where the pipe radius R = 2 m, and the center line velocity V0 = 1 m/s.",
      "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n    \nrho = 400 # density (kg/m^2)\nR = 2 # pipe radius (m)\nV0 = 1 # center line velocity (m/s)\n    \n# Apply momentum flux equation\nmdot_v = (2/5) * np.pi * rho * (V0 ** 2) * (R ** 2)\n    \nprint('The momentum flux is:'', mdot_v, 'N')\n",
      "explanation": "This code evaluates the integral of rho * v(r)^2 * 2pi * r dr from 0 to R in order to determine the momentum flux, where 'rho' is density, 'v(r)' is the velocity profile specified in the question, and 'R' is the pipe radius.",
      "reference": ""
    },
    {
      "question": "Plot a graph of area over throat area vs. Mach number for Mach numbers 0.1 to 3 where heat capacity ratio gamma is 1.4.",
      "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\nimport matplotlib.pyplot as plt\n    \ngamma = 1.4 # Heat capacity ratio\nM = np.linspace(0.1,3,100) # Mach number\nAoverAstar = (((gamma + 1)/2) ** (- (gamma + 1)/(2 * (gamma - 1)))) * (((1 + (((gamma - 1)/2) * (M ** 2))) ** ((gamma + 1)/(2 * (gamma - 1))))/M)\n    \nplt.plot(AoverAstar,M)\nplt.xlabel('A/A*')\nplt.ylabel('M')\nplt.show()\n",
      "explanation": "This code uses the relationship between area over throat area and Mach number to generate the desired graph.",
      "reference": ""
    },
    {
      "question": "Plot a graph of dimensionless impulse function (F / mdot*sqrt(cp*T0)) for Mach numbers 0.5 to 10 where heat capacity ratio gamma is 1.4.",
      "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\nimport matplotlib.pyplot as plt\n    \ngamma = 1.4 # Heat capacity ratio\nM = np.linspace(0.5,10,100) # Mach number\n    \ndimensionless_impulse_function=(((1 + (((gamma - 1)/2) * (M**2)))**(gamma/(gamma - 1))) ** (-1)) * (((gamma / np.sqrt(gamma - 1)) * M * ((1 + (((gamma - 1)/2) * (M**2)))**(-0.5 * (gamma + 1)/(gamma - 1))))**(-1)) * (1 + (gamma * (M ** 2)))\n    \nplt.plot(M, dimensionless_impulse_function)\nplt.show()\n",
      "explanation": "This code uses the relationship between dimensionless impulse function and Mach number to generate the desired graph.",
      "reference": ""
    },
    {
      "question": "Given a constant initial temperature T1 = 290 K, graph the resulting stagnation temperature for Mach numbers 0.5 through 5. It may be assumed that the heat capacity ratio gamma is 1.4.",
      "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\nimport matplotlib.pyplot as plt\n    \ngamma = 1.4 # Heat capacity ratio\nM = np.linspace(0.5,10,100) # Mach number\nT1 = 290 # Initial temperature (K)\n    \nT01 = T1 * (1 + (((gamma - 1)/2) * (M ** 2)))\n    \nplt.plot(M, T01)\nplt.show()\n",
      "explanation":  "This code uses the relationship between the ratio of stagnation temp (T01) over temperature (T1) and Mach number (M) to produce the desired graph.",
      "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "A piston/cylinder system containing 1 kg of “laughing gas” (nitrous oxide, N2O), is initially at 298 K and 1.00 bar. The system then goes through a process where heat transfer adds 101 kJ to the gas, and simultaneously the piston is moved in such a way that the product of pressure and volume in the cylinder is unchanged – in other words pV is constant during the heat addition. After the process has ended, the pressure of the N2O in the cylinder is 0.130 bar. N2O has a molecular weight of 44. What is the entropy change of the gas due to this process?",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nR = 8314 / 44 #converting gas constant\nP2 = 0.13 #final pressure (bar)\nP1 = 1 #initial pressure (bar)\n\n#solve for entropy\ns = -R * (np.log(P2/P1))\n\n\nprint('Change in entropy:', s, 'J/kgK')\n        ",
        "explanation": "For an ideal gas, pV = mRT. Because pV is constant, then mRT is also constant, so T1 = T2. Then, use entropy change equation to solve for the change in entropy.",
        "reference": "Frank White (2002) Fluid Mechanics"
    },
    {
        "question": "A low speed, open-return wind tunnel is being designed with a fan at the inlet, and a test section having a rectangular cross-section of 40in. x 42in. The designers want to achieve a 55 mph wind speed, with the air in the test-section nominally at 72ºF and 0.95 atm. How much air (mass flow rate) will the fan that runs the wind tunnel have to supply to meet these conditions?",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nP = 0.95 #pressure of test (atm)\nR = 0.73024 #gas constant (in ft per mol)\nT = (72 - 32) * (5/9) + 273.15 #temperature converting to (K)\nV = 55 * (88/60) #velocity (ft/s)\nA = 40 * 42 * (1/144) #area converting to (ft^2)\n\n#apply mass flow rate equation\nm = (P/(R*T)) * V * A\n\nprint('The mass flow rate:', m, 'lb/s')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code assumes we have an ideal gas and steady and uniform flow to find how much air the fan will have to supply",
        "reference": "Frank White (2002) Fluid Mechanics"
    },
    {
        "question": "A turbine produces shaft power from a gas that enters the turbine with a (static) temperature of 628 K, a velocity of 139 m/s and a stagnation pressure of 14 atm. The gas exits the turbine with a stagnation temperature of 275 K and a stagnation pressure of 0.95 atm. The gas passing through the turbine has a molecular weight of 16 and a specific heat ratio of 1.45. What is the stagnation temperature of the gas entering the turbine?",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nT1 = 628 #static temperature (K)\nV = 139 #velocity (m/s)\ng = 1/45 #gamma\nR = 8314 / 16 #gas constant (J/kgK)\n\n#apply stagnation temperature equation and Cp equation\nCp = ((g) / (g-1)) * R\nT01 = T1 + (V^2)/(2 * Cp)\n\nprint('The stagnation temperature is:', T01, 'K')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code assumes steady flow and adiabatic to solve for the stagnation temperature using static temperature, velocity, and Cp",
        "reference": "Frank White (2002) Fluid Mechanics"
    },
    {
        "question": "If there is an isentropic flow flowing at a speed of 1200 m/s at sea level, what is the stagnation temperature? Stagnation pressure?",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\ng = 1.4 #gamma\nV = 1200 #velocity (m/s)\nR = 287 #gas constant (J/kgK)\nT = 300 #temperature (K)\nP = 101325 #pressure (Pa)\n\n#apply temperature ratio equation\nTratio = 1 + ((g-1)/2) * ((V^2) / (g*R*T))\n\n#solve for stagnation temperature \nT0 = Tratio * T\n\n#apply pressure ratio equation\nPratio = (Tratio)**(g/(g-1))\n\n#solve for stagnation pressure\nP0 = Pratio * P\n\nprint('Stagnation temperature:', T0, 'K')\nprint('Stagnation pressure:', P0, 'Pa')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code applies the temperature and pressure ratio equations in order to find stagnation temperature and stagnation pressure.",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider a flow with a pressure and temperature of 1 atm and 288K. A pitot tube is inserted into this flow and measures a pressure of 1.555 atm. What is the velocity of the flow",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\n#determine subsonic or supersonic\nPratio = 1/0.528 #for sonic flow which is higher than the pressure given\n#flow is subsonic\n\nPratio2 = 1.555 #pressure ratio (atm)\nM = 0.82 #mach number found from subsonic flow table\ng = 1.4 #gamma\nR = 287 #gas constant\nT = 288 #temperature (K)\n\n#solve for speed of sound\na = np.sqrt(g * R * T)\n\n#solve for velocity\nV = M * a\n\nprint('Velocity of the flow:', V, 'm/s')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code initially determines if the flow is subsonic or supersonic by comparing the pressure ratio. Then, once decided that the flow is subsonic, the code solves for the speed of sound in order to find velocity.",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "Air is flowing through a round tube of 650mm diameter. The initial pressure of the tube is 50kPa and the initial Temperature is 200K. The temperature of the air at the exit of the tube is 320K. The mass flow rate of the tube is 5kg/s. The flow has sped up to twice it’s speed. Find initial velocity (V1), final pressure (P2), and final area (A2).",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nP1 = 50000 #pressure (Pa)\nR = 8.314 / 28 #converting gas constant\nT1 = 200 #temperature (K)\nT2 = 320 #final temperature  (K)\nmDot = 5 #mass flow rate (kg/s)\nA1 = (np.pi * (0.65**2)) / 4 #area (m)\n\n#solve for density\ndensity1 = P1 / (R*T1) #(kg/m^3)\n\n#use density to solve for velocity\nV1 = mDot / (density1 * A1) #(m/s)\n\n#solve for density2 to help find P2\n#mass flow in = mass flow out\n#(density1)(V1)(A) = (density2)(V2)(A)\ndensity2 = density1 / 2 #(kg/m^3)\n\n#solve for P2\nP2 = (density2)*(R)*(T2) #(kPa)\n\n#solve for A2\n#(density1)(V)(A1) = (density2)(V)(A2)\nA2 = ((density1)*(A1)) / density2 #(m^2)\n\n\nprint('Initial Velocity:', V1, 'm/s')\nprint('Final Pressure:', P2, 'kPa')\nprint('Final area', A2, 'm^2')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code assumes ideal gas and steady and uniform flow and uses the mass flow rate equation (mDot = (density)(V)(A)) and mass flow in = mass flow out to solve for V, P, and A.",
        "reference": "Frank White (2002) Fluid Mechanics"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider airflow over a 22.5 degree half-angle wedge. If M1=2.5, P1=1 atm, T1=300 K, and wave angle is 46 degrees, calculate P2, T2, and M2.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nM1 = 2.5 #mach 1\nbeta = 46 #wave angle (degrees)\nP1 = 1 #pressure (atm)\nT1 = 300 #temperature (K)\ntheta = 22.5 #half angle wedge (degrees)\n\n#solve for Mn1\nMn1 = M1 * (np.sin(beta))\n\n#use oblique shock table to find pressure ratio, temperature ratio, and Mn2\nPratio = 3.613\nTratio  = 1.531\nMn2 = 0.6165\n\n#solve for P2 from Pratio\nP2 = Pratio * P1\n\n#solve for T2 from Tratio\nT2 = Tratio * T1\n\n#solve for M2\nM2 = Mn2 / (np.sin(beta - theta))\n\n\nprint('Outlet mach number:', M2)\nprint ('Final pressure:', P2, 'atm')\nprint ('Final temperature:', T2, 'K')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code use the oblique shock table to try and find the final pressure, temperature, and mach number of an oblique shock.",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why does stagnation pressure decrease but static pressure increases across a shock?",
        "answer": "A shock is a compression wave which increases static pressure. However, the velocity decreases so much across a shock that the dynamic pressure drop causes the stagnation pressure to drop.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "What is A* and why does it change across a shock?",
        "answer": "A* is the area you would need to get the flow choked. A* changes across a shock because the stagnation pressure drops as well.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "Which equations for conservation of momentum has the most assumptions and what are they??",
        "answer": "Bernoulli’s equation is the conservation of momentum equation with the most assumptions: steady, inviscid, no body forces, on streamline, incompressible.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "How do bow shocks occur?",
        "answer": "When the turn angle of the flow exceeds the maximum turn angle, we get detached shocks",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "The first law of thermodynamics and the conservation of energy are  related. How do they differ in the types of energy considered?",
        "answer": "The first law of thermodynamics states that heat is supplied to the system (Q) causing change in internal energy of the system (delta U) and the system can do some work (W). Q = delta U + W. The first law also looks at heat transfers, work done, and changes in internal energy. However, conservation of energy looks at all forms of energy (i.e. potential, kinetic, chemical, etc.).",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "How do heat transfer and internal energy differ? In particular, which can be stored as such in a system and which cannot?",
        "answer": "Heat transfer is when heat energy is transferred from one system to another due to a temperature difference. The total energy is the the sum of kinetic and potential energy. Heat transfer cannot be stored like internal energy can be stored.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why, in terms of the first law of thermodynamics, does the temperature of a rapidly expanding gas decrease?",
        "answer": "As the gas expands rapidly, the system does not have enough time to interact with its surroundings, so heat does not flow from its surroundings to the system. Therefore, heat (Q) = 0, and the final internal energy is less than the initial because internal energy of the system is directly proportional to the temperature.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why is change in entropy important?",
        "answer": "It is important because it shows what happened in the process. A positive change in entropy means either entropy was produced or there was heat transfer to the system. A negative change in entropy means entropy was transferred out of the system. No change in entropy means the process was isentropic, reversible, and adiabatic.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "How is it unlikely that a process can be isothermal unless it is a very slow process. Is it the same for isobaric and isochoric processes?",
        "answer": "A isothermal process must be slow so that heat is transferred and the temperature does  not change. For isobaric and isochoric process, the system must be in thermal equilibrium with slow variations.",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "A pilot flying a mission over Germany in a Supermarine Spitfire has to manually convert the pressure measured by the pitot tube to velocity, as the transducer is broken. He is flying at an altitude of 15,000 feet and reads a pressure of 66.538 kPa. 2 Bf-109’s are quickly closing in and he needs to know if he has sufficient velocity to perform a special manoeuvre. What is the Spitfire’s velocity?",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nps = 57.157 # Pressure at 15000 feet (kPa)\np0 = 66.538 # Measured pressure (kPa)\nrho = 0.771 # Air density at 15000 feet (kg / m^3)\n      \n# Static, Dynamic, and Stagnation pressures relationship\n# ps + (1/2) * rho * v^2 = p0\n\n# Solve for v\nv = ((2*(p0 - ps)*1000) / rho)**(1/2)\n\nprint('Spitfire's velocity:', v, 'm/s')\n",
        "explanation": "This code utilizes the relationship between the dynamic, static, and total/stagnation pressures. The equation ps + (1/2) * rho * v^2 = p0 expresses this. It is important to understand that the pressure measured by the pitot tube is the stagnation pressure, as it measures the pressure of the fluid when it is brought to rest.",
        "reference": "Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, 5th Edition, John D. Anderson, Jr"
      },
      {
          "question": "Air enters a compressor at with zero velocity and leaves with a mass flow rate of 9 kg/s and velocity of 25 m/s. The power input to the compressor is 450 kW. The air flowing into the compressor has a temperature of 280 K, and the air flowing out has a temperature of 300 K. We may assume the flow is steady and a cp of 1005 J/kg-K. Find the rate of heat transfer.",
          "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nTi = 280 # Temperature before entering the compressor (K)\nTe = 300 # Temperature after exiting the compressor (K)\nWdot = -45000 # Power input (W)\nmdot = 9 # Mass flow rate (kg/s)\nve = 25 # Exit velocity (m/s)\ncp = 1005 # Specific heat capacity at constant pressure (J/kg-K)\n      \n# Steady Flow Energy Equation reduces to: Qdot - Wdot = mdot * ((1/2) * ve ** 2) + (he -    hi)\n\n# With:\ndeltah = cp * (Te - Ti)\n\n# We arrive at:\n\nQdot = Wdot + mdot * ((1/2) * (ve ** 2)) + (deltah)\n\nprint('Rate of heat transfer:', Qdot, 'J/s')\n",
          "explanation": "This code calculates the rate of heat transfer using the Steady Flow Energy Equation, which states that Qdot - Wdot = mdot * ((he + (1/2) * ve ** 2 + (g * ze) - (hi + (1/2) * vi ** 2 + (g * zi)).",
          "reference": "Introduction to Fluid Mechanics, 6th Edition, R. Fox, A. McDonald, P. Pritchard"
      },
      {
          "question": "During the hot summer in Atlanta, in order to cool a bottle of water, it is placed in a freezer for a certain period. If the room temperature is 25°C and the cooled beverage is at a final temperature of 5°C, determine the change in specific entropy of the water.",
          "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nT1 = 25 + 273.15 # Initial temperature (K)\nT2 = 5 + 273.15 # Final temperature (K)\ncp = 4.18 # Water specific heat capacity at constant pressure (J/(g-K))\n\n# Apply the perfect gas relations to the Tds equations\n\ndeltas = cp * np.log(T2 / T1)\n\nprint('Change in specific entropy:', deltas, 'kJ/kg-K')\n",
          "explanation": "This code calculates the change in specific entropy, utilizing the perfect gas relations and the Tds equations which yield s2 - s1 = cp * ln(T2 / T1), where s2 - s1 is the change in specific entropy between the initial and final states.",
          "reference": "Introduction to Fluid Mechanics, 6th Edition, R. Fox, A. McDonald, P. Pritchard"
      },
      {
          "question": "Water flows through a pipe with different inlet and outlet areas. The velocity at the inlet is 2 m/s and the velocity at the exit is 6 m/s. The pressure at the inlet is 120 kPa. If the water enters and exits the pipe at the same height, and it can be assumed to have steady, incompressible, and inviscid flow, what is the pressure at the outlet?",
          "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nv1 = 2 # Inlet velocity (m/s)\nv2 = 6 # Outlet velocity (m/s)\np1 = 120000 # Pressure at inlet (Pa)\nrho = 1000 # Water density (kg/m^3)\n\n# Apply Bernoulli’s equation along streamlines\n\n# p1 + (1/2)*rho*(v1**2) = p2 + (1/2)*rho*(v2**2)\n\n# Solve for p2\n\np2 = p1 + (1/2)*rho*((v1**2)-(v2**2))\n\nprint('Pressure at outlet:', p2, 'Pa')\n",
            "explanation": "This code utilises Bernoulli’s equation along streamlines for steady, incompressible and inviscid flow to calculate the pressure at the outlet of the pipe.",
            "reference": "Introduction to Fluid Mechanics, 6th Edition, R. Fox, A. McDonald, P. Pritchard"
      },
      {
          "question": "A British Airways Concorde is flying at 417 m/s over the Atlantic Ocean, on its way to JFK from LHR. If the outdoor temperature is 220 K, what is the Mach number?",
          "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nv = 417 # Velocity (m/s)\ngamma = 1.4 # Ratio of specific heats, cp/cv\nT = 220 # Temperature (K)\nR = 287 # Gas constant (J/kg-K)\n\n# Using the definition of the Mach number\n\n# M = v/a\n\n# And the definition of the speed of the speed of sound\n\n# a = np.sqrt(gamma*R*T)\n\nM = v/(np.sqrt(gamma*R*T))\n\nprint('Concorde’s Mach number:', M)\n",
          "explanation": "This code utilises the definitions for the Mach number and speed of sound to calculate the Mach number of the Concorde.",
          "reference": "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stagnation_pressure , Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, 5th Edition, John D. Anderson, Jr"
      },
      {
          "question": "A Boeing 747 is cruising at an altitude of 35000 feet at a speed of 550 mph. The external temperature is 220 K. When looking at a streamline that flows up to the 747’s nose, what is the stagnation temperature? Assume a steady, isentropic process with no external work done.",
          "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nv = 245.9 # Velocity (m/s)\ncp = 1005 # (J/kg-K)\nT1 = 220 # Temperature (K)\n\n# Using the definition of the stagnation temperature.\n\nT01 = T1 + (v**2)/(2*cp)\n\nprint('Stagnation temperature on nose of 747:', T01, 'K')\n",
          "explanation": "This code utilizes the definition of the stagnation temperature for a fluid if it were to be brought to rest by a steady isentropic process with no external work.",
          "reference": "https://psesh.github.io/ae2010-11/"
      },
      {
          "question": "An F-15 Eagle is flying at a speed of 1500 mph over the Mojave desert. What is the Mach angle, mu, of the generated wave? If the wave were to hit a concave corner, what can be said about the pre-shock and post-shock tangential velocity components?",
          "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nv = 670.6 # Velocity (m/s)\na = 328.4 # Speed of sound at altitude (m/s)\n\n# Calculate the Mach number\n\nM = v/a\n\n# Using the formula for the Mach angle\n\nmu = np.arcsin(1/M)\n\n# The pre- and post-shock tangential velocities are the same.\n\nprint('Mach angle:', mu)\nprint('The tangential velocity components do no change across the shock.')\n",
          "explanation": "This code utilizes the definitions of the Mach number and Mach angle to calculate the Mach angle.",
          "reference": "https://psesh.github.io/ae2010-11/"
      },
      {
          "question": "A cyclic heat engine operates a process between a heat source of 900 K and a heat sink of certain temperature. If the cycle is reversible, and the thermal efficiency is 45%, what is the heat sink temperature?",
          "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nT1 = 900 # Temperature (K)\neff = 0.4 # Thermal efficiency\n\n# Thermal efficiency equation (1st Law applied to Heat Engines)\n\n# eff = 1 - (T2/T1)\n\n# Solve for T2\n\nT2 = (1 - eff)*T1\n\nprint('Heat sink temperature:', T2, 'K')\n",
          "explanation": "This code calculates the heat sink temperature using the formula for thermal efficiency, which is derived from the First Law, which states that W = Qhot - Qcold.",
          "reference": "https://psesh.github.io/ae2010-11/"
      },
      {
          "question": "Water is flowing through a pipe with a constant bulk velocity and zero mean acceleration. If the cross-sectional diameter is 0.8 m, the mass flow rate is 750 kg/s, and water has a density of 1000 kg/m^3, what is the pressure drop over a length of 20 m? Assume a dynamic viscosity of 8.90 * 10^-4 Pa-s.",
          "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nmdot = 750 # Mass flow rate (kg/s)\nrho = 1000 # Water density (kg/m^3)\nD = 0.8 # Diameter (m)\nL = 20 # Length (m)\nmu = 8.90 * 10**(-4) # Dynamic viscosity of water (Pa-s)\n\n# Find volumetric flow rate\n\nQ = mdot / rho\n\n# Radius = Diameter/2\n\n# Hagen-Poiseuille Equation\n\ndeltap = (8 * mu * Q * L)/(np.pi * (D/4)**4)\n\n\nprint('Pressure drop over 10 meters:', deltap, 'Pa')\n",
          "explanation": "This code calculates the pressure drop using the Hagen-Poiseuille equation, which describes situations where the pressure loss can be directly related to the friction force by the walls.",
          "reference": "https://psesh.github.io/ae2010-11/"
      },
      {
          "question": "Extra credit. Plot a cycle. A certain mass of air undergoes 3 different processes in the cycle. 1. Isobaric expansion to double the volume. 2. Isochoric cooling. 3. Isothermal compression to the initial state. You may choose arbitrary values for the temperature and mass, but the graph shape and therefore relationships between variables must be correct.",
          "answer": "\nimport matplotlib.pyplot as plt\nimport numpy as np\n\nR = 8.314\nm = 1.0\nT1 = 300.0\n\n# Process 1: Isobaric expansion\n\nV1 = 1.0\nV2 = 2.0 * V1\nP1 = R * T1 / V1\nP2 = P1\nworkexp = P1 * (V2 - V1)\n\n# Process 3: Isothermal compression\n\nV3 = np.linspace(V2, V1, 100)\nP4 = R * T1 / V3\nworkcomp = np.trapz(P4, V3)\n\n# Process 2: Isochoric cooling\n\nT2 = 200.0\nindex = np.where(np.isclose(V3, V2))[0][0]\nP3 = P4[index]\n\n# Total work done\n\ntotal_work = workexp + workcomp\n\n# Plot diagram\n\nplt.plot([V1, V2, V1], [P1, P2, P1], label='Process 1')\nplt.plot([V2, V2], [P1, P3], linestyle='--', color='red', label='Process 2')\nplt.plot(V3, P4, label='Process 3')\nplt.xlabel('Volume (m^3)')\nplt.ylabel('Pressure (Pa)')\nplt.title('p-v Diagram')\nplt.xticks([])\nplt.yticks([])\nplt.legend()\nplt.grid(False)\nplt.show()\n",
          "explanation": "This code plots a p-v diagram showing the cycle consisting of 3 processes. It is based off of linear relationships for Processes 1 and 2, and an inverse relationship for Process 3.",
          "reference": "https://psesh.github.io/ae2010-11/ , https://www.khanacademy.org/science/physics/thermodynamics/laws-of-thermodynamics/a/what-are-pv-diagrams"
      },
      {
        "question": "What exactly is shaft work and how does one identify it?",
        "answer": "Shaft work refers to the work done by a rotating shaft or a similar mechanical device on a system, or the work done by the system on the surroundings through a rotating shaft. It can be identified by considering the mechanical energy exchanged between the system and its surroundings due to the rotation of a shaft. If a system involves rotating machinery or if there's mechanical motion involved in the system's operation, one may have to consider shaft work.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "https://psesh.github.io/ae2010-11/ , https://www.sciencedirect.com/topics/engineering/shaft-work ,https://chem.libretexts.org/Bookshelves/Physical_and_Theoretical_Chemistry_Textbook_Maps/DeVoes_Thermodynamics_and_Chemistry/03%3A_The_First_Law/3.07%3A_Shaft_Work"
      },
      {
        "question": "It is stated that for an irreversible process, one cannot set dW = pdV and dQ = TdS. How does one distinguish between a reversible and irreversible process?",
        "answer": "If a process occurs quasi-statically – that is, it passes through a continuous sequence of thermodynamic equilibrium states – it is reversible. If a process involves taking a specific path that cannot be retraced, it is irreversible. Reversible processes follow a well-defined and retraceable path between the initial and final states. If a process produces entropy between the initial and final states, it is irreversible. If a process involves dissipative effects such as friction, it is irreversible. These lead to energy losses and irreversibilities within the system.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "https://psesh.github.io/ae2010-11/ , https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irreversible_process"
      },
      {
        "question": "When a supersonic aircraft travels at high speeds, the air entering the engine's inlet experiences a rapid change in pressure and velocity. The airflow ahead of the engine is compressed due to the shockwaves generated by the aircraft's forward motion. If, in this compression process, the airflow experiences a rapid change in pressure and velocity without significant heat exchange with the surroundings, is the process adiabatic or not? Why?",
        "answer": "This process can be considered adiabatic. By definition, adiabatic processes are characterized by the absence of heat transfer into or out of the system. If the compression occurs sufficiently rapidly that there is not have enough time for significant heat exchange between the air and the surroundings, it is adiabatic.",
        "explanation":"", 
        "reference": "https://psesh.github.io/ae2010-11/ , https://www.britannica.com/technology/jet-engine/Ramjets-and-supersonic-combustion-ramjets"
      },
      {
        "question": "What differentiates the Lagrangian and Eulerian descriptions and how is this applied to flow mechanics?",
        "answer": "The Lagrangian description tracks the motion of individual fluid particles. Each particle is assigned a trajectory and describes its motion in terms of position as a function of time. It is useful when applied to highly unsteady or transient flows, such as turbulent flows. The Euelerian description tracks fixed points in space and their flow properties, such as the velocity, pressure and density. It is used to analyze steady flows, focusing on the overall behavior of the flow.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "https://psesh.github.io/ae2010-11/ ,https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lagrangian_and_Eulerian_specification_of_the_flow_field , https://web.mit.edu/fluids-modules/www/basic_laws/1-1-LagEul.pdf"
      },
      {
        "question": "What differentiates Couette and Poiseuille flow and how do favorable and unfavorable pressure gradients relate to these?",
        "answer": "Couette and Poiseuille flow are two distinct types of viscous flow. Couette flow occurs between two parallel plates, with one stationary and the other moving at a constant velocity, whereas Poiseuille flow occurs in a long, straight pipe with constant cross-sectional area, where a pressure difference is applied along the length of the pipe. It is also important to note that in Couette flow, the velocity gradient arises due to the relative motion of the plates, creating a shearing motion within the fluid. The velocity profile in Couette flow is linear, with the velocity increasing linearly from zero at the stationary plate to a maximum value at the moving plate. In Poiseuille flow, the pressure difference drives the flow, moving from high to low pressure. The velocity profile in Poiseuille flow is parabolic, with the maximum velocity occurring at the centerline of the pipe and decreasing towards the walls. In a favorable pressure gradient, the pressure decreases in the direction of flow, meaning that fluid increases in velocity along the flow direction. In an adverse pressure gradient, the pressure increases in the direction of flow, so the fluid decreases in velocity along the flow direction.",
        "explanation":"", 
        "reference": "https://psesh.github.io/ae2010-11/ , https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/2-25-advanced-fluid-mechanics-fall-2013/1a114d602956fa0dd328155f9b45f93d_MIT2_25F13_Couet_and_Pois.pdf ,https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Couette_flow"
      },
      {
        "question": "How does one distinguish between the static, stagnation, and total pressure, and what equations can be used to calculate them?",
        "answer": "The static pressure, p, can be described as the actual pressure at any given point in the flow. It represents the pressure that a fluid exerts perpendicular to any surface when the fluid is not in motion relative to the surface. It is the pressure that one would measure with a sensor at a fixed point in the flow, without altering its velocity. The stagnation pressure, p0, can be described as the pressure a fluid would have if it were brought to rest. In other words, it is the static pressure at a stagnation point – where the local velocity of the fluid is zero. It can be calculated using the following equation, which sums the free-stream static and dynamic pressures: p0 = p + (1/2)*rho*v^2. The total pressure, pt, sometimes used interchangeably with the stagnation pressure, differentiates itself from the stagnation pressure in situations where the effects of gravity need to be taken into consideration. It can be calculated using the following equation: p + (1/2)*rho*v^2 + rho*g*h.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "https://psesh.github.io/ae2010-11/ ,https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stagnation_pressure ,https://www.aft.com/learning-center-2/application-topics/692-stagnation-vs-static-pressure"
      },
      {
        "question": "In a converging-diverging nozzle, what happens to the flow depending on whether the flow is subsonic or supersonic, and how does exit static pressure affect the flow behavior?",
        "answer": "If the flow entering the nozzle is subsonic, the flow velocity will increase and static pressure decrease in the converging section, and the flow velocity will decrease and static pressure increase in the diverging section. If the flow entering the nozzle is supersonic, it behaves in the opposite way. The flow velocity will decrease and static pressure increase in the converging section, and the flow velocity will increase and static pressure decrease in the diverging section. Regarding shocks, if the flow remains supersonic through the nozzle and a shock develops in the diverging section, decreasing the exit static pressure decreases the pressure ratio across the shock, causing the shock to move downstream through the nozzle. In certain extreme cases when the exit static pressure is sufficiently reduced, the shock can even leave the exit of the nozzle.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "https://psesh.github.io/ae2010-11/"
      },
      {
        "question": "How do pitot tubes measure fluid velocity?",
        "answer": "Pitot tubes don't actually measure the velocity of a fluid, rather the differences in pressure. A hole head-on to the flow measures the stagnation pressure (when velocity is zero) while the smaller tubes on the sides measure static pressure. By utilizing Bernoulli's equation where velocity on one side is zero, stagnation pressure is equal to static pressure plus dynamic pressure--which is (1/2)rho*v^2 where rho is density and v is velocity. Using the measured pressures from the pitot tube, one can either use a computer or manually solve for velocity.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "[https://www.grc.nasa.gov/www/k-12/VirtualAero/BottleRocket/airplane/pitot.html]"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why is the minimum pressure at the center of curvature for curved streamlines?",
        "answer": "The pressure is minimized at the center of pressure in short due to Newton's second law and a modified application of Bernoulli's equation along curved streamlines. Along curves, normal acceleration must be balanced by a normal pressure force. To stay along the curve, there must be a centripetal acceleration caused by a pressure gradient acting normal to the streamlines. Mathematically, this can be noted by integrating dp/dn = p(V^2/R) and realizing that p is at its minimum when the distance from R is minimized.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "[https://web.mit.edu/hml/ncfmf/06PFFA.pdf]"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the difference between divergence and advection?",
        "answer": "Divergence essentially measures the change of a vector field (commonly velocity). It can dictate if a flow sources or sinks with respect to a specific point. Advection  is defined as 'Advection is defined as the exchange of energy, moisture, or momentum as a result of horizontal heterogeneity.' It is important to note that while this is the definition of advection, the operator is used in this course and can be generalized. It is more similar to divergence, but gives the variation of some other variable as velocity (or some other rate of change) changes across a vector field. Mathematically, divergence is simply the derivatives of the 3D components of velocity. The advection operator multiplies the components of velocity (or some other variable) by the derivative of some other variable with respect to space.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "[https://www.sciencedirect.com/topics/earth-and-planetary-sciences/advection]"
    },
    {
        "question": "Why can some processes be treated as adiabatic and why is this important?",
        "answer": "An adiabatic process is one in which no heat transfer occurs. As heat transfer takes time, processes that occur very rapidly may not be able to transfer heat. Because of this and the first law, change in internal energy can be set equal to the negative work done on the system and therefore the net work done can be considered independent of the path taken.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why is the efficiency of a heat engine maximimum when the process is reversible?",
        "answer": "A reversible heat engine is more efficient essentially due to the second law of thermodynamics. Reversible processes can be returned to their original state and can do so with no change in entropy, while irreversibilities occur with an increase in entropy. Irreversibilities occur for a multitude of reasons, but result in 'lost work' that makes the process less efficient. For example, energy lost from friction cannot be regained and used as energy in the system.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": ["https://web.mit.edu/16.unified/www/FALL/thermodynamics/notes/node48.html"]
    },
    {
        "question": "Why can't irreversible processes be plotted on p-V diagrams and what is the compromise?",
        "answer": "Many times, reversible processes take place in quasi-equilibrium, so they are able to be graphed according to equilibrium states. Irreversible processes however do not occur where p-V are in equilibrium and therefore cannot be represented with a continuous line. Instead, it is often graphed with a dotted line to indicate a process has taken place from point A to point B, but irreversibly.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why does the entropy of a system approach its maximum as it tends towards equilibrium?",
        "answer": "For an isolated system there is no change in work done as there is nothing to do work or do work on. As dS = dQ/dt + dS(irrev), dS = dS(irrev). So irreversible processes that change entropy are the only processses that can happen to move towards equilibrium. And as dS(irrev) can only be positive or zero, entropy can only keep increasing as it approaches its maximum amount.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "In Fanno flow, how do subsonic and supersonic flow have both similar and opposite behavior?",
        "answer": "The upper (starting subsonic) and lower (starting supersonic) curves cannot be transversed by the same curve. However they both are adiabatic processes and approach a sonic point of maximum entropy where the flow is choked. Similarly, total pressure decreases for both flows, though static increases for supersonic and decreases for subsonic. As for most other properties, they act oppositely. This mostly revolves around their different behaviors as the area effectively decreases due to friction. From standard mass flow rate conventions, subsonic flow speeds up to reach Mach 1 while supersonic slows down as area decreases.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "[https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fanno_flow#:~:text=Fanno%20flow%20is%20the%20adiabatic,also%20applies%20to%20incompressible%20flow.]"
    },
    {
        "question": "How can oblique shocks be treated as normal shocks?",
        "answer": "Oblique shock properties can be calculated like normal shocks simply by tilting the frame of reference so that the shock is perpendicular to the frame. To accomodate this one must calculate the Mach component and use that in the normal shock equations.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "A new radiation heat transfer sensor consists of a small, closed, rigid, insulated 0.0400 m^3 box containing a 0.0100 m^3 rubber balloon. Initially, the box is evacuated but the balloon contains argon (an ideal gas) at 20.0°C and 0.0100 MPa. When the balloon receives 0.100 kJ of radiation energy through an uninsulated window in the box, it bursts. The resulting pressure change is sensed by a transducer and an alarm is sounded. Determine the pressure and temperature inside the box after the balloon bursts. For argon, assume the constant volume is .315 kJ/kgK and the specific gass constant is .208 kJ/kgK.",
        "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\nVb = 0.0100 # balloon volume (m^3)\nVx = 0.0400 # box volume (m^3)\nT1 = 20.0 #initial temperature (C)\np1 = 0.0100 #initial pressure (MPa)\nQ = 0.100 #heat added (kJ)\nR = 0.208 # specific gas constant (kJ/kgK)\ncv = 0.315 # ideal gas constant for constant volume (kJ/kgK)\n\n#first law: Q-W = delta(U)\n#BUT dV is 0 as the gas doesn't face any resistance when expanding so W = int(pdV) = 0 Q = delta(U) = mcv(T2-T1)\n\n#first must calculate m using m = (p1V1)/(RT1)\np1 = p1 * 1000 # convert p to kPa\nm = (p1 * Vb) / (R * (T1 + 273.15))\n# solve for T2 using first law\nT2 = T1 + (Q / (m * cv))\n\n# solve for p2 using pV = mRT\np2 = (m * R * (T2 + 273.15))/(Vx)\n\n\nprint('The final temperature inside the box is', T2, '°C')\nprint('The final pressure inside the box is', p2, 'kPa')\n    ",
        "explanation": "This code uses an version of the first law of thermodynamics in which work is zero as the gas does not face any resistance as it expands into the vaccuum so Q - W = delta(U) [where Q is heat addition, W is work done, and delta(U) is change in internal energy] becomes Q = delta(U). It also takes advantage of the ideal gas law pV = mRT where p is pressure, V is volume, m is mass, R is specific gas constant, and T is temperature. We also assume that the changes in kinetic and potential energy are zero in order to solve the problem.",
        "reference": "Robert T. Balmer (2011) Modern Engineering Thermodynamics, Academic Press."
    },
    {
        "question": "Air is compressed from an initial state of 100 kPa and 17°C to a final state of 600 kPa and 57°C. Determine the entropy change of air during this compression process given cp of air is 1.006 kJ/kgK and R (specific gas constant) is 287 kJ/kgK",
        "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\np1 = 100 # initial pressure (kPa)\nT1 = 17 # initial temperature (C)\np2 = 600 # final pressure (kPa)\nT2 = 57 # final temperature (C)\ncp = 1.006 # given cp for air (kJ/kgK)\nR = 287 # given specific gas constant (J/kgK)\n\n# first be sure to convert temperatures to Kelvin\nT1 = T1 + 273.15\nT2 = T2 + 273.15\n\n# convert R to kJ/kgK\nR = 287 / 1000\n\n# use ideal gas energy equations\ns = cp * np.log(T2/T1) - R * np.log(p2/p1)\n\nprint('The change in entropy due to compression is', s, 'kJ/kgK')\n",
        "explanation": "Air is an ideal gas, so you can use the formula: s2 - s1 = cp * ln(T2/T1) - R * ln(p2/p1) where s2 and s1 represent respective entropies, T2 and T1 represent respective temperatures, and p2 and p1 represent respective pressures.",
        "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
    },
    {
        "question": "A 10-cm fire hose with a 3-cm nozzle discharges 1.5 m^3/min to the atmosphere. Assuming frictionless flow and density is 1000 kg/m^3, find the force exerted by the flange bolts to hold the nozzle on the hose.",
        "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\nD1 = 10 # entrance diameter (cm)\nD2 = 3 # nozzle exit diameter (cm)\nQ = 1.5 # volumetric flow rate (m^3/min)\nrho = 1000 # density (kg/m^3)\n\n# convert Q to m^3/sec\nQ = 1.5 / 60\n\n# convert diameters to meters\nD1 = D1 / 100\nD2 = D2 / 100\n\n# compute areas\nA1 = (np.pi/4) * D1**2\nA2 = (np.pi/4) * D2**2\n\n# use volumetric flow rate equation to find velocities\nv1 = Q / A1\nv2 = Q / A2\n\n# use Bernoulli's to find pressure\np = .5 * rho * (v2**2 - v1**2)\n\n# calculate mass flow rate\nmdot = rho * Q\n\n# use force-momentum equation and solve for force\nF = p * A1 - mdot * (v2-v1)\n\nprint('The force required to hold the nozzle on the hose is', F, 'N')\n",
        "explanation": "This code first utilizes the volumetric flow rate equation Q = Av (Q is volumetric flow rate, A is area, and v is velocity) which can be applied when the fluid is incompressible. Next it uses Bernoulli's equation along streamlines and takes in the exit pressure as 0 as the flow exits into the atmosphere (i.e., the pressure = pa = 0 gage). Bernoulli's equation is p1 = p2 + (1/2)rho(v2^2-v1^2) where p1 and p2 are respective pressures, rho is density, and v2 and v1 are respective pressures. Lastly to find the force one must use the force-momentum equation in which F + p1*A1 - p2*A2 = mdot1*v1 - mdot2*v2 where F is the force, p1 and p2 are pressures, A1 and A2 are areas, mdot1 and mdot2 are mass flow rates, and v1 and v2 are velocities.",
        "reference": "Frank M. White (2016) Fluid Mechanics, McGraw-Hill."
    },
    {
        "question":"A manometer is used to measure the pressure in a tank. The fluid used has a specific gravity of 0.85, and the manometer column height is 55 cm. If the local atmospheric pressure is 96 kPa and the density of water is 1000 kg/m^3 determine both the gauge pressure and the absolute pressure within the tank.",
        "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\nsg = 0.85 # specific gravity of fluid (no units)\nh = 55/100 # manometer column height (m)\npa = 96 # local atmospheric pressure (Pa)\nrhoW = 1000 # density of water (kg/m^3)\n\n# find density of the fluid\nrho = sg * rhoW\n\n# assuming the density of the fluid in the manometer is much higher, gauge pressure is about rho * g * h\ng = 9.81 # gravityy (m/s^2)\npg = (rho * g * h) / 1000 # find in kPa\n\n# add pa to find absolute pressure\npabs = pg + pa\n\nprint('The gauge pressure in the tank is', pg, 'kPa')\nprint('The absolute pressure in the tank is', pabs, 'kPa')\n",
        "explanation": "A manometer uses the known atmospheric pressure to measure another unknown pressure by using gauge pressure. First the code uses the specific gravity (sg) and density of water (rhoW) and the formula sg*rhoW to find the density of the fluid. After pgauge is calculated using rho * g * h where rho is the density of the fluid, g is gravity, and h is the height of the manometer column. Lastly gauge pressure is known to be p - pa so given pa, this compuation is quite simple. Additionally, we must assume that the density of the fluid in the manometer is much higher than the other fluid.",
        "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
    },
    {
        "question": "Air flows adiabatically through a duct. At point 1 the velocity is 240 m/s with T1 = 320 K and p1 = 170 kPa. Compute T0, p0, rho0, and Ma. At some point 2 further downstream v2 = 290 m/s and p2 = 135 kPa. What is the stagnation pressure p02? Assume gamma is 1.4 and cp is 1005 m^2/s^2K.",
        "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\nv1 = 240 # velocity at point 1 (m/s)\nT1 = 320 # temperature at point 1 (K)\np1 = 170 # pressure at point 1 (kPa)\nv2 = 290 # velocity at point 2 (m/s)\np2 = 135 # pressure at point 2\ngamma = 1.4 # ideal gas constant\ncp = 1005 # constant pressure (m^2/s^2K)\nR = 287 # ideal gas constant for air (m^2/s^2K)\n\n# use stagnation temperature formula\nT0 = T1 + (v1**2)/(2*cp)\nprint('The stagnation temperature at point 1 is', T0, 'K')\n\n# use stagnation temperature to find the Mach number\nM = np.sqrt(((T0/T1)-1)*(2/(gamma-1)))\n\n# following, use Mach number to calculate stagnation pressure\np0 = p1 * (1+((gamma-1)/2)*M**2)**(gamma/(gamma-1))\n\n# using ideal gas law, calculate density\nrho = (p0/(R * T0)) * 1000\n\nprint('The stagnation pressure at point 1 is', p0, 'kPa')\nprint('The density at point 1 is', rho, 'kg/m^3')\nprint('The Mach number at point 1 is', M)\n\n# to find the stagnation pressure at point 2 you must first find T2 realizing that T02 = T01 because the flow is adiabatic\nT2 = T0 - (v2**2)/(2*cp)\n\n# then use isentropic relations\np02 = p2 * (T0/T2)**(gamma/(gamma-1))\n\nprint('The isentropic stagnation pressure at point 2 is', p02, 'kPa')\n",
        "explanation": "The stagnation pressure is first found throught the formula T0 = T + (v^2/(2cp)) where T0 is stagnation temperature, T is static temperature, v is velocity, and cp is the molar capacity at constant pressure. Next, Mach number is calculated from the formula T0/T = 1 + ((gamma-1)/2)*M^2 where T0 and T are as previously defined, gamma is cp/cv, and M is the Mach number. Density is calculated through the ideal gas law pV = mRT modified to be rho = p/RT where rho is density, p is pressure, R is the universal gas constant, and T is temperature. Lastly stagnation pressure is calculated in two steps. The first uses the same stagnation temperature formula as prior, and the second uses the isentropic relations where p2/p1 = (T2/T1)^(gamma/(gamma-1)) where all the terms are as previously determined.",
        "reference": "Frank M. White (2016) Fluid Mechanics, McGraw-Hill."
    },
    {
        "question": "A nuclear explosion produces a normal shock wave that travels through still air with a Mach number of 5.50. The pressure and temperature of the air in front of the shock wave are 14.7 psia and 70.0°F. Determine the Mach number, pressure, and temperature behind the shock wave.",
        "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\nM1 = 5.50 # Mach number of the moving shock wave (no units)\np1 = 14.7 # pressure in front of the shock wave (psia)\nT1 = 70.0 # temperature in front of the shock wave (F)\ngamma = 1.4 # gamma factor of air (no units)\n\n# use normal shock relations to find Mach number\nM2 = np.sqrt((1+((gamma-1)/2)*M1**2)/(gamma*M1**2-((gamma-1)/2)))\nprint('The Mach number behind the shock wave is', M2)\n\n# it is important to note that these units are in imperial, particularly such that temperature should be converted to rankine and not kelvin\nT1 = T1 + 459.67\n\n# use normal shock relations for temperature\nT2 = T1*((1+((gamma-1)/2)*M1**2)/(1+((gamma-1)/2)*M2**2))\nprint('The temperature behind the shock wave is', T2, '°R')\n\n# use normal shock relations for pressure\np2 = p1*((1+gamma*M1**2)/(1+gamma*M2**2))\nprint('The pressure behind the shock wave is', p2, 'lbf/in^2')\n",
        "explanation": "This question simply utilizes all of the normal shock relations which can be computed through equations or referred to on the tables. Here, the equations used are M2^2 = ((1+M1**2*(gamma-1)/2)/(gamma*M1**2-(gamma-1)/2)) where M1 and M2 are Mach numbers and gamma is the gamma factor. The formula for temperature is T1(1+M1**2(gamma-1)/2)=T2(1+M2**2(gamma-1)/2 where T1 and T2 are temperatures and the rest are as previously defined. Lastly, the normal shock pressure equation is p1(1+gamma*M1^2) = p2(1+gamma*M2^2) where p1 and p2 are pressures and the rest are as previously defined. Here we assume the gamma factor of air to be 1.4.",
        "reference": "Robert T. Balmer (2011) Modern Engineering Thermodynamics, Academic Press."
    },
    {
        "question": "Air flows steadily between two sections in a long, straight portion of 4-in. inside diameter pipe. The uniformly distributed temperature and pressure at each section are, in the first section: 100 psia and 540°R and in the second section: 18.4 psia and 453°R. The average air velocity at section 2 is 1000 ft/s. If alternatively the temperature and pressure from section 1 remained constant, what would the area have to be in section 2 to have the same velocity, assuming the velocity in section 1 is as calculated previously?",
        "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\np1 = 100 # pressure at section 1 (psia)\nT1 = 540 # temperature at section 1 (R)\np2 = 18.4 # pressure at section 2\nT2 = 453 # temperature at section\nv2 = 1000 # velocity at section 2 (ft/s)\nD = 4 # diameter of the pipe (in)\n\n# the velocity change can be assumed to be due to changes in pressure, which in turn changes the density. Using ideal gas law to find the density ratio, R is not needed as it cancels out.\nrho_ratio = (p2 * T1) / (p1 * T2)\n\n# use the fact that mass flow rate is constant through the control volume\nv1 = rho_ratio * v2\n\nprint('The velocity at section 1 is', v1, 'ft/s')\n\n# use the volumetric flow rate for conservation of mass as in the second case density is constant\nA1 = (np.pi/4) * D**2 # in square inches\nA2 = (v1 * A1) / v2\nprint('The area of section 2 if pressure and temperature remained constant is', A2, 'square inches')\n",
        "explanation": "This code uses the conservation of mass by drawing a control volume over the two different sectors. From this conservation law, we know that the mass flow rate in is equal to the mass flow rate out, so rho1*A1*v1 = rho2*A2*v2 where rho1 and rho2 are densities, A1 and A2 are areas, and v1 and v2 are velocities. As the area of the pipe is constant, the areas cancel out. As we are solving for v1, we can assume that velocity changes based on changes in pressure and temperature and in turn a change in density. using pV = mRT we can calculate the ratio of pressures (omitting R as it will cancel out anyways) and then plug this value into the mass flow rate equation. For the second part of the question, a constant pressure and temperature implies that density is constant because the flow is incompressible. So we can use the relation Q1 = Q2 where Q1 and Q2 are the volumetric flow rates (Av) and solve for A2.",
        "reference": "Wade W. Huebsch et al., Fundamentals of Fluid Mechanics (2013), John Wiley & Sons, Inc."
    },
    {
        "question": "Why does Cp equal Cv for incompressible fluids?",
        "answer": "We know that under incompressible fluids that density does not change and stays constant under changes in pressure. In other words, this means that the volume does not change and dv=0. With the first law, we know U = pdV + Q, but dv=0, so U=Q=mCdeltaT where C is the specific heat of the substance and m is the mass. Essentially, all the heat added to the substance results in an increase in temperature disregarding pressure or volume, so there is no distinction between Cp and Cv for incompressible fluids. For this explanation, Cv and Cp are essentially constants because there are no changes in density with incompressible fluids. Since there are no significant changes in volume during the process, then we know that Cp and Cv are a function of temperature only and can be recognized as C.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
        },
        {
        "question": "What makes a process reversible or irreversible, and of these examples, name whether the process is reversible or irreversible? a. someone using a slinky with a spring b. the throttling process c. when particles move from an area of high concentration to low concentration (diffusion) d. imagine half a gas contained by a thermally insulated wall and the other half is in a vacuum, we then move the wall out of the way quickly e. ice cubes melting in water.",
        "answer": "A process is reversible if it can be turned back into its original state through the same process just reversed. A reversible process is what we associate isentropic processes with along with it being adiabtic. If something is reversible and adiabatic, then it is reversible, but just because it's reversible, does not guaratee it is isentropic. An irreversible process cannot be turned back into it's original state and there is also an increase in entropy or disorder of the system. An irreversible process is considered this way because it cannot be undone without using energy. a. reversible b. irreversible c. irreversible d. irrerversible e. irrerversible",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
        },
        {
        "question":"Explain what happens when a speed is subsonic (M<1) and the area increases, and then what happens when a speed is supersonic (M>1) and the area increases. Do the same for both subsonic and supersonic, but the area decreases. Which is intuitive and which is not?",
        "answer": "A subonic speed means that it is below Mach 1. If the area is increasing then the pressure will increase, while the velocity will decrease. When the speed is supersonic, the explanation is less intuitive. The velocity will increase, while the pressure decreases. This is with a converging nozzle or diffuser. The opposite occurs for decreasing area. With subsonic speeds, the pressure will decrease, while the velocity increases, which is in line with what we know already. But for supersonic speeds, the pressure increases, while the velocity decreases. Subsonic speeds are more intuitive because it goes along with incompressible fluids, while supersonic speeds do the opposite. We can see why they behave this way because of the variable nozzle flow equation.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
        },
        {
        "question": "What is the difference between a concave corner and convex corner, and what does each produce?",
        "answer": "When dealing with a concave corner, you will generate an oblique shock. A concave corner will produce one single shock at a specific angle given in a problem. This type of shock behaves just as a normal shock does. After the shock, the Mach number is smaller, static density, pressure, and enthalpy all increase, while stagnation pressure decreases. As for a convex corner, this generates an expansion fan. Expansion fans behave completely opposite as oblique shocks do, except that the stagnation pressure stays constant throughout the shock because they are isentropic. Many equations can be derived from using these relations.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
        },
        {
        "question":"What exactly is enthalpy and give an example of its use along with an equation to represent it?",
        "answer": "Enthalpy is the measure of energy in a thermodynamic system; it is the heat absorbed or released in a process at constant temperature. It is the total sum of internal energy plus pressure times velocity. Enthalpy is also known as a state function which means it only cares about the final state of the system. Enthalpy mainly cares about what current state you are in at the moment. It is useful in situations where there is constant external pressure meaning that enthalpy will be equal to energy exchanged by the environment with heat. Enthalpy can be used to improve thermal systems and maximize efficiency. A good formula is H = U + pV.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
        },
        {
        "question":"What is the difference between heat and temperature and give an example of each?",
        "answer": "Heat is all about the thermal energy that is transferred from one system to the next, while temperature is a measure of the average kinetic energy of molecules in a system. We are able to actually calculate the amount of heat absorbed or released by using the specific heat capcity, mass, and temperature change. An example would be looking at the heat exchange between a hot block and a cold block, then stating the temperature of each. Heat is more spoken about as a process and not a state. Temperature is more of a state function which comes from the zeroth law. The zeroth law states that when two objects in thermal equlibrium are in contact, there is no heat transfer and we call them the same temperature. It also states that heat flows from one source to another only if there is a difference between the two which is temperature. Anytime you use a thermometer, you are using the zeroth law.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
        },
        {
        "question": "How is Bernoulli's equation related to the conservation of energy, and what do each of the terms mean?",
        "answer": "Bernoulli's equation basically expresses the conservation of enegery for flowing fluids. Bernoulli's equation is representing the flow of something in terms of pressure, velocity, and height. It includes both kinetic and potential energy plus pressure. The sum of these values will remain constant along a streamline that is not curved. The conservation of energy states that energy within a closed system is constant. Going along with Bernoulli's terms, the kinetic energy term shows the energy with fluid motion, the potential energy term shows energy due to a fluids height, while the pressure term reflects the energy stored internally. Bernoulli's equation is a convienent way to express the conservation of energy for incompressible fluids.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
        },
        {
        "question": "In what ways does the concept of enthalpy impact the design of heat exchangers?",
        "answer": "From before, we know that enthalpy can have a huge effect on the efficiency and effectiveness of heat exchangers. When thinking about designing a heat exchanger, you must think about the enthalpy changes to ensure you get the desired temperature change. You would need to consider the first two laws of thermodynamics in order to be most precise. When thinking about the first law, you could calculate the amount of heat that needs to be transferred which makes you think about the size of the heat exchanger. When thinking about second law, this shows us the direction of flow and efficiency. In order to produce the best heat exchanger, you would need to know how to maximize the energy using the concept of enthalpy. By carefully measuring the changes in enthalpy, you can find the system that works the best while staying in thermodynamic limits.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
        },
        {
        "question":"How would you differentiate between isothermal and adiabatic processes regarding the amount of work done?",
        "answer": "First, it would be good to define an isothermal process. An isothermal process is when the temperture remains constant and the amount of work done is equal to the amount of heat transferred, while an adiabatic process is when there is no heat transferred during the process. For an adiabatic process, any work done results in a change in the system's internal energy and change in temperature. We know that Q= 0 when some process is adiabatic and that a useful equation would be that internal energy is equal to the amount of work done. You can also distinguish between the two by knowing the equation for an isothermal process which will give you the amount of work done. This would be W=nRTln(Vf/Vi) where n is the number of moles, T is temperature, and R is the universal gas constant.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."  
        },
        {
        "question":"A manometer containing oil (density = 850 kg/m^3) is attached to a tank filled with air. If the oil-level difference between the two columns is 45 cm and the atmospheric pressure is 98 kPa, determine the absolute pressure of the air in the tank.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\npatm = 98 # atmospheric pressure (kPa)\nd = 850 # oil density in manometer (kg/m^3)\ng = 9.81 # gravity (m/s^2)\nh = 0.00045 # height (km)\n\n# Apply manometer principle (equation is straight forward as given)\np = patm + (d*g*h)\n\nprint('The absolute pressure of air in the tank is:', p, 'kPa')\n",
        "explanation": "This code uses the manometer principle that we learned in some of the very first lessons showing that pressure changes with height. By plugging the values into the equation, we are able to see that pressure does change with height and gravity plays a role as well. An problem like this is simple to solve knowing the type of equation to use and what assumptions to make. We know to use gravity becuase height is changing and we can also infer to use the manometer equation because of the mention of the device stated in the problem.",
        "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
        "question": "A piston-cylinder device initially contains 0.4 m^3 of air at 100 kPa and 80°C. The air is now compressed to 0.1 m^3 in such a way that the temperature inside the cylinder remains constant. Determine the work done during this process.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nv1 = 0.4 # inital volume before compression (m)\nv2 = 0.1 # final volume after compression (m)\np = 100 # pressure (kPa)\nT = 80 # constant temperature (°C)\n\n# Using ideal gas equation, find work by setting work equal to the integral from v1 to v2, and setting P = Constant/V. Also, noting that PV = nRT which is equal to a constant.\nw = (p*v1)*np.log(v2/v1)\n\nprint('The amount of work done during this process is:', w, 'kJ')\n",
        "explanation": "Using the ideal gas equation and knowing that the volume changes but the temperature stays constant meaning isothermal, we need to take the integral of the work formula. Work ends up being negative because work is done on the system and compression is performed. We see here that pv is equal to a constant and that constant is nRT, we have set it up this way knowing that that the problem is isothermal. When volume changes, we know we must take an integral to obtain the correct equation because something is changing. We could have multiplied it by nRT, but that would obtain the some answer.",
        "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
        "question": "Steam enters a turbine with a velocity of 40 m/s and an enthalpy of 3433.8 kJ/kg. At the outlet, 2 meters lower than the inlet, the velocity is 162 m/s, and the enthalpy is 2675.5 kJ/kg. A heat loss of 1 kJ/kg is experienced from the turbine casing. The work output per unit mass is closest to...",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nv1 = 40 # inlet veloctiy (m/s)\nv2 = 162 # outlet velocity (m/s)\nh1 = 3433.8 # inlet enthalpy (kJ/kg)\nh2 = 2675.5 # outlet enthalpy (kJ/kg)\nz = 2 # height difference (m)\nQ = -1 # heat (kJ/kg)\ng = 9.81 # gravity (m/s^2)\n\n# Apply the steady state flow energy equation: W - Q = (v1^2/2 + h1 + z1g) - (v2^2/2 + h2 + z2g)\nworkpermass = (v1**2/(2*1000)+ h1 + (z*g)/1000)-(v2**2/(2*1000)+ h2 + 0) + Q\n\nprint('The work output per unit mass is:', workpermass, 'kJ/kg')\n",
        "explanation": "Using the steady flow energy equation, we are able to manipulate it to give us work per unit mass by dividing by the mass flow rate. We knew that the inlet area was 2 above the outlet, therefore we needed to include that in our calculations along with converting between units by dividing by 1000 in for the veolcity and height. By doing these things, we arrive at our result. We converted velocity into kilometers to match up with out other units in the equation. We also converted gravity to kilometers as well. Doing this kind of problem is mostly straight forward, as long as your assumptions about the equation are correct. We know we have potential energy and we also know there is kinetic energy by inferring from the problem statement.",
        "reference": "https://faculty.utrgv.edu/constantine.tarawneh/Thermodynamics/ThermodynamicsProb.pdf"
        },
        {
        "question": "A rigid tank contains a hot fluid which is cooled while being stirred by a paddle wheel. Initially, the internal energy of the fluid is 800 kJ. During the cooling process, the fluid loses 500 kJ of heat, and the paddle wheel does 100 kJ of work on the fluid. Determine the final internal energy of the fluid. Neglect the energy stored in the paddle wheel.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nu1 = 800 # inital internal energy (kJ)\nQ = -500 # heat (kJ)\nW = -100 # work done on system (kJ)\n\n# Apply the conservation of energy principle: Q — W = deltaU + deltaKE + deltaPE\nu2 = Q - W + u1\n\nprint('The final internal energy of the fluid is:', u2, 'kJ')\n",
        "explanation": "We can use the conservation of energy principle to solve this problem. We know that work is negative because it is done on the system, and heat is lost, so it is also negative. By neglecting the kinetic and potential energy, we can reaarange the equation to formulate our answer. We know we cna neglect these terms because in the problem statement, it says to neglect any potential energy. We also know that we can neglet any kinetic energy because there is no mention of velocity in the problem. A problem like this can be solved with simple assumptions and knowing what equation to use to solve it.",
        "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
        "question": "A nozzle with a diameter of 0.500 cm is attached to a garden hose with a radius of 0.900 cm. The flow rate through hose and nozzle is 0.500 L/s. Calculate the speed of the water (a) in the hose and (b) in the nozzle.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nd = 0.005 # diameter of nozzle (m)\nr = 0.009 # radius of hose (m)\nQ = 0.0005 # flow rate (m^3/s)\nA = 3.14*(r**2) # area of hose (m^2)\n\n# For part a, use the flow rate equation: Q = vA\nv1 = Q/A\n\nprint('The velocity through the hose is:', v1,'m/s')\n\n#For part b, use the equation of continuity: A1v1 = A2v2\nv2 = (r**2/(d/2)**2)*v1\n\nprint('The veloctiy through the nozzle is:', v2, 'm/s')\n",
        "explanation": "Using the fact that Q is equal to velocity times area, we are able to find the first speed through the hose. This equation was introduced to us during incompressible fluids. It is very useful when you know the flow rate and the area but need the velocity. Then, we can use the continuity equation to relate the two equations, knowing they are equal and that the areas cancel out, we find the speed through the nozzle. This is equation was also introduce early on with incompressible fluids, but can be used in many scenarios. It is good to note that the speed of the water in the hose is v1 because we are workign with it's radius and flow rate equation first. Be sure to use the correct diameters/radii when doing a problem such as this. ",
        "reference": "https://openstax.org/books/university-physics-volume-1/pages/14-5-fluid-dynamics"
        },
        {
        "question":"A Carnot heat engine receives 500 kJ of heat per cycle from a high-temperature source at 652°C and rejects heat to a low-temperature sink at 30°C. Determine (a) the thermal efficiency of this Carnot engine and (b) the amount of heat rejected to the sink per cycle.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nTh = 652 + 273.15 # temperature of hot source (K)\nTc = 30 + 273.15 # temperature of cold source (K)\nQin = 500 # amount of heat given to hot source (kJ)\n\n# For part a, apply the thermal efficiency equation (equation is straight forward)\nn = 1 - (Tc/Th)\n\nprint('The thermal efficiency of this Carnot heat engine is:', n)\n\n# For part b, apply the second law: Qout/Tc = Qin/Th\nQout = (Tc/Th)*Qin\n\nprint('The amount of heat expelled during this process is:', Qout, 'kJ')\n",
        "explanation":"By using the thermal efficiency equation we derived in lecture, we can just simply apply it here by plugging in the numbers given. This equation is used for finding the therml efficiency of a heat engine. Using this type of equation is generally straight foward. For part b, we can use a form of the second law and manipulate it, so that we get the amount of heat expelled. Here we have applied the second law which tells us more about the direction and efficency of a system. We use it here to compare the two hot and cold sources and can come up with the ratio in order to solve for our unknown variable. Always make sure temperature is in Kelvin.",
        "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
        "question": "Air enters a diffuser with a velocity of 200 m/s. Determine (a) the velocity of sound and (b) the flow Mach number at the diffuser inlet when the air temperature is 30°C.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nv = 200 # velocity entering diffuser (m/s)\nT = 30+273.25 # temperature of air (K)\nk = 1.4 # specific heat ratio determined by 30°C and the tables\nR = 287 # gas constant of air (kJ/kg*K)\n\nimport math\n\n# For part a, use the equation for speed of sound: a = sqrt(K*T*R)\na = math.sqrt(T*R*k)\n\nprint('The velocity of sound is: ',a , 'm/s')\n\n# For part b, use the Mach number equation\nM = v/a\n\nprint('The mach number at the inlet is: ', M)\n",
        "explanation": "By using the speed of sound equation and the tables provided, we are able to come up with the answer by plugging in the numbers and making sure the temperature has the correct units. We start by looking at this problem and seeing what is needed first. In order to find the mach flow number at the inlet, we needed to find what the speed of sound was. Upon finding that while using the numbers given, we are then able to apply that to the mach number equation. For part b, we know the Mach number equation, so we can easily plug in the values to obtain the answer. For problems such as these, it is good to take things step by step and see what minor steps may be needed to arrive at the final answer.",
        "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
            "question" : "Explain the difference between Poiseuille and Couette Flow." ,
            "answer" : "Poiseulle flow is characterized by a constant pressure gradient causing the laminar flow of an incompressible fluid moving between two fixed plates (such as a pipe). Couette flow, however, involves one stagnant plate and one moving plate that drives the flow of the fluid through shear stress, rather than a pressure gradient.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question" : "How can there be a temperature change within an adiabatic process?",
            "answer" : "An adiabatic process refers to that fact that there is no heat exchange between the system and its surroundings. However, a temperature change within the system itself is allowed. In other words, the temperature can be altered by work, but there is no exchange with the surroundings.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question" : "How do you distinguish between a reversible and irreversible process?",
            "answer" : "A reversible process is a process where both the system and the surroundings can be returned to their initial states. This means that the net heat and net work exhchange between the system and the surroundings is zero. Irreversibilites are caused by factors such as friction, unrestrained expansion, and heat transfer across a finite temperature difference.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question" : "Can the Clausis inequality be used on both reversible and irreversible processes?",
            "answer" : "The cyclic integral of SQ/T is always less than or equal to zero. This is valid for reversible and irreversible cycles. If a cycle is reversible, the integral will be equal to zero. The Kelvin-Plank statement tells us that no system can produce a net amount of work while operating in a cycle and exchanging heat with a single thermal energy reservoir. Due to this statement, we know that the total work of the system cannot be greater than 0. However it can be less than 0, allowing us to utilize the Clausius Inequality for irreversible processes.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "What does it mean for a process to be both internally reversible and adiabatic?",
            "answer": "When a process is both reversible and adiabatic, it can be deduced that the process also has constant entropy. This is known as an isentropic process.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question" : "What are the implications of using a control volume on a steady flow process?", 
            "answer": "The rate of entropy change within a control volume during a process is equal to the sum of the rate of entropy transfer through the control volume boundary by heat transfer and mass flow, and entropy generation within the boundaries by irreversiblities. Therefore, many control volumes acting in steady flow processes experience no change in their entropy. This makes it possible to use isentropic relations, and assume constant conditions through the control volume.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question" : "What happens to the Mach number downstream of a normal shock vs an oblique shock?",
            "answer" : "Similar to normal shocks, the mach number decreases across an oblique shock and is only possible if the upstream flow is supersonic. However, unlike normal shocks which always have a subsonic downstream mach number, oblique shocks may have a subsonic, sonic, or supersonic downstream Mach number depending on the upstream value.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question" : "Explain when supersonic processes are irreversible.",
            "answer" : "When flow moves faster than the speed of sound (Mach 1), there is a very sudden decrease in the flow area, and shock waves are generated in the flow. Across a shock wave, the static pressure, temperature, and density change drastically and nearly instantaneously, meaning the flow properities occur non-isentropically.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question" : "How does the first law of thermodynamics define the property total energy?",
            "answer" : "Consider the statement 'for all adiabatic processes between two specified states of a closed system, the net work done is the same regardless of the nature of the closed system and the details of the process'. If net work is the same for all adiabatic processes of a closed system between two defined states, then the value of the net work must depend soley on the end states of the system, which corresponds to a change in property called total energy. The different forms that constitute total energy are kinetic, potential, and internal energy.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question" : "What does the area under the process curve represent on a P-v diagram?",
            "answer" : "The area under the process curve on a P-V diagram is equal to the work done during a quasi-equilibrium expansion or compression process of a closed system. It represents the boundary work done per unit mass, therefore if the system is isochoric, the boundary work associated is always zero.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question" : "A frictionless piston-cylinder system contains 2kg of an ideal gas at 100 kPa and 300 K. The gas is slowly compressed, undergoing a polytropic process, until it reaches a final temperature of 360 K. Calculate the work input during this process. Assume n = 1.4",
            "answer" : "\n            import numpy as np\n            m = 2 # kg\n            P1 = 100 # kpa\n            T1 = 300 # K\n            T2 =360 # K\n            R = 0.287 # gas constant\n            n = 1.4 # ideal gas\n\n            #calculate work for a polytropic process\n            W = (m * R * (T2-T1))/(1-n)\n\n            print('The work input during this process is', W, 'kJ')\n                ",
            "explanation" : "We know the process is polytropic, therefore utilzing the work formula for a polytropic process W = (P1*V1-P2*V2)/(n-1). We can rearrange this formula to W = (m*R*(T1-T2))/(n-1) to fit the parameters given.",
            "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
            "question" : "A piston-cylinder device initially contains 0.4 m^3 of air at 100 kPa and 80*C. The air is compressed to 0.1 m^3 in such a way that the temperature inside the cylinder remains constant. Determine the work done during this process and graph the process on a P-V diagram.",
            "answer": "\n            import numpy as np \n            import matlablib.pyplot as plot\n            V1 = 0.4 # m^3\n            V2 = 0.1 # m^3\n            P1 = 100 # kPa\n            T0 = 80 # C\n\n            #calculate work by using ideal gas law and integrating\n            W = (P1*V1)*np.log(V2/V1)\n\n            print('The work done during this process is', W, 'kJ')\n\n            #plot diagram\n            T_K = T0 + 273.15\n            P2 = (P1*V1)/V2\n            V_range = np.linspace(V1, V2, 100)\n            P_range = (P1*P2)/V_range\n            plt.figure(figsize=(8, 5))\n            plt.plot(V_range, P_range, label='Isothermal Compression')\n            plt.xlabel('Volume (m³)')\n            plt.ylabel('Pressure (Pa)')\n            plt.title('PV Diagram of an Isothermal Compression')\n            plt.legend()\n            plt.grid(True)\n            plt.show()\n                ",
            "explanation" : "Assume the compression process is quasi-equilibrium, and that the gas is ideal due to high temperature and low pressure. Using the ideal gas law, find that P = constant / V. To find the work done, substitute C/V into the Pdv integral, and compute the integral from state 1 to 2. This yields P1*V1*ln(V2/V1).",
            "reference" : "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
            "question" : "An ideal gas flows steadily in a pipe at 300kPa, 77*C, and 25 m/s at a rate of 18 kg/s. Determine the diameter of the pipe.",
            "answer" : "\n            import numpy as np\n            P = 300 # pressure\n            T = 77 # temp in celcius\n            v = 25 # velocity m/s\n            m = 18 # mass flow rate kg/s\n            R = 287 # gas constant j/(K*kg)\n            pi = 3.14159\n\n            # find density using ideal gas law\n            rho = P / (R*T)\n            # use mass flow rate formula to calculate area --> diameter\n            d = ((4*m)/(pi*rho*v))**(-1/2)\n\n            print('The diamater of the pipe is: ', d, 'meters')\n                ",
            "explanation" : "Assume that this is a steady flow process, where mass in = mass out. Recognizing that the gas is ideal, we are able to rearrange the formula P = rho*R*T to find rho. Once rho is found, we are able to substitute this into the mass flow rate formula m = rho*A*v. Rearranging for diameter yields: d = ((4*m)/(pi*rho*v))**(-1/2)",
            "reference" : "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
            "question" : "Air enters an adiabatic nozzle steadily at 300kPa, 200*C, and 30 m/s. It leaves at 100kPa and 180 m/s. The inlet area of the nozzle is 80cm^2. Determine the mass flow rate through the nozzle and the exit temperature of the air. Assume Cp = 1.005 kJ/kg*K",
            "answer" : "\n            import numpy as np\n            P1 = 300 #kPa\n            T_C = 200\n            T = T_C + 273.15\n            v1 = 30 # m/s\n            A1 = 80 * 10**(-4)\n            P2 = 100 # kPa\n            v2 =180 # m/s\n            R = 0.287\n            Cp = 1005\n\n            # find mass flow rate:\n            m = (P1/(R*T)) * A1 * v1\n            # find exit temp of air\n            T2 = ((Cp*T_C)+((v1**2)/2)-((v2**2)/2))/Cp\n            print('The mass flow rate through the nozzle is ', m)\n            print('The temperature at the exit of the nozzle is ', T2)\n                ",
            "explanation" : "Assuming that this is a steady flow, adiabatic process with only one inlet and exit, we can use the mass flow rate formula by substituting in rho = P/R*T. ",
            "reference" : "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
            "question" : "A heat engine with a thermal efficiency of 40 percent rejects 1000kJ/kg of heat. How much heat does it receive?",
            "answer" : "\n            import numpy as np\n            n = 0.4\n            Q2 = 1000 # kJ/kg\n\n            #using efficency formula\n            Q1 = (-Q2)/(n-1)\n\n            print('The heat engine receives', Q1, 'kJ/kg of heat.')\n                ",
            "explanation" : "Utilizing the efficiency formula where n = 1 - Q2/Q1, rearrange for Q1. This formula represents the fration of heat that becomes useful work, where Q2 is heat rejected and Q1 is heat received.",
            "reference" : "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
            "question" : "A 3-ft^3 adiabatic rigid container is divided into two equal volumes by a thin membrane. Initially, one of these chambers is filled with air at 100 psia and 100*F, while the other chamber is evacuated. Determine the internal energy change of the air when the membrane is ruptured and the final air pressure in the container.",
            "answer" : "\n            import numpy as np\n            P1 = 100 #psia\n            T1 = 100 # F\n            V1 = 1.5\n            V2 = 3\n\n            #change in internal energy\n            dU = 0 \n            #use isothermal properties because no change in temperature\n            P2 = P1*V1/V2\n            print('The change in internal energy of the system is', dU, 'and the final air pressure of the container is', P2)\n                ",
            "explanation" : "The system is stationary, therefore the potential and kinetic enrgy changes are 0, leaving dU = 0 as the system is not doing any work or exchanging heat with the surroundings. As the container is adiabatic, we can use isothermal relations as no heat is lost to the surroundings. Rearranging for P2, we get the equation P2 = P1*V1/V2.", 
            "reference" : "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
            "question" : "Air expands isentropically from 1.5 MPa and 60*C to 0.4 MPa. Calculate the ratio of the initial to final speed of sound. Assume gamma = 1.4",
            "answer" : "\n            import numpy as np\n            T1 = 60 + 273.15 # celcius to kelvin\n            P1 = 1.5 # MPa\n            P2 = 0.4 # MPa\n            ga = 1.4\n            R = 287\n\n            #using isentropic relations, find T2\n            T2 = (T1)*(P2/P1)**((ga-1)/ga)\n            #find speed of sound at inlet and outlet\n            a1 = np.sqrt(ga*R*T1)\n            a2 = np.sqrt(ga*R*T2)\n            #find ratio of inlet to outlet\n            ratio = a1/a2\n\n            print('The ratio of the initial to final speed of sound is', ratio)\n                ",
            "explanation" : "The problem states the air expands isentropically, therefore use isentropic relations between pressure and temperature to find T2. From this, use the formula (square root of gamma*R*T) to calculate the acceleration for initial and final speed.",
            "reference" : "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
            "question" : "A 50kg block of iron at 500K is thrown into a body of water that is at a temperature of 285K. When the iron block reaches thermal equilibrium with the water, determine the entropy change of the iron block. Assume the average specific heat to be 0.45 kJ/kg*K",
            "answer": "\n            import numpy as np\n            m = 50 # kg\n            T_b = 500 # K\n            T_L = 285 # K\n            C = 0.45 #kJ/kg*K\n\n            #change in entropy\n            dS = m*C*np.log(T_L/T_b)\n\n            print('The change in entropy of the iron block when in equilibrium with the lake is', dS)\n                ",
            "explanation" : "Assume the rock and the water are both incompressible. The kinetic and potential energy changes of the block are negligible once the block is in the water, therefore dE=dU. Given that a lake is very large in reference to a rock, the final temperature of the lake and rock will be that of the lake initially. By integrating the entropy formula m(s2-s1), we get m*C*ln(T_f/T_i).", 
            "reference" : "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
            "question": "Define a fluid in relation to its ability to sustain shear stress.",
            "answer": "A fluid is a substance which cannot sustain shear stress when at rest. Shear stresses are sustained in fluids only when relative motion between fluid particles takes place. Another way to say this is that when a fluid is at rest, there are no shear stresses.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "Describe how pressure acts upon a stationary object submerged in a fluid using the hydrostatic equation.",
            "answer": "A body immersed in a fluid will still experience a force even if there is no relative motion between the body and the fluid. Since no shear stresses are present in a stationary fluid, pressure is set by the normal component of force with respect to the surface. Considering the weight of the object and the hydrostatic equation dp = -g * rho * dy, we can say that pressure increases with depth and that the net force on the object acts only in the vertical direction. Archimedes Principle states that the upward force on the submerged body is equal to the weight of the fluid displaced by the body.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "Define gauge pressure and its importance.",
            "answer": "Gauge pressure is the relative pressure with respect to the atmospheric pressure. Often, the pressure of a fluid is far greater than the atmospheric pressure, meaning the affects of atmospheric pressure can be ignored and gauge pressure used in calculations.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "What is the physical significance of Bernoulli's Equation?",
            "answer": "When velocity increases, pressure decreases, and when velocity decreases, pressure increases. Bernoulli's equation is also a relation for mechanical energy in an incompressible flow as it states that the work done on a fluid by pressure forces is equal to the change in kinetic energy of the flow",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
            "question": "What are Couette and Poiseuille Flows and what occurs when they are combined?",
            "answer": "Couette flow occurs between two parallel plates when one plate is stationary and the other moves at a constant velocity, creating a linear velocity profile between them. Poiseuille flow occurs in a fully enclosed pipe or between two stationary parallel plates driven by a pressure gradient. The velocity profile for Poiseuille flow is parabolic, with the maximum velocity occurring at the center of the pipe or midway between the plates and decreasing to zero at the walls. When these flows are combined, the force balance and equations of motion are the same but the boundary conditions are different. Either a favorable pressure gradient occurs (when dp/dx < 0) or and adverse pressure gradient occurs (when dp/dx > 0)",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question":"Explain the implications of an adiabatic process within the First Law of Thermodynamics",
            "answer":"The first law states that energy cannot be created nor destroyed, meaning a state has a total energy, denoted as E. The energy of a system is the sum of kinetic energy, potential energy, and internal energies. Energy can be transferred as heat, work, or mass flow. An Adiabatic process involves no heat transfer. Assuming no kinetic or potential energy contributions, this means that the work done on or by a system during an adiabatic process is independant of the path taken.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question":"What is a polytropic process and how does the value of the parameter n determine what type of process occurs?",
            "answer":"A polytropic process is a compression or expansion for which the pressure and volume are related by p*V^n = constant. The parameter n is assumed to remain constant throughout the process. For ideal gasses, n = gamma indicates an isentropic proccess, n = 1 represents an isothermal process, n = 0 is isobaric, n = infinity is isochoric, n between 1 and gamme usually indicates a process with heat transfer.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question":"Elaborate on the clausius and kelvin-planck statements and how they limit the efficeincy of heat engines.",
            "answer":"The Kelvin-Planck statement states that it is impossible to build a cyclic device whose sole effect is to produce positve work while recieving heat from a single thermal reservoir, which is assumed to have infinite thermal heat capacity. This statement says that all the heat cannot be converted into useful work, there must be some limit on the efficiency. The clausius statement demonstrates the irriversibility of nature, stating that heat cannot be transferred from a colder body to a hotter one without an input of work. In summmary, these statements conclude that heat engines are limited in effieciency. The maximum efficiency of a cyclic heat engine operating between two thermal reservoirs is attained when the cycle is reversible.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question":"Explain why change in entropy is path independant and what the only way to reduce the entropy of a system is.",
            "answer":"Entropy is an extensive property representing the inability of a systems thermal energy to produce useful mechanical work. By the definition of a thermodynamic property, the value of entropy must depend only on the state of the system, not on the path taken. Entropy change is proportional to the mass of a system. Entropy can only be integrated over a reversible process. For irriversible processes, there is an infinitesimal entropy production due to the irreversability within the system, meaning the only way to reduce the entropy of a closed system is to give up heat to the surroundings.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "Invicid, incompressible air flows along a streamline. Air density along the streamline is 1.225 kg/m^3. At point 1 along the streamline, pressure is 100 KPa and velocity is 3 m/s. Downstream the velocity is 60 m/s. Calculate the pressure downstream.",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nrho = 1.225 # Density (kg/m^3)\np1 = 101314 # Pressure 1 (Pa)\nv1 = 3 # Velocity 1 (m/s)\nv2 = 60 # Velocity 2 (m/s)\n\n# Apply bernoulli's equation along streamlines (p1 + 0.5 * rho * (v1**2)) = p2 + 0.5 * rho * (v2**2))\np2 = p1 + 0.5 * rho * ((v1**2)-(v2**2))\n\nprint('Downstream Pressure:', p2, 'Pa')\n        ",
            "explanation": "This code utilized bernoulli's equation to show the relation between pressure and velocity along a streamline. As shown, a small change in pressure results in a large change in velocity.",
            "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
            "question":"JP-7 fuel flows through a 5 meter long pipe with a diameter of 0.1 meters at a temperature of -34.5 degrees celcius and a volumetric flow rate of 0.5 m^3/s. Calculate the pressure drop thorugh the pipe. Assume viscosity is 0.012 Pa-s",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nl = 5 # Length of Pipe (m)\nd = 0.1 # Diameter of Pipe (m)\nr = d/2 # Radius of Pipe (m)\nQ = 0.5 # Volumetric Flow Rate (m^3/s)\nmu = 0.012 # Viscosity (Pa-s)\npi = np.pi\n\n# Calculate bulk velocty using relation V = Volumetric Flow Rate/Cross Sectional Area\nV = Q/(pi * (r**2))\n\n# Apply Hagen-Poiseuille Equation\nDelta_P = (8*mu*V*l)/(r**2)\n\nprint('The loss in pressure is:', Delta_P, 'Pa')\n        ",
            "explanation": "This code utilizes the volumetric flow rate - bulk velocity relation and the hagen-poiseuille equation to calculate pressure loss through a pipe.",
            "reference": "https://wiki.anton-paar.com/us-en/aviation-fuels"
        },
        {
            "question":"Contrary to the Clausius statement of the second law, 100 Joules of heat is transferred from a 600 K colder body to a 1200 K hoter body. Prove that this violates the increase in entropy principle.",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nQ = 100 # Heat Energy (J)\nT_hot = 1200 # Temperature of Hot Body in Kelvin\nT_cold = 600 # Temperature of Cold Body in Kelvin\n\n# Entropy Change of Hot Body\n\ndelta_S_hot = Q/T_hot\n\n# Entropy Change of Cold Body\n\ndelta_S_cold = -1 * Q/T_cold\n\n# Total Entropy Change\n\ndelta_S = delta_S_hot + delta_S_cold\n\nprint('The total entropy change is', delta_S, 'J/K which violates the entropy principle since the total entropy change is negative.')\n        ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the entropy change of two bodies where heat is transferred in an internally reversible isothermal heat transfer process.",
            "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
            "question":"Calculate the entropy change for an ideal gas that undergoes an adiabatic expansion from 1 bar to 0.5 bar. Assume initial temperature is 300 K, heat capacity at constant pressure is 1005 J/(kg*K), and specific gas constant R = 287 J/(kg*K)",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nP1 = 1  # initial pressure (bar)\nP2 = 0.5  # final pressure (bar)\nT1 = 300  # initial temperature (K)\n\nCp = 1005  # heat capacity at constant pressure J/(kg*K)\nR = 287  # specific gas constant for air J/(kg*K)\n\n# Calculate the final temperature\n\ngamma = Cp / (Cp - R)\n\n# Using Isentropic Relations\n\nT2 = T1 * (P2 / P1)**((gamma - 1) / gamma)\n\n# Calculate the entropy change\ndelta_S = Cp * np.log(T2 / T1) - R * np.log(P2 / P1)\n\nprint('Entropy change is:', delta_S, 'J/K')\n        ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates entropy change for an ideal gas where Q = 0. After the final temperature is calculated, Tds relations are used to find the change in entropy.",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question":"An airplane flies at a velocity of 500 m/s. Calculate its Mach number if it is flying at a standard altitude of sea level. Assume temperature at sea level is 288 Kelvin and gamma is 1.4.",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\ngammma = 1.4\nT = 288 # Temperature in Kelvin\nR = 287  # specific gas constant for air J/(kg*K)\nV = 500 # velocity of\n\n# Calculate speed of sound\n\na = np.sqrt(gamma * R * T)\n\n# Calculate Mach Number\n\nM = V/a\n\nprint('The airplane is flying at Mach ', M)\n        ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates mach number using the speed of sound equation and then the relation between mach numbeer, flow velocity, and speed of sound.",
            "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
            "question":"A normal shock wave in air where the upstream flow properties are v1 = 680 m/s, T1 = 288 K, and p1 = 1 atm. Assuming gamma = 1.4, calculate the velocity, temperature, and pressure down- stream of the shock using normal shock property tables",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\ngamma = 1.4\nR = 287  # specific gas constant for air J/(kg*K)\nT1 = 288 # Temperature in Kelvin\nv1 = 680 # Velocity (m/s)\np1 = 1 # Pressure (atm)\n\n# Calculate speed of sound\n\na1 = np.sqrt(gamma * R * T1)\n\n# Calculate Mach Number\n\nM = v1/a1\n\n# Values from Property Tables at calculated M\n\np2_p1 = 4.5\nT2_T1 = 1.687\nM2 = 0.5774\n\n# Calculate downstream properties\n\np2 = p2_p1 * p1\n\nT2 = T2_T1 * T1\n\na2 = np.sqrt(gamma * R * T2)\n\nv2 = M2 * a2\n\nprint('Pressure:', p2, 'atm')\nprint('Temperature:', T2, 'K')\nprint('Velocity:', v2, 'm/s')\n        ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates downstream properties Temperature, Pressure, and Velocity using the speed of sound and normal shock relations found in property tables associated with gamma = 1.4",
            "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
            "question":"Air enters a 1 m diameter pipe steadily at 2000 Pa and 20 C with a velocity of 5 m/s. Air is heated as it flows, and leaves the pipe at 1800 Pa and 40 C. Determine the velocity and volume flow rate at the exit.",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nv1 = 5 # Velocity of incoming air (m/s)\np1 = 2000 # Pressure of incoming air (Pa)\nT1 = 20 # Temperature of incoming air (C)\nd = 1 # Diameter of pipe (m)\np2 = 1800 # Pressure of exiting air (Pa)\nT2 = 40 # Temperature of exiting air (C)\nR = 287  # specific gas constant for air J/(kg*K)\nr = d/2 # Radious of pipe (m)\n\n# Calculate volume flow rate at inlet\n\nvol_flow1 = np.pi*(r**2)*v1\n\n# Calculate density\n\nrho1 = p1/(R*(T1+237))\nrho2 = p2/(R*(T2+237))\n\n# Calculate mass flow rate using m_dot = rho * A * V\n\nmass_flow = rho1*(np.pi*(r**2))*v1\n\n# Since mass flow in is equal to mass flow out\n\nvol_flow2 = mass_flow/rho2\n\n# Calculate Velocity Out\n\nv2 = vol_flow2/(np.pi*r**2)\n\nprint('Volume flow at exit:', vol_flow2, 'm^3/s')\nprint('Velocity at exit:', v2, 'm/s')\n        ",
            "explanation": "This code uses the principle of conservation of mass to calculate the velocity at the exit of the pipe given that density changes.",
            "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
            "question": "Based on Bernoulli’s equation, what are some forms of energy in a fluid? (Note that these forms are conservative, unlike heat transfer and other dissipative forms not included in Bernoulli’s equation.)",
            "answer": "Kinetic energy due to velocity, and the work done by a pressure difference.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": "https://openstax.org/books/university-physics-volume-1/pages/14-conceptual-questions"
        },
        {
            "question": "What is the difference between a control volume and a system?",
            "answer": "A system refers to a fixed mass with a boundary. However, with time the boundary of the system may change, but the mass remains the same. Instead of focusing on a fixed mass, we can observe the flow through a window, this window is called a control volume.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": "http://www-mdp.eng.cam.ac.uk/web/library/"
        },
        {
            "question": "How does steady flow differ from unsteady flow?",
            "answer": "In steady flow, the conditions (such as velocity, pressure, and cross-section) can vary from point to point within the fluid, but they do not change over time. While in unsteady flow the fluid conditions change with time, for example water distribution systems during valve opening or closing.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "A rigid tank contains a hot fluid that is cooled while being stirred by a paddle wheel. First, the internal energy of the fluid is 800 kJ. The fluid loses 500 kJ of heat, and the paddle wheel does 100 kJ of work on the fluid. Determine the final internal energy of the fluid disregarding the energy of the paddle wheel.",
            "answer": "\\n                import numpy as np\\n\\n                W = 100 # shaft work (kJ)\\n                Qout = 500 # heat lost from the fluid (kJ)\\n                U1 = 800 # initial internal energy (kJ)\\n\\n                U2 = W - Qout + U1\\n\\n                print(\"The final internal energy of the system is\", U2, \"kJ\")\\n                ",
            "explanation": "The tank is called rigid, and the system is stationary because it does not have any changes in their velocity or elevation during a process.",
            "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
            "question": "Consider steady heat transfer through a 5-m × 7-m brick wall of a house that is 30 cm thick. On a day outside temperature is 0°C, inside the house the temperature is 27°C. The temperatures of the inner and outer surfaces of the brick wall are measured to be 20°C and 5°C. The rate of heat transfer through the wall is 1035 W. Determine the rate of entropy generation in the wall.",
            "answer": "\\n                import numpy as np\\n\\n                Qdot = 1035 # rate of heat transfer (Watts)\\n                T1 = 293 # temperature on outer surface (Kelvins)\\n                T2 = 278 # temperature on inner surface (Kelvins)\\n\\n                Sdotin = Qdot / T1\\n                Sdotout = Qdot / T2\\n                Sgen = -1 * Sdotin + Sdotout\\n\\n                print(\"Therefore, the rate of entropy generation in the wall is\", Sgen, \"W/K\")\\n                ",
            "explanation": "The entropy change of the wall is zero during this process because the heat and entropy enter from one side and leave from the other and inside the wall, there is no change.",
            "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
            "question": "What is the change in entropy in an adiabatic process? Does this imply that adiabatic processes are reversible?",
            "answer": "An adiabatic process occurs without transferring heat or mass between the system and its environment and only transfers energy as work. In a reversible adiabatic process, the entropy change is zero but in an irreversible adiabatic process the entropy increases. So, this does not necessarily imply reversibility.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": "https://www.britannica.com/science/adiabatic-process"
        },
        {
            "question": "Are the following scenarios reversible or irreversible? A) getting into a pool slowly B) jumping into a pool (from the perspective of water) C) a balloon deflating",
            "answer": "A is a reversible process because when you go into a pool slowly the water level rises slowly and maintains equilibrium and if you slowly get out the pool water will go back to normal. B is irreversible because by jumping into a pool, the water experiences sudden turbulence and waves cannot be reversed. C is reversible since balloons typically deflate slowly and unless the plastic is overly stretched, inflating a balloon would put it back to its original state.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "A real process may be nearly adiabatic if it occurs over a very short time. How does the short time span help the process to be adiabatic?",
            "answer": "The short time span helps the process because the heat does not take enough time to enter the system and the transmission of heat from the surroundings takes time, so if the changes of the system occur suddenly, then there may not be enough time for the transmission of heat.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": "https://courses.lumenlearning.com/suny-physics/chapter/15-2-the-first-law-of-thermodynamics-and-some-simple-processes/"
        },
        {
            "question": "Consider a normal shock wave in a supersonic airstream where the pressure upstream of the shock is 1 atm. Calculate the loss of total pressure across the shock wave when the upstream Mach number is (a) M1 = 2, and (b) M1 = 4.",
            "answer": "\\n                import numpy as np\\n\\n                # We can obtain upstream total pressure using p01 = (p01/p1)*p1 using the ratio corresponding with M1=2 from the isentropic flow tables\\n                P1 = 1 # upstream pressure (atm)\\n                P01overP1 = 7.824\\n                P01 = P01overP1 * P1 # (atm)\\n\\n                # To get total pressure behind normal shock we use p02 = (p02/p01)*p01 again using M1 = 2 from the normal shock tables\\n                P02overP01 = 0.7209\\n                P02 = P02overP01 * P01 # (atm)\\n\\n                # The loss of total pressure for a\\n                aloss = P01 - P02 # (atm)\\n\\n                # For M1 = 4 and we follow the same process again\\n                P01onP1 = 151.8\\n                P0_1 = P01onP1 * P1 # (atm)\\n                P02onP01 = 0.1388\\n                P0_2 = P02onP01 * P0_1 # (atm)\\n                bloss = P0_1 - P0_2 # (atm)\\n\\n                print(\"The loss of total pressure for part a\", aloss, \"atm\")\\n                print(\"The loss of total pressure for part b\", bloss, \"atm\")\\n                ",
            "explanation": "The values used to get the ratio values are found in Appendix A and then Appendix B",
            "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
            "question": "Consider an oblique shock wave with a wave angle of 30 degrees. The upstream flow Mach number is 2.4. Calculate the Mach number behind the wave.",
            "answer": "\\n                import numpy as np\\n                import math\\n\\n                # Using the wave angle, theta, and Mach number graph in figure 9.9 we get theta to be 6.5 degrees\\n                theta = 6.5 # (degrees)\\n                beta = 30 # (degrees)\\n\\n                # Also, we can find M1’s normal component to be 1.2 giving the normal Mach number behind the wave\\n                Mn2 = 0.8422\\n                dif = beta - theta\\n                den = math.sin(math.radians(dif))\\n                M2 = Mn2 / den\\n\\n                print(\"The Mach number is\", M2, \"behind the wave\")\\n                ",
            "explanation": "Mn2 is the normal Mach number behind the shock wave. The downstream Mach number itself, M2, needed to be found using the geometry displayed here.",
            "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
            "question": "A supersonic flow with M1 = 1.5, p1 = 1 atm, and T1 = 288 K is expanded around a sharp corner (see Figure 9.26) through a deflection angle, theta, of 15 degrees. Calculate M2, p2, T2, p02, and T02.",
            "answer": "\\n                import numpy as np\\n\\n                P1 = 1 # (atm)\\n                T1 = 288 # (Kelvins)\\n\\n                # Looking at appendix C we get that M1 = 1.5 has nu1 = 11.91 degrees and we can use nu1 + theta = nu2 which is 26.91 degrees. And the corresponding Mach number for that is M2 = 2\\n                # Using appendix A for M1 = 1.5 we get the following ratios\\n                P01overP1 = 3.671\\n                T01overT1 = 1.45\\n\\n                # And for M2 = 2 we get\\n                P02overP2 = 7.824\\n                T02overT2 = 1.8\\n\\n                # This flow is isentropic so T01 = T02 and P01 = P02 so we can use the following ratios to solve for P2 = (P2/P02)*(P02/P01)*(P01/P1)*P1\\n                P2 = (1 / P02overP2) * 1 * P01overP1 * P1\\n                T2 = (1 / T02overT2) * 1 * T01overT1 * T1\\n                P0 = P01overP1 * P1\\n                T0 = T01overT1 * T1\\n\\n                print(\"The static pressure after the expansion fan is\", P2, \"atm\")\\n                print(\"The temperature after the expansion fan is\", T2, \"K\")\\n                print(\"The stagnation pressure is\", P0, \"atm\")\\n                print(\"The stagnation temperature is\", T0, \"K\")\\n                ",
            "explanation": "The challenging part of this question is understanding the properties of expansion fans, they are isentropic, so the stagnation temperature and pressure remain constant throughout.",
            "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
            "question": "Why can't incompressible flows have shock waves?",
            "answer": "Shock waves happen when an object moves faster than the speed of sound so, there cannot be any usual reactions to variations in pressure and density which causes pressure builds up rapidly causing a wave. Now, incompressible flows are isochoric meaning that volume does not change and are characterized by having negligible changes in density. This means that incompressible flows cannot have shock waves.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "Is stagnation temperature constant across an oblique shock?",
            "answer": "While it is true that the static temperature, pressure, and density increase immediately across an oblique shock. The stagnation temperature remains constant because the flow is still adiabatic, so there cannot be any heat addition.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "What are the basic components of a supersonic wind tunnel and what do they do?",
            "answer": "The basic components of a supersonic wind tunnel are the nozzle, the testing or working station, the diffuser, the compressor, and a heat exchanger. The way the nozzle is shaped determines the Mach number and accelerates the air to supersonic speeds. Then the supersonic airflow goes to the working or testing station, which is where aircraft or airfoils are to be placed so the aerodynamic effects can be observed. Leaving the test section, the diffuser is where the airflow slows down and the air finally exits the wind tunnel having had pressure and velocity reduced. Due to the shock loss, air experiences a loss of stagnation pressure, the compressor helps restore that with a byproduct of increasing the temperature so there is also a heat exchanger to cool it.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supersonic_wind_tunnel"
        },
        {
            "question": "Describe the difference between Lagrangian and Eulerian frameworks and which would be more useful in modeling the flow of fluid through a pipe fixture.",
            "answer": "Lagrangian framework proposes following the movement of every single particle within a fluid. This allows one to easily apply Newton's laws of physics to said particles. Eulerian framework, on the other hand, focuses on the field in which the fluid flows, modeling fluid quantities as a function of their position in space. This allows one to more easily model large numbers of fluid particles, which Lagrangian is much less capable of doing, by discerning the fluids relative velocity as a function of their position in space. As such, for a large mass of fluid flowing through a pipe wherein our focus would likely be on mass flow, of which velocity plays a key role in, it would be more appropriate to utilize an Eulerian framework to properly discern the fluid's velocity profile.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
          },
          {
            "question": "Does a temperature increase always correlate to a decreaes in viscosity in all fluids? If not, explain why.",
            "answer": "No. Increased temperature in a liquid does serve to decrease its viscosity as increased temperature causes an increase in kinetic energy and hence more vibrations that will allow particles to slide past one another much easier. However, this is not the same case with gases. In gases, increased temperature also increases kinetic energy, but this increase correlates to a higher particle collision rate, which in turn produces more resistance to movement, and hence higher viscosity. As temprature increasess, viscosity of liquids decrease, and viscosity of gases increase. Although this is almost contradictory, it must be understood, since gases and liquids should therefore be treated differently when it comes to assessing their viscous effects on flow.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
          },
          {
            "question": "Describe Bernoulli's Equation, its assumptions, and a use case.",
            "answer": "Bernoulli's Equation is the fundamental equation regarding following the flow of a fluid along a streamline, relating pressure, density, and velocity in one compact equation. Given quantities at one point, we can always determine the quantities at another point, provided they are connected by the same streamline. The main assumptions made are that the flow is isentropic, that no heat is being added to the system, and that the flow is incompressible. A good use case is determining the difference in flow quantities on two sides of an orifice. We can measure the pressure and velocity on one side and given a fixed temperature, the density of the fluid will not change. Now, given either velocity or pressure, we can work out the missing quantities. Change in height can also be easily factored in to the equation if it is pertinent.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
          },
          {
            "question": "What is the difference between static and stagnation pressure, and how would you measure them?",
            "answer": "Static pressure is the pressure of the fluid as it is in motion, or retains its velocity. Stagnation pressure is the pressure of the fluid if it were to be isentropically slowed to rest. To measure them, you would use two different types of pitot tubes. One is an invasive design, where the pitot tube is inserted into the flow and aligned parallel to the flow. This allows measurement of stagnation pressure by reducing velocity of the stream to zero. To measure static pressure, you would use a pitot tube aligned perpendicular to the flow without extending into the flow. This prevents stagnation of the flow and thus you are able to measure the pressure of the flow without altering its velocity.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
          },
          {
            "question": "What is the difference between an extensive and an intensive property, and list some corresponding examples.",
            "answer": "The only difference between extensive and intensive properties is that extensive properties change as the amount of the matter changes, such as mass or volume. Intensive properties, on the other hand do not change as more matter is added, such as temperature or pressure. However, extensive properties can be normalized to their intensive counterparts, such as specific volume, by dividing the value by mass. This works because it now tells us the characteristics of the matter as an intrinsic value related to the mass, which is the defnition of an intensive property. This can be extremely useful, such as when determining specific impulse, where it is normal to compare engine efficiency as a function of their impulse relative to vehicle mass, which aids in unbiased analysis of propulsion systems.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
          },
          {
            "question": "What is the main concern when attempting to determine fluid flow behavior in high differential pressure testing?",
            "answer": "The main concern is choking the flow. When the differential between downstream and upstream pressures reaches a certain level, the flow becomes choked, wherein the mass flow through the choked area does not change, no matter how much differential pressure is increased. This makes it near-impossible to record accurate and meaningful data past the point of choked flow. The best way to avoid choked flow is to prevent the main contributing factors. That is: length of the pipe, smallest area of pipe, and skin friction coefficient. The longer the pipe, the smaller the area of the pipe, and the higher the skin friction coefficient, the more likely flow is to choke. When flow is choked, the mass flow through the pipe does not increase, no matter how much the downstream pressure is decreased.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
          },
          {
            "question": "Why are gas property tables so important in the study of thermodynamics?",
            "answer": "We use gas property tables to relate Mach number to ratios between pressure, temperature, and density, as well as data for specific Mach and gamma (ratio of specific heat capacity to specific enthalpy) relations since those equations are extremely difficult to solve numerically. Without these tables, which are solved for graphically instead of numerically, we can easily locate and utilize values to solve questions much more quickly than we would be able to otherwise. This is only possbile because of our equations are only dependent on two factors, gamma, which is the ratio between specific heat capacities at constant pressure and volume, and Mach number, which are both easily recognizable values. This makes navigating and using a gas property table much simpler and therefore so much more effective.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
          },
          {
            "question": "What are the assumptions required in order to derive equations for fluid flow across a shock wave?",
            "answer": "Fluid flow through a shock wave is non-isentropic, meaning it is irreversible, since the flow is still adiabatic as it does not transfer or gain energy from its surroundings. However, mass, momentum, and energy are conserved across a shock wave, and we can therefore employ equations for this. Using continuity (conservation of mass), conservation of momentum, and conservation of energy equations in their isentropic forms to determine the change in Mach number across a shock using the following relation: (energy * continuity)/(momentum^2). From here, we can then substitute downstream Mach into the conservation equations, and rearranging will provide upstream-downstream relations for temperature, pressurem, and fluid density in compressible flow, which is extremely useful in solving for quantities as fluid flows through a shock wave.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
          },
          {
            "question": "Describe entropy and why it is useful.",
            "answer": "Entropy, the inability of a system's thermal energy to yield useful work, is an extensive property that outlines the disorderliness of a system. The higher the entropy of the system, more disordered it is and the less energy there is that can perform useful mechanical work. Generally, entropy can not be measured as a state variable as it is not a physical quantity, but the difference between two states can be determined in order to generate powerful relations in the form of T-s diagrams, relating temperature to entropy and in turn allowing us to make sense of isobaric and isochoric processes. This allows one to determine certain pressure, temperature, and volume relations in accordance with isentropic changes in state. This also allows us to determine the irreversibility of processes. If entropy increases within a system, it cannot return to a lower state of entropy without applying work to the system. This is apparent in T-S diagrams, when a process increases in entropy the process is irreversible.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
          },
          {
            "question": "How much work is required to compress an ideal diatomic gas isobarically at 2.5 x 10^5 Pa from an initial volume of 0.015 m^3 to a final volume of 0.010 m^3?",
            "answer": "\n    import numpy as np\n    P = 250000\n    V_1 = 0.015\n    V_2 = 0.01\n    W = P * (V_1 - V_2)\n    print(str(W), 'J')\n    ",
            "explanation": "Given: Isobaric, so constant pressure, and the gas is ideal. Now we can derive the equations to solve this problem. Work = W, Pressure = P, Force = F, Area = A, Volume = V, Displacement = d. W = F * dx, F = P * A, W = P * A * dx, A * dx = dV, W = P * dV",
            "reference": ""
          },
          {
            "question": "Suppose an aerospace engineer wants to determine the skin friction coefficient in a section of 50 cm diameter piping. They perform a series of tests, wherein the values are as follows: Mach number entering the section is 1.5 and length to choked flow is 3 m. How can they determine the skin friction coefficient? List any assumptions made.",
            "answer": "\n    import numpy as np\n    fourcfL_D = 0.1361\n    D = 0.5\n    L = 3\n    cf = (0.1361*0.5) / (4*3)\n    print(str(cf))\n    ",
            "explanation": "Assuming the flow is viscous and compressible, to achieve choked flow conditions, one can use the following equation: (4*cf*L)/D, where D = diameter, L = length and cf = skin friction coefficient. Then, using a table to determine the value at Mach 1.5, we get 0.1361. This is the number we plug into the equation before. This allows us to rearrange and solve for cf.",
            "reference": ""
          },
          {
            "question": "If the average human mouth inlet area is 45 cm^2 and the density of orange juice is 15.7 g/cm^3, find the mass flow if the orange juice is entering Dave's mouth at 195 ft/min.",
            "answer": "\n    import numpy as np\n    rho = 15.7\n    v = 195\n    A = 45\n    v1 = 195 * (1/60) * (0.3048/1) * (100/1) #converts ft/min to cm/s\n    m_dot = rho * v1 * A\n    print(str(m_dot), 'g/s')\n    ",
            "explanation": "Mass flow can be determined by M_dot = rho * v * A where rho = density, v = velocity, A = area.",
            "reference": ""
          },
          {
            "question": "Elmo and Cookie Monster's houses are a comfortable 20 and sweltering 35 degrees Celsius respectively. If the mass flow rate between the two houses is 0.035 kg/s, what is the energy input needed in order to bring the two rooms to an equilibrium temperature?",
            "answer": "\n    import numpy as np\n    T1 = 273.15 + 20\n    T2 = 273.15 + 35\n    T_av = (T2-T1)/2\n    deltaT = np.abs(T_av - T1)\n    m_dot = 0.035\n    cp = 1003.5\n    Q_dot = cp*m_dot*deltaT\n    print(str(Q_dot), 'kW')\n    ",
            "explanation": "Assuming air as a perfect gas, cp = 1003.5 J/(kg*s)  We first need to convert the temperature to degrees Kelvin, then we find the average and determine the change in temperature for each house (which should be the same, just in opposite directions). Then, we use SFEE, wherein we can zero out the work, kinetic, and potential energy terms. Thus we are left with Q_dot (power) Q_dot=m_dot*(he-hi), which can be substituted for m_dot*cp(Te-Ti) or m_dot*cp(deltaT) to solve for Q_dot in units of kW.",
            "reference": ""
          },
          {
            "question": "Two adjacent pipes of diameter d at Hershey's Chocolate Factory are flowing coolant with density of 0.001112 kg/m^3 into a larger pipe of diameter 3d connecting the two inlet pipes. The incoming free-stream velocity is V and 2V respectively. Given the pressure at the outlet after the flow is completely mixed is 20 psi and V = 8 m/s, what is the incoming pressure in each pipe if both pipes have the same pressure.",
            "answer": "\n    import numpy as np\n    rho = 0.001112\n    d = 1\n    V = 8\n    p2 = 20\n    A1 = (np.pi*d*d)/4 #Area of 1 inlet pipe\n    A2 = (np.pi*(3*d)*(3*d))/4 #Area of outlet pipe\n    m_dot1 = rho * V * A1\n    m_dot2 = rho * 2 * V * A1\n    V_o = (m_dot1 + m_dot2)/(rho * A2)\n    m_dotout = rho * V_o * A2\n    p1 = (m_dotout * V_o - (m_dot1 * V + m_dot2 * 2 * V) + p2 * A2) / (2 * A1)\n    print(str(p1), 'psi')\n    ",
            "explanation": "Assume incompressible and steady flow and ignore viscous effects. Using conservation of mass, we set m_dot = rho * V * (pi*d^2)/4, such that m_dotin = m_dotout becomes m_dot1 + m_dot2 = m_dotout => rho * V * (pi*d^2)/4 + rho * 2V * (pi*d^2)/4 = rho * V_o * (pi*(3d)^2)/4. Solve for V_o. Then, we can use conservation of momentum to determine the incoming static pressures. F + sum(p*A) = sum(m_dot*v) => 0 + p1 * 2*(pi*(d)^2)/4 - p2 * (pi*(3d)^2)/4 = m_dotout * V_o - m_dot1 * V - m_dot2 * 2V. Rearrange, plug in values and solve to find p1. (Diameter of the pipe is not given, but we can see it cancels out in the equation, so plugging in 1 in the calculations will not affect the results.)",
            "reference": ""
          },
          {
            "question": "If SpaceX's Raptor engines have a specific impulse of 380 s, using air cp = 1.005 kJ/(kg*K) and inlet temperature of 525 degrees Kelvin, what is the Mach number of flow input required",
            "answer": "\n    import numpy as np\n    I_sp = 380\n    cp = 1.005\n    T_0 = 525\n    val = np.sqrt(cp * T_0)\n    imp = I_sp / val\n    print(str(imp))\n    #Find this number in gas properties table and we get that the Mach number is between Mach 0.2 and 0.3\n    ",
            "explanation": "Since specific impulse is just F/m_dot, we can use F/(m_dot * sqrt(cp * T_0)) to determine the value we need to reference in our gas properties table, assuming gamma is 1.4 for an ideal diatomic gas (air). This will provide us the correct Mach number the input flow should enter the engine at for our given inlet conditions.",
            "reference": ""
          },
          {
            "question": "Graph the relationships between isobaric, isochoric, isentropic, adiabatic, and isothermal processes on T-dS and P-V diagrams.",
            "answer": "\n    import numpy as np\n    import matplotlib.pyplot as plt\n    plt.plot([2,2],[1,12],'b-',[5,5],[6,19],'b-',[1,2,3,4],[6,8,12,18],'r--',[3,4,5,7,8],[3,4,5,11,16],'r--',[1,2,4,6],[8,8.5,10,13],'g--',[4,5,7,9],[5,5.5,7.5,10],'g--')\n    plt.axis([0, 10, 0, 20])\n    plt.text(3,15,'P2')\n    plt.text(7,13,'P1')\n    plt.text(8,8,'V1')\n    plt.text(4,11,'V2')\n    plt.text(2.25,5,'S1')\n    plt.text(5.25,18,'S2')\n    plt.title('T-S Graph')\n    plt.gca().get_xaxis().set_visible(False)\n    plt.gca().get_yaxis().set_visible(False)\n    plt.plot([2,3,5,7,9],[17,11,8,7,6.5],'y-',[2,3,4,5,7,9],[16,8,6,5,3.5,3]'y-',[2,3,4,5,7,9],[18,15,12,11,10,9.5],'y-',[4,5,6,7,9],[12,9,7,5.5,3],'p--')\n    plt.axis([1, 10, 0, 20])\n    plt.text(6,12,'Isothermal processes')\n    plt.text(8,2,'T1')\n    plt.text(8,7.5,'T2')\n    plt.text(8,10.5,'T3')\n    plt.text(6.5,4.5,'Adiabatic process')\n    plt.title('P-V Graph')\n    plt.gca().get_xaxis().set_visible(False)\n    plt.gca().get_yaxis().set_visible(False)\n    ",
            "explanation": "Isobaric means constant pressure, isochoric means constant volume, and isentropic means constant entropy. Thus, on a T-S diagram, I would graph an isentropic process as a vertical line. For isobaric and isochoric processes, they would be shaped like a second order polynomial, with isobaric being steeper than isochoric due to the behavior of the TdS equations. TdS=dU+vdP and TdS=dH-vdP. Replacing dH and dU with CpdT and CvdT, we can see that the slope of the isochoric process will be greater than the isobaric process, as denoted by the V lines as opposed to the P lines. In a P-V diagram, the isotherms (T) represent constant temperature processes, while the blue dashed line represents an adiabatic one, as even though there is no heat exchange between the system and its surroundings, the system still may change temperature, as seen by the adiabatic process line crossing the isotherms.",
            "reference": ""
          },
          {
            "question": "Find the mass of air vented out of a fan in a day given that the density of the air is 1.2 kg/m^3 and Vdot of the air is .050 m^3/s",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nrho = 1.2  # Density (kg/m^3)\nVdot = .030  # Vdot (m^3/s)\n\n# Manipulate mass flow equation\nmdot = (rho * Vdot)  \n\nprint('Mdot equals:', mdot, 'kg/s')\n      ",
            "explanation": "This code uses a different version of the mass flow equation given that Area * velocity is equal to Vdot.",
            "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2015) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
          },
          {
            "question": "Find the initial and final temperatures of helium gas and the work required to compress it given that the initial and final specific volumes are 7 and 2 respectively and that it is compressed at 180 KPa.In addition, the gas constant of helium is 2.0769 ",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nsv1 = 7  # Specific Volume (m^3/kg)\nsv2 = 2\np1 = 180   #pressure (kPa)\nR = 2.0769 # Gas constant for Helium (kJ/Kg*k)\n\n# Manipulate the ideal gas equation (p*v = mRT)--> divide by m ---> (p*v/m = RT)\n#v/m = specific volume = sv\nT1 = (p1 * v1)/R # Temperature (K)\n\n#Pressure is constant (T2/T1 = V2/V1)\nT2 = (sv2/sv1)*T1\n\n# Pressure is constant, work integral  = integral(pdv) = P(v2-v1)\nwork = p1 * (sv2-sv1)\n\nprint('Initial temperature is:', T1, 'K', 'Final Temperature is:', T2, 'K', 'and work equals:', work, 'kJ')\n      ",
            "explanation": "This code uses the Ideal Gas Laws and the work equation to find the intial and final temperatures and the work done on the gas.",
            "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2015) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill." 
          },
          {
            "question": "Find the power output and thermal efficiency of a power plant given that the rate of heat supply is 290 GJ/h and the heat loss is 139 GJ/h",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nQdoth = 290 # Rate of heat in (GJ/h)\nQdotl # Rate of heat out(GJ/h)\n\n#Net power output is Qdotin - Qdotout\nWnet = Qdoth - Qdotl\n\n# Find thermal efficiency (useful work/heat input)\nnth = Wnet / Qdoth * \n\nprint('Net work is:', Wnet, 'GJ/h', 'Thermal efficiency is:', nth, '%')\n      ",
            "explanation": "This code uses the thermal efficiency equation and heat exchange theorems to calculate the work output and thermal efficiencies. ",
            "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2015) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
          },
          {
            "question": "A plastic tank is filled with water. Determine the total weight given that the density of the water is 1000 kg/m^3, volume of the water is .4 m^3 and weight of the tank is 5kg",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nrho = 1000  # Density (kg/m^3)\nMtank = 3  # Mass of the tank (kg)\nV = .4  # Volume (m^3)\n\n# Use the mass equation; m = rho*v\nmw = rho * V\n\n#Find total mass\nmtot = mw + mtank\n\nprint('Total mass:', mtot, 'kg')\n      ",
            "explanation": "This code utilizes the equation for mass and finds the total mass for the system.",
            "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2015) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill." 
          },
          {
            "question": "Air is compressed steadily by a compressor. The air temp is maintained constant by heat rejection to the surroundings.Determine the rate of entropy change given that the work in is 15 kW and the temperature is 25 degrees celcius.",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nT = 25  # Temperature  (degrees Celcius)\nWin = 15 # Work (kW)\n\n# The work in is equal to the heat out\nQdot = Win\n\n# Use the equation for change in entropy equation. ds = dq/T + ds_irrev\nds = -Qdot / (T + 273.15)\n\nprint('Final change in entropy is :', ds, 'W/K')\n      ",
            "explanation": "This code uses the formula for entropy of a system. This is underlined by the assumptions that this is a steady flow process, kinetic and potential energy changes are negligible, and there are no irreversibilities due to friction.",
            "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2015) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill." 
          },
          {
            "question": "A 7 meter high cylindrical container is filled with equal volumes of water and oil. Find the gauge pressure between the top and bottom of the container. The density of the oil is 800 kg/m^3 and the density of the water is 1000 kg/m^3",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nrhow = 1000  # Density (kg/m^3)\nrhoo = 800  # Density (kg/m^3)\ngrav = 9.81\n\n# equal volumes of each so heights are evenly split\nh = 7 / 2\n\n# Find the gauge pressure for each piece (delp = rho * g * delh)\ndelpw = rhow * grav * h / 1000\ndelpo = rhoo * grav * h / 1000\n\n#Add to get the total pressure\ngaugepressure = delpw + delpo\n\nprint('Final gauge pressure:', gaugepressure, 'kPa')\n      ",
            "explanation": "This code uses the equation for pressure given a height, delp = rho * g * h. The assumption is that the density is uniform throughout each piece.",
            "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2015) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill." 
          },
          {
            "question": "Find the power generation potential from a hydraulic turbine-generator that is generating electricity from a large reservoir. The reservoir is 120m high and the mass flow rate through the generator is 2500 kg/s. ",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nz = 120 # Height (m)\nmdot = 2500 # Mass flow rate (kg/s)\ngrav = 9.81  # Velocity 1 (m/s)\n\n# Assume all the potential energy can be turned into kinetic energy (total energy = \n# potential energy = gz\ntotenergy = grav * z\n\n#Use work equation (Qdot - Wx = E_cv + mdot_out(h_e + 1/2v_e^2 + gz_e) - \n# mdot_in(h_i + 1/2v_i^2 + gz_i))\n# energy in is only gz_i. so -Wx = -mdot * gz_i\nPowerpot = mdot * totenergy\n\nprint('Power potential is:', Powerpot, 'm/s')\n      ",
            "explanation": "This code uses the shaft work equation to find the maximum power output for a generator given some height of a reservoir.The underlying assumption is that the entire amount of energy can be converted.  ",
            "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2015) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill." 
          },
          {
            "question": "What is the difference between gauge pressure and absolute pressure?",
            "answer": "Gauge pressure is the difference between the pressure you have and atmospheric pressure and absolute pressure is the total pressure you have.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "What is the difference between Cp and Cv and how do they change?",
            "answer": "Cp and Cv are specific heat constants under two different constraints. Cv is the specific heat constant under a constant volume, and Cp is the specific heat constant under constant pressure. The equations for Cv and Cp respectively are (du/dt)_v and (dh/dt)_p. When a gas is semi-perfect, Cp and Cv are functions of temperature, but when a  gas is perfect, Cp and Cv are constants.  ",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "What is entropy?",
            "answer": "Entropy is an extensive property that defines the limit on extracting useful work from a system. It increases with irreversibility and increases in temperature.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "What can affect the energy of a system?",
            "answer": "Doing work on a system and adding heat to a system can raise the energy of that system. In addition, you can raise or lower the height, speed up or slow down the system, or change the enthalpy. You can see this in the steady flow momentum equation: (Qdot - Wx = E_cv + mdot_out(h_e + 1/2v_e^2 + gz_e) - mdot_in(h_i + 1/2v_i^2 + gz_i))",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "What is the difference between a control volume and a system boundary?",
            "answer": "Mass cannot cross a system boundary. Energy in the form of work or heat however can cross that boundary. The mass of the things in the boundary do not change but the size can change. In a control volume, the size is fixed but because of this, mass is permitted to cross its boundaries. A control volume can also move at a constant speed. ",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "What is work and what does it represent?",
            "answer": "Work is a mode of transfering energy to a system from its surroundings. It can take many forms, such as magnetic, mechanical, or electric work. Mechanical work is when a system is moved by forces acting on the boundary. This work is very common.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "What makes a process reversible or irreversible?",
            "answer": "A process is reversible if the system and surroundings can be returned to the states they were originally at. All reversible processes are quasi-equilibrium processes meaning that they are done in very small steps and take place slowly. Some examples of irreversible processes are turbulence and heat transfer without a heat source. ",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "What does Bernoulli's equation represent and when can it not be used?",
            "answer": "Bernoulli's equation gives the pressure change along a streamline in terms of height change and velocity change. This is only valid along streamlines and it cannot be used when the flow is compressiple, viscid or unsteady.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "How does friction change the velocity profile in a pipe?",
            "answer": "Friction causes the speed profile to reflect a parabola where the center of the pipe has the greatest speed and the ends are lower. This is termed a favorable profile.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "What is the difference between Couette flow and Pouseille flow and what happens when they are combined?",
            "answer": "Couette flow is a type of viscous flow where one plate is moving an another is stationary. In that case, the flow moves at the speed of the moving plate near it and the flow is near zero at the stationary plate. On the contrary Pouseille flow is flow where both plates are stationary. This results in a parabolic flow where speed is maximum halfway between both plates. When they are combined, you can have an adverse or favorable pressure gradient. Favorable flow happens when dp/dx is less than zero so as you move from one side to the next pressure drops. This velocity profile has a direction of the moving plate. An adverse pressure gradient happens when dp/dx is greater than 0 so pressure increases as you move from one side to another. That results in a velocity profile generally pointing in the opposite side of the plate movement. ",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question" : "Consider the velocity field given by u = y/(x^2 + y^2) and v = −x/(x^2 + y^2). Calculate the equation of the streamline passing through the point (1,2).",
            "answer" : "\n                    import numpy as np\n                x = 1 #x coordinate of point streamline passes through\n                y = 2 #y coordinate of point streamline passes through\n                c = x^2 + y^2\n                print('The equation of the streamline passing through point (1,2) is x^2 + y^2 = ',c,'.')\n                ",
            "explanation" : "This code utilizes the differential equation for a streamline in two dimensions vdx - udy = 0. Substituting the given equations for v and u into this equation gives -xdx = ydy (the 1/(x^2 + y^2) cancels out). After integrating both sides and some rearranging, you get x^2 + y^2 = c (c is the constant of integration), which also means that the streamline is in the shape of a circle. Then to find the value of c, you just plug in the coordinates of the given point the streamline passes through.",
            "reference" : "Fundamentals of Aerodynamics Sixth Edition by John D. Anderson, Jr."
    },
    {
            "question" : "What is the main issue with using a system boundary to contain continuously flowing liquid?",
            "answer" : "Since a system boundary is an imaginary barrier where mass cannot enter or exit the system, the only way to conatin continuously flowing liquid is to flollow it. A control volume would be better in this scenario because they allow liquid to flow through them so long as the mass out is equal to the mass in.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference" : "https://psesh.github.io/ae2010-11/"
         },
        {
            "question" : "Consider an air particle moving along a streamline. The streamline follows a path 45 degrees above horizontal at 5 m/s. What is the particles velocity normal to the streamline?",
            "answer" : "By definition, a streamline is tangent to the local velocity vector. So the velocity of the air particle normal to the streamline would be 0 since it is following the streamline.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference" : "https://psesh.github.io/ae2010-11/"
    },
             {
            "question" : "From your knowledge on curved streamlines, where must the lowest pressure be in a tornado?",
            "answer" : "From Bernoulli's equation, we know that low pressures are related to high velocities. We also know that the fastest moving air in a curved streamline is on the inside of the streamline, and we can visualize a tornado as a circular streamline. So the lowest pressure in a tornado would be located at the center.",
            "explanation":"",     
            "reference" : "https://psesh.github.io/ae2010-11/"
    },
             {
            "question" : "Consider the floor of a race car (the underside of the car). Some aerodynamics engineers want to test a new floor design that is parallel to the road. What type of flow would the air have under the car, and where would the air be moving the fastest under the car?",
            "answer" : "Since the floor of the car is moving and the ground is stationary, the air would be experiencing couette flow. With couette flow, the fastest moving air would be closest to the moving boundary, so the fastest air would be closest to the car's floor.",
            "explanation":"", 
            "reference" : "https://psesh.github.io/ae2010-11/"
    },
        {
            "question" : "Inside of an insulated box, two copper blocks with a finite temperature difference are brought into thermal contact with each other. Is this process adiabatic, reversible, or both? and Explain why.",
            "answer" : "The system boundary is an insulated box, so there is not heat in or out of the system. When heat is tranfered over a finite temperature difference, the system finds equilibrium afterwards, meaning that the process did not happen in a quasi-equilibrium state. Since there is no heat transfer between the system and its surroundings, the process is adiabatic, but it is irreversible because the process did not occur in quasi-equilibrium.",
            "explanation":"", 
            "reference" : "https://psesh.github.io/ae2010-11/"
    },
        {
            "question" : "A car is driving on a beach going 200 km/h. It has a radiator that is 0.3 m by 0.7 m. At sea level, the density of air is approximately 1.225 kg/m3. What is the mass flow of air through the car's radiator in kg/s?",
            "answer" : "\n                    import numpy as np\n                v = 200 * (1000/3600) #converting km/h to m/s\n                a = 0.3 * 0.7 #the area of the radiator's grill\n                rho = 1.225 #the density of air\n\n                mdot = rho * a * v\n\n                print('The mass flow of air through the cars radiator is ',mdot,' kg/s.')\n                ",
            "explanation" : "This code utilizes the formula for mass flow through an area which is given by mass flow = density * area * velocity normal to the area (since the velocity is already normal to the area, the normal velocity is equal to the velocity).",
            "reference" : "Fundamentals of Aerodynamics Sixth Edition by John D. Anderson, Jr."
    },
        {
            "question" : "Consider an airfoil in a flow at standard sea level conditions with a freestream velocity of 100 m/s. At a given point on the airfoil, the pressure is 0.75E5 N/m^2. At standard sea level conditions, density is 1.23 kg/m^3 and freestream pressure is 1.01E5 N/m^2. Calculate the velocity at this point.",
            "answer": "\n                    import numpy as np\n                rho = 1.23\n                v1 = 100 #velocity before airfoil\n                p1 = 1.01 * 10**5 #pressure before airfoil\n                p2 = 0.75 * 10**5 #pressure at point on airfoil\n                v2 = ((2 * (p1-p2)/p) + v1**2)**(1/2) #equation for velocity at a point on a streamline derived from Bernoulli's equation relating pressure and velocity at two points on a streamline\n\n                print('The velocity at the point on the airfoil is ',v2,' m/s.')\n                ",
            "explanation" : "This code utilizes Bernoulli's equation relating pressure and velocity at to points on a streamline: p1 + (1/2) * rho * v1**2 = p2 = (1/2) * rho * v2**2. Rearranging this equation gives a formula for velocity down the streamline.",
            "reference" : "Fundamentals of Aerodynamics Sixth Edition by John D. Anderson, Jr."
    },
     {
            "question" : "Consider a Boeing 747 flying at a standard altitude of 12 km. The pressure at a point on the wing is 17 kPa. Assuming isentropic flow over the wing, calculate the temperature at this point.",
            "answer" : "\n                    import numpy as np\n               p2 = 20000 #pressure on wing\n               t1 = 216.66 #freestream temperature (K) at 12000 m according to appendix D in textbook\n               p1 = 19399 #freestrem pressure (Pa) at 12000 m according to appendix D in textbook\n               gamma = 1.4 #ratio of specific heats of air under standard conditions\n               t2 = t1 * (p2/p1)**((gamma-1)/gamma) #formula for temperature at point on wing from relationship between temperature and pressure for an isentropic process\n\n                print('The temperature at the point on the wing is ',t2,' K.')\n                ",
            "explanation" : "This code utilizes the equation that relates pressure and temperature for an isentropic process: p2/p1 = (t2/t1)**(gamma/(gamma-1)) where gamma is the ratio of specific heats for air under standard conditions. This equation is then rearranged for t2 which is the temperature at the point on the wing in this problem.",
            "reference" : "Fundamentals of Aerodynamics Sixth Edition by John D. Anderson, Jr."
    },
         {
            "question" : "Consider an airplane flying at a velocity of 270 m/s. Calculate its Mach number if it is flying at a standard altitude of 5 km?",
            "answer" : "\n                    import numpy as np\n               t = 255.7 #freestream temperature in kelvin at 5 km above sea level according to appendix D in the textbook\n               v = 270 #airspeed in m/s\n               gamma = 1.4 #ratio of specific heats of air under standard conditions\n               r = 287 #specific gas constant for air\n               a = (gamma * r * t)**(1/2) #equation for the speed of sound with the given conditions\n               m = v/a #equation for mach number using the previously calculated speed of sound\n\n\n                print('The Mach number of the plane flying at 5 km above sea level is ',m,'.')\n                ",
            "explanation" : "This code utilizes the equation to find the speed of sound with a given temperature assuming air is a calorically perfect gas. After finding the speed of sound with the current conditions, the equation M = v/a gives the mach number where v is the airspeed and a is the speed of sound.",
            "reference" : "Fundamentals of Aerodynamics Sixth Edition by John D. Anderson, Jr."
         },
         {
            "question" : "Consider an oblique shock wave with a wave angle of 40 degrees. The upstream flow Mach number is 2.2. Calculate the mach number behind the wave.",
            "answer" : "\n                    import numpy as np\n                    beta = 40 #wave angle in degrees\n                    theta = 14 #using the figure 9.9 in the textbook along with the mach number 2.2 and the wave angle 40 gives the deflection angle theta\n                    m1 = 2.2 #freestream mach number\n                    mn1 = m1 * np.sin(radians(beta)) #this gives a normal mach number of 1.41\n                    mn2 = 0.7314 #using mn1 in appendix B of the textbook\n                    m2 = mn2/np.sin(radians(beta-theta)) #formula for downstream mach number using wave angle, deflection angle, and downstream normal mach number (mn2)\n\n                print('The mach number behind the wave is ',m2,'.')\n                ",
            "explanation" : "This code utilizes the equation for downstream mach number using wave angle, deflection angle, and downstream normal mach number: downstream normal mach number/sin(wave angle - deflection angle).",
            "reference" : "Fundamentals of Aerodynamics Sixth Edition by John D. Anderson, Jr."
    },
         {
            "question" : "A piston in a circular pipe of diameter 0.2 m is under pressure 5kPa. The pressure in the pipe has displaced the piston 0.5 meters from its original position. What is the work done by the air pressure on the piston?",
            "answer" : "\n                    import numpy as np\n                    r = 0.2/2 #radius of pipe/piston in m\n                    p = 5000 #pressure in Pa\n                    dx = 0.5 #displacement of piston in m\n                    a = np.pi * r**2 #area of piston/pipe\n                    f = p * a #force on piston due to pressure N\n                    w = f * dx #work due to pressure Nm\n\n                print('The work done my the pressure in the pipe on the piston is ',w,' Nm.')\n                ",
            "explanation" : "This code utilizes the equation for force of pressure on a piston and the formula for mechanical work.",
            "reference" : "https://psesh.github.io/ae2010-11/"
    },
        
     {
            "question" : "Heat is transferred to a heat engine from a furnace at a rate of 100 MW. If the rate of waste heat rejection to a nearby river is 65 MW, determine the net power output and the thermal efficiency for this heat engine.",
            "answer" : "\n                    import numpy as np\n                    qdotl = 65 #low temerature reservoir heat tranfer in MW\n                    qdoth = 100 #high temerature reservoir heat tranfer in MW\n                    wdotout = qh-ql #net power out of heat engine in MW\n                    n = wdotout/qdoth #thermal efficiency of heat engine\n\n                print('The thermal efficiency of the heat engine is ',n,', and the net power output is ',wdotout,' MW.')\n                ",
            "explanation" : "This code utilizes the equation for net work output of a heat engine and effieciency of a heat engine. Also heat loss is assumed to be negligible.",
            "reference" : "Thermodynamics an Engineering Approach 5th Edition by Yunus A. Cengel and Michael A. Boles"
    },
    {
            "question" : "Explain the signifigance of the Clausius inequality in regards to a reversible cyclic system.",
            "answer" : "The Clausius inequality states that the cyclic integral of dQ/T is always less than or equal to zero, so for a process that is reversible, the cyclic integral of dQ/T will be zero. This is because when the system reverses, the integral would have to become positive if it was originally negative.",
            "explanation":"", 
            "reference" : "Thermodynamics an Engineering Approach 5th Edition by Yunus A. Cengel and Michael A. Boles"
    },
        {
            "question" : "Under what conditions is entropy conserved?",
            "answer" : "Only under idealized reversible processes, so in all irreversible cases entropy increases. Entropy is never conserved in real life.",
            "explanation":"", 
            "reference" : "Thermodynamics an Engineering Approach 5th Edition by Yunus A. Cengel and Michael A. Boles"
    },
        {
            "question" : "What is a common feature of all reversible processes?",
            "answer" : "A common feature of all reversible processes is that they must not substantially deviate from equilibrium. To do this, reversible processes occur very slowly in quasi-equilibrium.",
            "explanation":"", 
            "reference" : "https://psesh.github.io/ae2010-11/"
    },
         {
            "question" : "Consider compressible flow through a very long pipe with friction alonw with the assumptions that the flow is adiabatic and the cross sectional area of the pipe is constant (Fanno Flow). Describe what would happen if subsonic air flowed through the pipe versus supersonic air.",
            "answer" : "Friction will decrease the effective area in the pipe for the air to flow through in both cases, but for subsonic air this will cause an increase in velocity while supersonic air will decrease in velocity.",
            "explanation":"", 
            "reference" : "https://psesh.github.io/ae2010-11/"
    },
    {
        "question": "How would you determine the amount of work done in a given system by a shock wave?",
        "answer": "Shock waves do not do work on the surrounding system.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Explain the difference between heat transfer through conduction and heat transfer through convection.",
        "answer": "Conduction is when energy from more highly energetic particles is transferred to particles with less energy from inter-particle interactions. Convection is when heat moves with particles as they flow as a part of a fluid. There is no redistribution of heat during convection.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "An incompressible fluid with a constant density is flowing at 10 meters per second through a circular pipe with a radius of 0.5 meters. The pipe then decreases in size so that it now has a radius of 0.15 meters. Find the velocity of the fluid in the section of the pipe with reduced size.",
        "answer": "\n\t    import numpy as np\n\t\n\t    v1 = 0.5\n\t    r2 = 0.15\n\t    v1 = 10\n\t    A1 = r1*2*3.14   #Calculating the area of the large pipe\n\t    A2 = r2*2*3.14   #Calculating the area of the small pipe\n\t    v2 = (A1*v1)/A2.  #Calculating the second velocity\n\t\n\t    print(\"Velocity through the smaller pipe section:\", V2, \"meters per second\")\n\t    ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the velocity of flow of an incompressible fluid in a circular pipe after the radius changes. This is done by using the mass flow rate equation m=pvA where m is the mass flow rate (which is the same in both sections of the pipe), p is the density (which is also the same in both pipe sections), v is the flow velocity, and A is the area of the pipe.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "After a system undergoes an irreversible process can it be returned to its original state? If so, how?",
        "answer": "A system that undergoes an irreversible process can be returned to its original state by undergoing the appropriate heat transfer.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "What is a heat reservoir and what assumption is often made regarding them?",
        "answer": "A heat reservoir is a body that acts as either a source or sink of heat and they are often assumed to have an infinite heat capacity.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "In what range of Mach numbers is flow assumed to be incompressible?",
        "answer": "Fluids are assumed to be incompressible for Mach numbers less than 0.3.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "If the temperature of a gas in an enclosed space increases, what is likely to happen to the pressure and volume of said gas?",
        "answer": "The pressure of the gas would likely increase since a higher temperature is the result of particles having more energy. This results in the particles wanting to move more, creating more inter-molecular collisions, increasing the pressure inside the space. The volume of the gas would not change due to the gas being held in an enclosed space.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the Magnus effect?",
        "answer": "The Magnus effect is the term for the lift force that is applied to an object moving through a fluid while undergoing rotation. The direction of this lift force is dependent upon the direction of the rotation.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "What are possible explanations for an airfoil experiencing flow separation?",
        "answer": "The airfoil could be at a high angle of attack, the airfoil could be accelerating, the flow could be non-uniform, or the airfoil\u2019s angle of attack could be varying.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "A stream of air at a constant velocity of 25 meters per second is attached to a circular object with a radius of 3 meters for a period of time at sea level. Assuming the stream has a constant height of 0.2 meters and a constant area, what is the surface pressure of the circular object? Assume the air density is 1.23 kg per meter^3.",
        "answer": "\n\t    import numpy as np\n\t\n\t    v = 25\n\t    r = 3\n\t    h = 0.2\n\t    rho = 1.23\n\t    atm_pressure = 101325\n\t    surface_pressure = atm_pressure - (rho * (v^2) * np.ln((r + h)/r))\n\t\n\t    print(\u201cSurface pressure on the face of the circular object:\u201d, surface_pressure, \u201cPascals\u201d)\n\t    ",
        "explanation": "The equation to solve this question is obtained by rearranging and integrating the equation for the pressure gradient in the normal direction along a curve which is given as dp/dn = rho*(v^2)/r.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "A chamber contains a gas with at a pressure of 15 MPa, a volume of 0.1 m^3, and a mass of 10 kg. What is the temperature of this gas?",
        "answer": "\n\t    import numpy as np\n\t\n\t    m = 25\n\t    P = 15 * 10^6\n\t    V = 0.1\n\t    R = 287\n\t    T = (P * V) / (R * m)\n\t\n\t    print(\u201cTemperature of the gas:\u201d, T, \u201cKelvin\u201d)\n\t    ",
        "explanation": "This problem is solved by using the ideal gas equation PV = mRT where R is the ideal gas constant.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "A powerplant is built that cycles between a natural hot spring and a cool pond nearby. The temperature of the hot spring is 90 degrees Celsius while the temperature of the pond is 45 degrees. Assuming no heat is lost during the transition between the two bodies of water, what is the maximum thermal efficiency?",
        "answer": "\n\t    import numpy as np\n\t\n\t    T1 = 90 + 273.15\n\t    T2 = 45 + 273.15\n\t    thermal_eff = (1 - (T2 / T1)) * 100\n\t\n\t    print(\u201cMaximum Thermal Efficiency:\u201d, thermal_eff, \u201c%\u201d)\n\t    ",
        "explanation": "The max thermal efficiency assumes all heat loss is used to create work. This means that after converting from Celsius to Kelvin all that is required is subtracting the ratio between the lower heat and the heat source from 1.",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "According to Laplace, how does the temperature of a fluid react when exposed to a strong sound wave?",
        "answer": "The temperature will change adiabatically. The pressure changes as well.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the Mach number of a flow downstream of a normal shock if the flow had a Mach number of 0.8 upstream of the shock? Assume gamma equals 1.4.",
        "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n\t\n\t    M1 = 0.8\n\t    gamma = 1.4\n\t\n\t    M2 = ((1 + ((gamma \u2013 1) / 2) * M1^2) / (gamma * (M1^2) \u2013 (gamma \u2013 1) / 2))^(1/2)\n\t\n\t    print(\u201cMach number downstream:\u201d, M2)\n\t    ",
        "explanation": "To find the answer the Mach number normal shock formula was used.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Calculate the specific gas constant of a gas inside of a container if that gas is 35% Helium (4.003 g/mol) and 65% Nitrogen (14.007 g/mol).",
        "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n\t\n\t    mH = 4.003\n\t    pH = 0.35\n\t    mN = 14.007\n\t    pN = 0.65\n\t    R = 8.314\n\t\n\t    m = pH * mH + pN * mN\n\t\n\t    R_gas = R / m\n\t\n\t    print(\u201cSpecific gas constant:\u201d, R_gas, \u201cJ / (kg * K)\u201d)\n\t    ",
        "explanation": "By adding together the percent masses of both elements present the molecular mass of the gas can be found. Dividing the ideal gas constant by the found molecular mass of the gas gives the specific gas constant.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the drop in pressure across a pipe if the pipe has a length of 700 meters and a radius of 0.25 meters? The velocity is 34 meters per second and the fluid has a viscosity of 2.5 kilograms / (meters * seconds).",
        "answer": "\n\t    import numpy as np\n\t\n\t    L = 700\n\t    r = 0.25\n\t    v = 34\n\t    visc = 2.5\n\t\n\t    P = (8 * L * visc * v) / (r^2)\n\t\n\t    print(\u201cPressure Drop:\u201d, P, \u201cPascals\u201d)\n\t    ",
        "explanation": "To find the answer the Mach number normal shock formula was used.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Why is cavitation typically detrimental to liquid fluid systems, and why are cavitating venturis not subject to these issues?",
        "answer": "Cavitation occurs when local static pressure in a liquid is reduced below the vapor pressure of said fluid, causing vapor bubbles to form and nearly immediately collapse, causing violent pressure waves. These pressure waves can cause erosion, generate significant noise, and increase peak stresses which can damage equipment. Cavitating venturis are not subject to these issues because the cavitation is localized to an area near the throat, where geometry and material choices are optimized to counteract detrimental effects. Essentially, it boils down to an issue of control. Cavitation that does not suit a particular purpose is undesirable, but when it is useful, engineers optimize designs to mitigate issues.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Supersonic wind tunnels contain diffusers to slow down exiting fluid flow. Unlike nozzles, which usually have a smooth shift from convergent to divergent geometry, supersonic diffusers often transition between converging and diverging geometry using a constant area pipe. Why?",
        "answer": "Shock waves in pipes typically occur due to changes in cross-sectional area and geometry causing streamlines to turn into or away from one another, causing oblique shocks and expansion fans, respectively. Keeping area and geometry constant allow oblique shocks from the contracting geometry to reflect and weaken gradually, encouraging laminar flow, reducing the risk of turbulence and high-intensity shocks. Also, practically, pipes are significantly easier to machine due to cylindrical symmetry, making designs more cost-effective.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "How are Euler's equations modified to generate the Navier-Stokes equations for fluid flow?",
        "answer": "An additional viscosity term is introduced into the Newtonian equations for material derivative of flow, contributing to the addition of a term equal to the viscosity multiplied by the Laplacian of the velocity field. This makes the equations of motion significantly more complex, and is partially responsible for why the Navier-Stokes equations are both difficult and significant enough to justify their spot as a Millenium Problem.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "A Pitot tube measures stagnation pressure when directly facing fluid flow, but measures static pressure orientated away from fluid flow. Explain why the optimal configuration to measure static pressure is perpendicular to fluid flow, and how pitot tubes have to be modified for the supersonic regime.",
        "answer": "Ideally, the Pitot tube would still measure static pressure at any angle away from fluid flow. However, in practice, other angles besides perpendicular place the opening further downstream from the pipe geometry and can induce flow separation or turbulence which may alter the fluid velocity field and affect the accuracy of pressure readings. In the supersonic regime, the setup does not need to be altered besides for structural integrity. However, we must modify our analysis of the measurements, as in supersonic flow a Pitot tube will generate a bow shock in front that will reduce the stagnation pressure and give inaccurate readings about the general flow.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "What is enthalpy and why is it useful for constant pressure processes?",
        "answer": "Enthalpy can be thought of as the sum of internal energy of a system and work required to establish that system's physical dimensions from an initial zero volume to a final volume at constant pressure. This quantity is useful for constant pressure processes because for perfect gasses at constant pressure, change in enthalpy is linear with change in temperature. Also, since enthalpy represents a Legendre transformation such that pressure is a variable, i.e. E(S,V) becomes H(S,P), constant pressure simplifies the description of energy transfer to one degree of freedom when enthalpy is used.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the material derivative in the Eulerian description and why is the Eulerian description more useful for control volumes?",
        "answer": "The material derivative in the Eulerian description is the sum of the advection and time derivative operators. Advection describes changes in a value due to movement, whereas the time derivative describes generation or removal due to all other factors. This description is more useful for control volumes because control volumes impose conservation of mass and hence we often analyze them from the perspective of steady-state flow. This nullifies the time derivative and allows us to focus on advection alone. The Eulerian perspective also allows us to calculate in a static universal reference frame which makes calculus far less cumbersome.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Under what circumstances are streamlines and pathlines the same?",
        "answer": "Streamlines are tangent to fluid velocity at any given time based on absolute position. Pathlines are the trajectories of individual particles. The velocity of any given particle will be tangent to its pathline at any given time, but in unsteady fluid flow the pathline of a particle marks a history of fluid velocity, whereas streamlines are always current. Hence, streamlines and pathlines are identical only when flow is steady, and hence the present is the same as the history.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "In Fanno flow, why can friction cause fluid flow to accelerate?",
        "answer": "Friction with the pipe walls causes a loss of mechanical energy, increasing fluid entropy while decreasing stagnation pressure along the duct length. For a calorically perfect gas, entropy is maximized at Mach 1, so regardless of the fluid velocity, it will approach the speed of sound as it moves along the duct. The boundary layers formed due to the friction result in a virtual narrowing of the pipe, intuitively requiring a fluid velocity increase for subsonic flow.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Why does viscosity change differently under temperature variation for gasses compared to liquids?",
        "answer": "Viscosity increases with temperature for gasses but decreases with temperature for liquids. In gasses, the mean free path of particles is much greater and momentum transfer is largely a function of molecular speed, which is a function of temperature. Hence for hotter gasses, viscosity increases. In liquids, molecules are constrained by bonds which enhance momentum transfer. While there is no systematic microscopic theory for liquid viscosity, increased temperature makes particles more likely to overcome the attractive forces of bonds and hence reduce momentum transfer, thus reducing viscosity.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "A pipe bends 90 degrees. All cross-sections perpendicular to fluid flow are circular, but of variable area. The initial cross sectional area is 0.1m^2, but decreases gradually towards the end of the bend to 0.05m^2. The velocity is 10m/s at the inlet with a pressure of 200kPa gauge, and you can take the density of water to be 1g/mL. Calculate the magnitude of the pressure forces acting parallel and perpendicular to the initial direction of fluid flow entering the bend.",
        "answer": "\n    A_1 = 0.1 # m^2\n    v_1 = 10 # m/s\n    A_2 = 0.05 # m^2\n    v_2 = v_1 * A_1 / A_2 # m/s\n    rho = 1000 # kg/m^3\n    p_1 = 200000 # Pa\n    p_2 = p_1 - 0.5 * rho * (v_2**2 - v_1**2) # Pa\n    F_para = p_1 * A_1\n    F_perp = p_2 * A_2\n    print(f'The perpendicular force magnitude is: {F_perp}N')\n    print(f'The parallel force magnitude is: {F_para}N')\n            ",
        "explanation": "We can assume incompressible flow. Since the area at the exit is halved, velocity must be doubled. We can then use Bernoulli's equation to calculate the exit pressure as 50kPa gauge. Finally, we calculate the pressure forces. Note that there are also momentum forces due to momentum fluxes through the control volume.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Taylor-Couette flow is Couette flow between two infinitely long coaxial cylinders. The inner cylinder has a radius R and rotates at a constant angular velocity omega. The outer cylinder has radius 2R but does not rotate. Assuming the angular velocity is sufficiently slow as for the flow to be approximately laminar, the flow is incompressible, and being given the azimuthal velocity as v(r)=4/3*omega*R^2/r-1/3*w*r, calculate kinetic energy stored in a length L of the pipe. Then, use values L=2m, R=3m, w=0.5Hz, and calculate the value numerically.",
        "answer": "\n    import numpy\n    omega = 0.5 # Hz\n    L = 2 # m\n    R = 3 # m\n    KE = 14 * numpy.pi / 27 * L * omega**2 * R**3\n    print(f'The total kinetic energy in this section of pipe is {KE/numpy.pi}pi J = {round(KE, 2)}J.')\n            ",
        "explanation": "Differential contributions to the kinetic energy can be expressed as 0.5*rho*v^2, where v is the velocity at a point in the fluid field and rho is the uniform density. We can then integrate over the section of pipe in cylindrical coordinates to sum over these differential contributions and calculate the total kinetic energy. The integral works out to KE = 14pi/27 * L * omega^2 * R^3. Quite nicely, the numerical answer is KE = 7pi Joules.",
        "reference": "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taylor%E2%80%93Couette_flow,https://farside.ph.utexas.edu/teaching/336L/Fluid/node137.html"
      },
      {
        "question": "Dr. Robotnik, in designing a new rocket booster for his Mega Rocket Shoes, models the rocket as a heat engine that performs work in the form of thrust in transforming heat into work accelerating an incompressible exhaust. We assume the fluid ejects from the approximately massless rocket nozzle at 50m/s. Suppose the combustion chamber operates at a temperature of 2000K and the ambient air is at room temperature. The combustion chamber provides a heat flux of 60000W. Using the ideal gas law, calculate the maximum possible thrust such an rocket thruster can produce. If Dr. Robotnik weighs 200kg and aims the thruster straight down, can it counteract his weight and allow him to levitate?",
        "answer": "\n    T_C = 295 # K\n    T_H = 2000 # K\n    eta = 1 - T_C / T_H # dimensionless, represents maximum efficiency\n    print(f'The maximum efficiency of this engine is {eta}.')\n    Q_dot = 60000 # W\n    W_dot = eta * Q_dot # W\n    v_e = 50 # m/s\n    F_thrust = 2 * W_dot / v_e # N\n    g = 9.81 # m/s\n    F_g = 200 * g # N\n    print(f'The thrust produced is {F_thrust}N.')\n    if F_thrust >= F_g:\n      print(f'This thrust is sufficient to lift Dr. Robotnik, as {F_thrust}N >= {F_g}N.')\n    else:\n      print(f'This thrust is insufficient to lift Dr. Robotnik, as {F_thrust}N < {F_g}N.')\n            ",
        "explanation": "This problem is somewhat whimsical, and so it is best if we stay within the safe and solid grounds of physics and mathematics to calculate the numerical answer. The maximum efficiency of a heat engine is given for a reversible Carnot cycle, being eta=1-T_C/T_H. We can them calculate work as W_dot = eta * Q_dot, a function of the heat flux into the thruster. Finally, we apply this as force to calculate whether the thruster can support Dr. Robotnik. Note that W_dot = 1/2 * rho * Q * v_e^2, where v_e is the exhaust velocity. We arrive at this term by treating Dr. Robotnik as a control volume and taking the momentum flux across the volume boundary from exhaust. Then, F_thrust = p_dot = m_dot * v_e = 2 * W_dot / v_e. We find that F_thrust = 2046N, which is just barely enough to lift Dr. Robotnik, who weights 1962N. Since we only care about momentary results, we can neglect factors such as fuel depleting over time and requiring us to utilize a rocket equation.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Suppose you have a choked converging-diverging air nozzle with an exit area of 1m^2 and exhaust density of 1.8kg/m^3. Calculate the throat area that would be required for perfect expansion if the ambient pressure is 101.325kPa.",
        "answer": "\n    import numpy\n    gamma = 7/5\n    p_a = 101325 # Pa\n    rho_ex = 1.8 # kg/m^3\n    T = 295 # K\n    R = 287.053\n    a = numpy.sqrt(gamma * R * T) # m/s\n    lambda_1 = (0.5 * (gamma + 1))**((gamma)/(1-gamma)) * (1 + gamma) # This is an algebraic placeholder\n    lambda_2 = (0.5 * rho_ex * a**2 * lambda_1 - p_a * gamma) # This is an algebraic placeholder\n    M_2 = numpy.sqrt((1-lambda_1) * p_a / lambda_2) # This is an algebraic placeholder\n    A_star = 1\n    A = A_star * (2 / (gamma + 1) + (gamma - 1) / (gamma + 1) * M_2**2)**(0.5 * (gamma + 1) / (gamma - 1))\n    print(f'The cross-sectional area of the exhause nozzle exit is {round(A,2)}m^2.')\n            ",
        "explanation": "First, we take the flow to be isentropic so that p_01 = p_02. Then p_2 / p_02 = p_2 / p_1 * p_1 / p_01. We have exact formulas for both of these ratios in terms of the Mach number, the former from momentum conservation via the Euler equation, the second via other isentropic relations. We take the subscript 1 to apply to the choke point so that M_1=M*=1. We then substitute p_02 in terms of p_2 and M_2, yielding an equation for M_2 in terms of the exit pressure. Since this nozzle is perfectly expanded, the exit pressure is ambient. Finally, we can solve for M_2. We can then use the A/A* relation to find the exit area given the exit Mach number M_2, yielding A=3.52m^2.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Suppose you have an aircraft travelling at a rate of 400m/s at t=0, accelerating by 4m/s^2. The aircraft is flying at an altitude of 10000ft. The density and pressure at such an altitude are 0.414kg/m^3 and 26.5kPa. Calculate the time at which the angle of the Mach cone becomes 45 degrees. Assume an isentropic, ideal gas.",
        "answer": "\n    import numpy\n    P = 26.5*1000 # Pa\n    rho = 0.414 # kg/m^3\n    R_air = 287.053 # J/kgK, R_specific for dry air\n    T = P / (rho * R_air) # K\n    gamma = 1.4\n    a = numpy.sqrt(gamma * R_air * T)\n    v = a / numpy.sin(numpy.pi / 4)\n    print(f'The plane will be flying at a speed of {round(v,2)}m/s when the Mach cone angle reaches 45 degrees.')\n    t = (v - 400) / 4\n    print(f'It will take {round(t,2)} seconds to accelerate to this speed.')\n            ",
        "explanation": "There exists an exact formula for the angle of a Mach cone: mu=arcsin(1/M). Since we assume the air is ideal and isentropic, we can calculate the temperature using the ideal gas law, and subsequently the speed of sound as a=sqrt(gamma*R*T), where R is the gas constant, gamma is the isentropic expansion factor, and T is the temperature. Note that R_specific for dry air is approximately 287 J/kgK, as can be found in a lookup table. Finally, we take v=a*csc(mu), and calculate the velocity of the plane at a 45 degree Mach cone to be 423.35m/s, corresponding to t=5.84s.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "The steam engine of an old train operates by converting heat from the fire into hot steam which operates a cyclic piston. We can model this as a heat engine between a reservoir at T_H=1000K and T_C=273K, generating a work of 8kW. Suppose that since it's a freezing winter, this engine siphons some energy to heat the passenger cars which are maintained at 297K (toasty!). Use the Clausius inequality to calculate a lower bound for which heat must be supplied by the engine to reject 2kW of heat to the passenger cars. Is this a better or worse lower bound than that imposed by energy conservation?",
        "answer": "\n    W_dot = 8000 # kW\n    T_p = 297 # K\n    T_h = 1000 # K\n    T_c = 273 # K\n    Q_p_dot = 2000 # kW\n    Q_H_dot_min = (Q_p_dot / T_p - (Q_p_dot + W_dot) / T_c) / (1 / T_H - 1 / T_C)\n    print(f'The lower bound stipulated by the Clausius inequality is that the heat rejected by the hot reservoir must exceed {Q_H_dot_min}W.')\n            ",
        "explanation": "By Clausius' inequality we have that Q_H/T_H - Q_C/T_C - Q_P/T_P <= 0, where H is the hot reservoir, C is the cold reservoir, and P is the passenger cars. Although we are working with rates, I will multiply all rates by 1 second to obtain Joule values so the naming convention is simpler (Q_H rather than Q_H_dot). Because of energy conservation, Q_C = Q_H - Q_P - W. Then, we can construct an inequality for Q_H that yields by substitution that Q_H must be greater or equal to 10.35kJ. Energy conservation implies Q_H must be at least 10kJ, so the bound imposed by the Clausius inequality is stronger.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "A quantity of unusual air slowly expands against a piston in a rectangular box until its volume doubles. The initial volume is 10L and the initial pressure is 2 bar. Unlike typical air, however, this substance is a unique mixture and exhibits polytropic index 1.8 for this process. Write a code to sketch the process on a p-V diagram and calculate the work transfer of this process.",
        "answer": "\n    import numpy as np\n    import matplotlib.pyplot as plt\n    \n    # Constants\n    n = 1.8\n    p_1 = 101325 # Pa\n    V_1 = 10 / 1000 # m^3\n    V_2 = 2 * V_1 / 1000 # m^3\n    \n    # Calculations\n    work = p_1 * V_1**n / (1-n) * (V_2**(1-n) - V_1**(1-n))\n    print(f'The work performed by the system is {-round(work,1)}J.')\n    \n    # Volume values\n    V = np.linspace(0.01, 0.02, 100)\n    \n    # Pressure values\n    p = p_1 * V_1**n / V**n / 1000\n    \n    # Plot\n    plt.plot(V, p, color='red')\n    plt.xlabel('Volume (m^3)')\n    plt.ylabel('Pressure (kPa)')\n    plt.title('Pressure vs Volume of Polytropic Expansion')\n    plt.grid(True)\n    plt.show()\n            ",
        "explanation": "To calculate the work performed by the system, we integrate over the pdV term in the fundamental constraint over the process. We make the polytropic substitution, leveraging the fact that pV^n remains constant over the process to integrate with respect to V. This yields the work done by the system, 181.4kJ. The polytropic relation yields an exact formula p(V) for us to plot on a p-V graph of the system using matplotlib.",
        "reference": "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polytropic_process"
      },
      {
        "question": "A golfer practicing at the range notices that if he hits the club lower down on the ball, creating backspin, then his shots tend to go further than if he leaves no spin on the ball. State what phenomena is going on and how it works.",
        "answer": "The Magnus Effect is taking place here, which demonstrates that when a ball is rotating through a fluid, there is an lift force created on it due to the forces of friction allowing air to stick to the ball, deflecting the air upwards as the ball is spinning backwards.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": "https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=23f1jvGUWJs"
      },
      {
        "question": "Supersonic Flow hits a wedge with an incline of 15 degrees. The resulting oblique shock angle is 55 degrees. What is the angle at which the flow continues, and what happens to the static pressure, static temperature, and Mach number of the fluid after the shock?",
        "answer": "The flow will follow the wedge angle of 15 degrees and static pressure and static temperature will increase, while Mach number will decrease as a result of the shock relations",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Explain the difference between heat, enthalpy, and temperature.",
        "answer": "In thermodynamics, heat refers to the transfer of thermal energy from a hotter system to a cooler temperature, while temperature is the measure of the average kinetic energy of all the molecules in a system. Enthalpy simply measures the amount of heat that flows between a system and its surroundings, therefore at a constant pressure, enthalpy and heat are the same value.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": "https://www.khanacademy.org/science/chemistry/thermodynamics-chemistry/internal-energy-sal/a/heat, https://ch301.cm.utexas.edu/thermo/#enthalpy/enthalpy-all.php"
      },
      {
        "question": "Why does honey flow out of a jar slower and appear to be thicker than water flowing out of a bottle? Name what this property is and what it entails.",
        "answer": "The property being described is called viscocity and it measures the fluids resistance to flow. This resistance is a result of internal friction between molecules which is related to the molecular structure of the fluid. Thus honey has more internal friction that water due to its molecular composition.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": "https://www.princeton.edu/~gasdyn/Research/T-C_Research_Folder/Viscosity_def.html"
      },
      {
        "question": "Explain the difference between laminar and turbulant flow and what property quantifies this difference",
        "answer": "Laminar flow describes flow that is very uniform and constant at all points, whereas turbulant flow is very irregular and chaotic. The reynolds number quantifies this by using a nondimensional expression, where a low value represents laminar flow and a high value represents turbulant flow.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": "https://www.engineersyard.com/fluid-mechanics-interview-questions/#q3-differentiate-between-laminar-flow-and-turbulent-flow-give-an-example-of-each"
      },
      {
        "question": "A hollow  perfectly-insulated cube contains gas that is confined to one side by a diaphram, while there is a vacuum on the other side. If the diaphram broke, describe what would happen to the pressure, volume, and temperature. Additionally, state whether this process is reversible or irreversible and why.",
        "answer": "If the diaphram broke, pressure would decrease, volume would increase and temperature would remain constant. Pressure decreaased and volume increased due to the ideal gas relations. Temperature is constant because there is no heat being added to the system and no work is being done because there must be resistance for work to occur. Therefore, according to the first law of thermodynamics (U = Q + W), dU = 0, thus dT = 0. Additionally, this process is considered irreversible, because it will require work to bring the system back to its original state.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": "https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-01-unified-engineering-i-ii-iii-iv-fall-2005-spring-2006/resources/q7_9/"
      },
      {
        "question": "Can the entropy of an ideal gas change during an isothermal process?",
        "answer": "Yes, an isentropic process must be adiabatic and reversible, neither of which depend on whether the system is isothermal. For example, a gas expanding at a constant temperature would be isothermal, but entropy would still increase since molecules are able to move around in more places with a constant kinetic energy",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill. p406"
      },
      {
        "question": "When watching a tank pressurization sequence, you notice that the pressure rise over time is in exponential decay, even though the valve is a simple ball valve that is either fully open or closed. Why does this happen?",
        "answer": "When the valve first opens and the tank is empty, there is a large pressure difference between the pressure reservoir and the tanks, however, as the tank becomes more and more full, the pressure difference decreases. The fluid particles are going to diffuse quicker when there is a large pressure drop, thus creating a funciton with a large initial slope that tapers off as the tank fills up further. This can also be though of in terms of pressure = force x area, thus more pressure difference means more force, which means more acceleration of fluid particles according to Newtons second law.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Can you explain what it means to have a Langrangian frame of reference? Also list another common frame of reference and how it differs from the Langragian view.",
        "answer": "A Langragian frame of reference involves taking a look at each induvidual fluid particle separately in order to find a desired output. The Eulerian frame of reference is also comomonly used and sets up a system boundary and deals with a system of particles moving through the boundary.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": "https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S1352231014000946#:~:text=Lagrangian%20approach%20deals%20with%20individual,of%20a%20number%20of%20particles."
      },
      {
        "question": "Imagine a water duct 1 meter tall and 0.5 meters wide bending around a 5m inner radius. Pressure Transducers at each end of the duct read a pressure drop of 50 Pa. You can assume a density of 1000 kg/m^3. What is the velocity of the fluid around the bend?",
        "answer": "\n    import numpy as np\n          \n    dp = 50 #Pa\n    ρ = 1000 #kg/m^3 \n    r1 = 5 #m (inner radius) \n    r2 = 5.5 #m (outer radius (inner + width)) \n    v = (dp/(ρ*(np.log(r2/r1))))**(1/2) \n    print('The velocity of the fluid around the bend is '+str(v)+' m/s.')\n        ",     
        "explanation": "To get our solution, we start with the relationship of flow around a bend: dp/dr = (ρ(v(r))^2)/r. Rearranging the equation we get: dp = ((ρ(v(r))^2)/r)dr. Integrating both sides over the limit of the inner and outer radius (r1 and r2), we get: ∆p = (ρ(v(r))^2)ln|r|. Rearranging for v(r) = (∆p/ρln|r2/r1|)^(½). Plug in and solve.",
        "reference": "https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=A47wqBhzEnE"
      },
      {
        "question": "You are tasked with designing a fluid feed system for an engine test stand and you need to calculate pressure loss from the tanks to the main valves. You know the volumetric flow rate of the system is 12 m^3/s and you can assume the pipe to be one long straight segment of 5 meters with a diameter of 0.0254 m. Note that the fluid has a viscosity of 1.54E-3 kg/(ms) and calculate pressure drop through the pipe.",
        "answer": "\n    import numpy as np\n          \n    mu = 1.54 * 10**(-3) #kg/ms (viscosity)  \n    Q = 12 #m^3/s (volumetric flow rate)  \n    D = 0.0254 #m (diameter)  \n    R = D/2 #m (radius)  \n    L = 5 #m (length)\n    Delta_p = (8 * mu * Q * L)/(np.pi*(R**4))  \n    print('The loss in pressure is '+str(np.around(Delta_p,3))+' Pa.') \n        ",
        "explanation": "Use the Hagen Poiseuille Equation: ∆p = (8MuQL)/(πR^4). Plug in all the values provided to find the pressure drop.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Consider a room with a rectangular floor that is 5 m by 7 m, and a 3.3 m high ceiling. The air pressure and temperature in the room are 1 atm and 25 C, respectively. Calculate the internal energy and the enthalpy of the air in the room.",
        "answer": "\n    H = 3.3 #m (height) \n    L = 4 #m (length) \n    W = 7 #(width) \n    V = H*L*W #m^3 (volume) \n    T = 273.15 + 25 #K\n    P = 1*(1.01*(10**5)) #Pa \n    R = 287 #Gas constant\n    M = (P*V)/(R*T) \n    γ = 1.4 #gamma\n    cp = (γ*R)/(γ-1) #J/kg*K (specific heat at constant pressure) \n    cv = R/(γ-1) #J/kg*K (specific heat at constant volume)\n    #Now that we have these values, we can solve for H and U: \n    H = M*cp*T #J\n    U = M*cv*T #J\n    print('The enthalpy in the room is '+str(H)+' J and the internal energy in the room is '+str(U)+' J.')\n        ",
        "explanation": "To calculate mass of air in the room, we must use M = pV/RT, where V is the volume of the room, R is the ideal gas constant for air (287) and T is the temp of the room. We will need the values of cp and cv for air. We know R to be 287 and γ = 1.4, and by using cv/cp = γ and cp – cv = R, we can derive: cp = γR/(γ-1) & cv = R/(γ-1)",
        "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill. p536 7.1"
      },
      {
        "question": "Calculate the ratio of kinetic energy to internal energy at a point in an airflow where the Mach number is 2",
        "answer": "\n    M = 2 \n    γ = 1.4 \n    ratio = (1/2)*(γ*(γ-1))*M**2 \n    print('The ratio of kinetic energy to internal energy is '+str(ratio)+'.') \n        ",
        "explanation": "We know the kinetic energy is K= 1/2mv^2 and internal energy is U = mcvT. The ratio of these leaves us with ((½)(v^2)/cvT). M = v/a, and a = sqrt(γRT), thus v^2 = M^2γRT. The T’s then cancel out and R = cp-cv, simplifying the final equation to (½)(γ(γ-1)M^2. We are given M and γ is 1.4 for air, allowing the ratio to be solved.",
        "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill. p578 8.3"
      },
      {
        "question": "Consider a venturi with a throat-to-inlet area ratio of 0.8 mounted in a flow at standard sea level conditions. If the pressure difference between the inlet and the throat is 7 lb/ft^2, calculate the velocity of the flow at the inlet. You may assume flow to be incompressible.",
        "answer": "\n    import numpy as np\n    \n    ratio = 0.8 #Ratio of A1/A2\n    ρ = 0.002377 #slug/ft^3 (sea level conditions)\n    dp = 7 #lb/ft^2\n    v1 = np.sqrt((2*(dp))/(ρ*(((1/ratio)**2)-1)))\n    print('The velocity of the flow at the inlet is '+str(v1)+' ft/s.')\n        ",
        "explanation": "Bernoullis equation and conservation of momentum can be used to find the velocity of the flow. Bernoulli's equation states that p1 + (1/2)ρv1^2 = p2 + (1/2)ρv2^(2). Consevation of momentum states that A1v1 = A2v2. Rearranging this shows that v2 = v1(A1/A2). Plugging this in to bernoullis equation and solving for v1 yields: v1 = sqrt((2(p2-p1))/(ρ((A2/A1)^2-1)).",
        "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill. p226 3.3"
      },
      {
        "question": "Consider a low-speed subsonic wind tunnel with a 12/1 contraction ratio for the nozzle. If the flow in the test section is at standard sea level conditions with a velocity of 50 m/s, calculate the height difference in a U-tube mercury manometer with one side connected to the nozzle inlet and the other to the test section.",
        "answer": "\n    import numpy as np\n          \n    ratio = 1/12 #ratio of A2/A1\n    ρ = 1.23 #kg/m3 (density of air at sea level)\n    w = 1.36*(10**4) #kg/m3 (desnity of mercury)\n    g = 9.8 #(m/s/s) #acceleration due to gravity\n    v2 = 50 #m/s (velocity of flow in test section)\n    dp = (1/2)*ρ*(v2**2) - (1/2)*ρ*(((ratio)*v2)**2)\n    #dp = wgdh\n    dh = dp/(w*g)\n    print('The change in heigh of the monometer will be '+str(dh)+' m.')\n        ",
        "explanation": "The first step to solving this problem is using bernoulli's equation to solve for pressure difference between the nozzle and test section. Bernoulli's equation can be written as p1 + (1/2)ρv1^(2) = p2 + (1/2)ρv2^(2), where v1 can be set equal to v1 = (A2/A1)v2 due to conservation of momentum. Plugging this in and solving for difference is static pressure yields: p1 - p2 = (1/2)ρv2^2 - (1/2)ρ((A2/A1)v2)^2. We also know that p1-p2 = wg(h1-h2), where w is the density of mercury in the monometer, and g acceleration due to gravity. Thus, the only unknown becomes change in height.",
        "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill. p226 3.4"
      },
          {
        "question": "Draw a P-V Diagram for a process of isobaric compression from 10 m^3 to 5 m^3 at 10 Pa. Calculate the work done from this process.",
        "answer": "\n    import numpy as np\n    import matplotlib.pyplot as plt\n        \n    x = np.array([5, 10]).reshape(2,1)\n    y = np.array([10, 10]).reshape(2,1)\n    plt.plot(x, y, 'r')\n    plt.ylabel('Pressure (Pa)')\n    plt.xlabel('Volume (m^3)')\n    plt.show()\n    p = 10 #Pa\n    v = 5 #m^2\n    W = p*v\n    print('The amount of work done during this process was '+str(W)+' J.')\n        ",
        "explanation": "In isobaric compression, pressure remains the same while volume changes, thus showing this on the graph represents a horizontal line of constant pressure and changing volume. To find work from this, we know work is the integral of p*dv, thus the area under this graph will demonstrate the total work done.",
        "reference": "https://www.khanacademy.org/science/thermal-physics-essentials/x34146f1b92e003ad:how-is-the-universe-going-to-end/x34146f1b92e003ad:pv-diagrams/e/work-from-pv-diagrams"
      },
      {
        "question": "What happens to stagnation pressure across an expansion fan and why, and how, does this differ from stagnation pressure ratios across an oblique shock?",
        "answer": "Across an expansion fan, stagnation pressure stays constant because entropy stays constant, meaning that the flow is isentropic. For a flow to be considered isentropic, the flow must be reversible and adiabatic. Since the flow turns in small angles and changes across each expansion wave are small, the flow can be considered to be in quasi-equilibrium, which means that the flow is adiabatic and reversible, thus isentropic. In an oblique shock however, stagnation pressure decreases across the shock as flow across any shock is non-isentropic, since many of the gas’ properties increase instantaneously during a shock.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why does a violation of the Kelvin-Planck statement also violates the Clausius statement?",
        "answer": "The Kelvin-Planck statement of the second law of thermodynamics states that it is impossible to construct a cyclic device with the sole effect to produce positive work while receiving heat from a single thermal reservoir, or in other words all heat from a heat reservoir cannot be converted into useful work, meaning there is a max efficiency for said process. Whereas Clausius’ statement states it is impossible to create a cyclic device with the sole effect of transferring heat from a cooler to warmer body. While these two statements refer to different configurations of a cyclic device, the consequences of these statements are equivalent to each other due to the nature of heat engines and irreversibilities from heat transfer. One way to visualize this concurrent violation is consider a violation of the Kelvin-Planck statement, where a heat engine converts all heat into useful work. Now imagine connecting that useful work into a cyclic device, so that it is able to transfer heat from a cooler to warmer body. Since the work came from a device that violates the Kelvin-Planck statement, that cyclic device that transfers heat from cooler to hotter body would also be in violation. Thus, a violation of Kelvin-Planck also violates Clausius statement.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why does Bernouli’s Principle only apply along streamlines, and not across streamlines?",
        "answer": "Bernoulli’s Principle expresses the pressure variation along streamlines as a function of velocity and height, and is valid for flows that are steady, incompressible, and inviscid. This principle is not valid across streamlines because of the velocity and pressure variations between the streamlines. Since Bernoulli’s assume the flow to be steady, or velocity is fixed, the velocity and pressure gradients across the streamlines makes Bernoulli’s invalid.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Can you elaborate on the two-property rule?",
        "answer": "The two-property rule states that within a system, two properties must be specified as independent to have the state fixed. In other words, it not possible to vary pressure, temperature, and volume independently at once, rather two of these three properties must be fixed, and the third property must be expressed as an equation of state of the two fixed properties. For example, if volume and pressure are fixed, and temperature needs to be determined, then temperature should be expressed as a function of volume and pressure.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "How is a control volume different from a system boundary and why are control volumes important?",
        "answer": "System boundaries are often thought of as an imaginary boundary where mass cannot cross the boundary, while energy in the form of work or heat is able to cross. In a system boundary, the volume is not fixed, meaning that if the volume expands or shrinks, then the system boundary would be altered to accommodate the change. Control volumes are similar to a system boundary, but unlike a system boundary, the volume and shape stays fixed in a control volume. Furthermore, mass is permitted to cross its boundaries and since volume is fixed, mass flowing in must be equal to the mass flowing out. Control volumes are important when determining mass flows of inlets and outlets of various sections, since mass is conserved within the control volume, meaning that continuity is applied.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why can’t the isentropic flow relations be applied across a shock?",
        "answer": "While a shock is adiabatic, since the gas’ properties increase instantaneously in a short period of time where there is no time for heat to be transferred, a shock is an irreversible process, since there is a loss in total press across the shock. This means that flow across a shock is non-isentropic as for flow to be considered as isentropic, the flow must be reversible and adiabatic.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "What's the difference between Fanno and Rayleigh flow?",
        "answer": "While both flows occur in duct of constant area and are types of adiabatic and steady compressible flows, Fanno flow is flow where viscous effects are present, and Rayleigh flow is flow with heat transfer at the walls of the duct. In addition, Fanno flow is an isothermal process (temperature is constant), whereas Rayleigh flow is an isentropic process (entropy is constant).",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why is only the change in entropy defined and not static entropy?",
        "answer": "Entropy is defined as a system’s inability to do useful work and is only defined as the change of entropy between two states because there is no method of measuring entropy at certain points of time. Since entropy is a state function, the change in entropy will be the same between two states no matter which path was taken to reach from state one to state two.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why are conservation laws used to form the shock relations?",
        "answer": "Conservation laws are able to be utilized to form relations for different values across a shock because while the shock itself is not isentropic, flow before and after the shock are in isentropic flow. In addition, mass, momentum, and energy are all conserved throughout the flow before and after a shock since flow still follows the laws of physics. Knowing that conservation laws are valid for flow before and after the shock, relations can be built around the forming of ratios of certain properties of the gas (such as pressure, velocity, and temperature) before and after a shock to tell us how a shock impacts the properties of a gas, as a shock cuts of the line of communication between the entrance and exit of said shock.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    { 
    
        "question": "Consider the isentropic flow over an airfoil at gamma 1.4. The freestream conditions correspond to a standard altitude of 10,000 ft and free stream mach of 0.82. At a given point on the airfoil, M = 1.0. Calculate the static pressure at that point. (Note: You will have to use the standard atmopsheric vs. altitude table.)",
        "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n        # Based upon the standard atmosphere vs. altitude table, we get a free stream pressure of 1455.6 lbf/ft^2\n        # Looking at isentropic flow charts at Mach = 0.82, we get a free stream pressure over stagnation pressure ratio value of 0.6430.\n        # For our purposes, we will invert this ratio to now have a stagnation pressure over free stream pressure ratio value of 1.555\n        # Now, look at Mach = 1, and we will get a stagnation pressure over static pressure value of 1.893. This ratio will also need to be inverted so that we can get final static pressure. This static pressure indicates the static pressure where Mach = 1.\n        # Since we have both ratios and the initial free stream pressure, we can now find the final static pressure. This is done by multiplying the ratios and free stream pressure together, as the ratios will cancel out stagnation pressure and the free stream pressures will cancel out as well.\n        p0overp1 = 1.555\n        p2overp0 = 0.528\n        p1 = 1455.6\n        p2 = p2overp0 * p0overp1 * p1\n        print('The static pressure over an airfoil where mach = 1 is:', p2, 'lbf/ft^2')\n        ",
        "explanation": "For this problem, we utilize the table of values for isentropic, subsonic, flow at gamma = 1.4. Given the intial and final mach numbers, we can find the pressure ratios. From there the pressure ratios can be manipulated in a way to cancel certain pressure values out and to then find the static pressure at the Mach 1 point on the airfoil. In addition the table of standard atmospheric conditions at varying altitudes was necessary to find the free stream pressure.",
        "reference": "Problem 8.6 | Page 611 from John Anderson, (2023) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, Seventh Edition, McGraw-Hill"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider air at a temp of 330 K and flowing at Mach 1.5, find the velocity of the air.",
        "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n        # Recall the following equations: a = sqrt(gamma * R * T) & M = v / a\n        # First need to find speed of sound (a)\n        gamma = 1.4\n        R = 287\n        T = 330\n        a = np.sqrt(gamma * R * T)\n        # Now that we found a, rearrange the latter equation for velocity\n        M = 1.5\n        v = M * a\n        print('The velocity of the air is', v, 'm/s')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the velocity of air by the utilization of the definition of a mach number and definition of speed of sound. For the formulas shown, v is the velocity of the air, R is the gas constant, T is temperature, gamma is the ratios between specific heat capacities of constant pressure and volume, a is speed of sound, and M is mach number",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider an airfoil in a flow at standard sea level conditions with a freestream velocity of 50 m/s. At a given point on the airfoil, the pressure is 0.9 × 105 Pa. Find the velocity at this given point. (Assume at standard sea level, densitySL = 1.23 kg/m3 and pressureSL = 1.01 × 105 N/m2).",
        "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n        # Since flow is in free stream and density is constant, flow is incompressible and thus Bernoulli's Principle can be applied.and\n        rhoSL = 1.23\n        p1 = 1.01 * 10**5\n        v1 = 50\n        p2 = 0.9 * 10 **5\n        # Bernoulli's Principle: p1 + 0.5 * rhoSL * (v1**2) = p2 + 0.5 * rhoSL * (v2**2)\n        # Re-arrange above expression for v2 to find the velocity at that specific point\n        v2 = np.sqrt(((2 * (p1 - p2))/(rhoSL)) + (v1**2))\n        print('The velocity at the point where the pressure is 0.9 x 10^5 N/m^2 is:', v2, 'm/s')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code uses Bernoulli's principle to find the velocity at another point along a streamline, since the flow is considered incompressible. Using the given values, the expression can be re-arranged to find the velocity.",
        "reference": "Example 3.1 | Page 212 John Anderson, (2023) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, Seventh Edition, McGraw-Hill"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider a closed system containing 5 m^3 of air pressurized at 5 x 10^5 Pa and at 350 C. Specific heat at constant volume is  0.74 kJ / Kg*K. If 2500 kJ of heat is added isochorichly, what is the final pressure in the system?",
        "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n        #First, we need to find the mass of the air, so that we can then use mass in the first law of thermodynamics expression.\n        #To find mass, we must use the ideal gas relation: pV = mRT and re-arrange to solve for mass.\n        p1 = 5 * 10 ** 5\n        V = 5\n        T1 = 350 + 273.15\n        cv = 0.74\n        Q = 2500\n        R = 287\n        m = (p1 * V) / (R * T1)        \n        # Second, we must find change in temperature, which can be determined by utilizing the first law of thermodyanmics: Q - W = delt(U)\n        # We also need to recognize the following expression only valid for perfect gasses: delt(U) = m * cv * deltT\n        #Subsituting the latter expression into the first law expression, we get the following expression: Q - W = m * cv * deltT\n        # Note that this is a closed system, so there is no work done or being done by the system. Now, re-arrange the expression for deltT\n        deltT = (Q) / (m * cv)\n        # Final temperature can now be found since we already know intiial temperature and change in temperature\n        T2 = T1 + deltT\n        # Since volume remains constant, the process is isochoric, and we can use the isochoric relations to find final pressure\n        #The isochoric relation that will be used is (p2/p1) = (T2/T1), in which we rearrange to solve for p2\n        p2 = (T2 / T1) * p1\n        print('The final pressure in the system is:', p2, 'Pa.')\n        ",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "A tank that has two inlets and outlets is filled with a fluid that has a density of 800 kg/m^3 . At one inlet, the fluid enters with a volumetric flow rate of 5 m^3/s, and exits the outlet with a cross-sectional area of 0.125 m^2 at 75 m/s , if the velocity entering the second inlet is 2 m/s, what is the cross-sectional area of that inlet?",
        "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n        Q1 = 5\n        rho = 800\n        v3 = 75\n        A3 = 0.125\n        v2 = 2\n        # First, we must find the individual mass flows with given values. The mass flow rate is density * area * velocity. \n        # Recall that volumetric flow rate is equal to area * velocity.\n        # Note that the mass flow rate for inlet 2 will not be found yet, as we do not know the cross-sectional area of that inlet.\n        m1 = Q1 * rho\n        m3 = rho * A3 * v3\n        # Applying the principle of continuity (m1 + m2 = m3), where mass flow in equates to mass flow out, we can then find the cross-sectional area of the second inlet by expanding m2 into A2 * v2. \n        A2 = (m3 - m1) / v2\n        print('The cross-sectional area of the second inlet is:', A2, 'm^2.')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code uses the principle of continuity for incompressible flow, which states that the mass flow remains constant throughout the inlets and outlets.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider an oblique shock wave with a wave angle of 35 deg, and a pressure ratio (p2/p1) = 3. Calculate the upstream Mach Number.",
        "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n        #Using the table of values corresponding to oblique shock waves, we can find that for the pressure ratios, the intiial normal Mach is 1.64.\n        #Using the definition of the normal mach number component seen by a moving observer, we get the expression of normal Mach = Mach * sin(beta).\n        # Re-arranging the above expression to find the initial mach gives us Mach = (normal Mach) / sin(beta).\n        Mn1 = 1.64\n        #Convert beta to radians\n        beta = 35 * ((np.pi) / 180)\n        M1 = (Mn1) / (np.sin(beta))\n        print('The upstream Mach number is:', M1, '.')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This problem uses the concept of reference frames in oblique shocks, as oblique shocks are simply normal shocks but at an wedge angle and wave angle. The normal mach number is the mach number that is perpendicular to the shock. In addition, the table of values for oblique shocks was used as well in order to find the normal upstream mach number from pressure ratios.",
        "reference": "Example 9.4 | Page 632 John Anderson, (2023) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, Seventh Edition, McGraw-Hill"
    },
    {
        "question": "A gas with a gamma value of 1.89 is initially at  15 kg/m3 and is expanded adiabatically and reversibly to 5 times its initial volume. Find the final density.",
        "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n        gamma = 1.89\n        rho1 = 15\n        # Since the gas is being expanded adiabatically, the process is isentropic since it is reversible and adiabatic. From this we can use the isentropic relation between density and volume.\n        # The isentropic relationship between density and volume is: (rho2/rho1) = (V1/V2)^(gamma - 1).\n        # Since the gas was expanded to a volume 5 times the initial volume, we can write the ratio of V1/V2 as 1/5.\n        # Now, we plug in the newfound volume ratio and solve for rho2.\n        rho2 = ((1/5)**(1.89-1)) * rho1\n        print('The final density of the gas after being expanded is:', rho2, 'kg/m^3.')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This problem utilized the isentropic relations after assuming flow is isentropic due to the gas being expanded adiabatically. The isentropic relation needed is between volume and density, in which volume ratio was given as 1/5 and final density can be solved for.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "A fluid with a density of 1000 kg/m^3 enters a pipe with a cross-sectional area of 0.1 m^2 at a velocity of 2 m/s. The pipe narrows to an area of 0.05 m^2. What is the fluid's velocity at the narrower section?",
        "answer": "\\n        import numpy as np\\n        rho = 1000\\nA1 = 0.1\\n        v1 = 2\\nA2 = 0.05\\n        v2 = (A1 * v1) / A2\\n        print('Velocity in the narrower section:', v2, 'm/s')",
        "explanation": "This code utilizes the principle of continuity for incompressible flow, which states that the mass flow rate remains constant. The equation A1*v1 = A2*v2 expresses this, where A represents cross-sectional area and v represents velocity.",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "Explain the difference between laminar and turbulent flow.",
        "answer": "Laminar flow is characterized by smooth, orderly movement of fluid particles in parallel layers, while turbulent flow is chaotic and characterized by irregular fluctuations in velocity and pressure. Reynolds number is used to determine flow regime, with laminar flow occurring at low Reynolds numbers and turbulent flow at high Reynolds numbers.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "Calculate the Mach number when an aircraft is traveling at a speed of 300 m/s and the speed of sound in air is 340 m/s.",
        "answer": "\\n        import numpy as np\\n        v = 300\\n        a = 340\\n        M = v / a\\n        print('Mach number:', M)",
        "explanation": "The Mach number (M) is the ratio of the speed of an object to the speed of sound in the medium through which the object is moving. It indicates how fast an object moves compared to the speed of sound. The formula to calculate Mach number is M = v / a, where v is the speed of the object and a is the speed of sound in the medium.",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "What is Bernoulli's principle and how does it apply to fluid dynamics?",
        "answer": "Bernoulli's principle states that in a fluid flow, an increase in the speed of the fluid occurs simultaneously with a decrease in pressure or potential energy. This principle is derived from the conservation of energy in fluid flow and is commonly used to explain phenomena such as lift in aerodynamics and the functioning of carburetors and atomizers.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "A gas at 300 K and 1 atm expands isothermally to a volume three times its initial volume. Calculate the final pressure of the gas.",
        "answer": "\\n        import numpy as np\\n        T = 300\\n        P = 1\\n        V1 = 1\\n        V2 = 3\\n        P2 = P * (V1 / V2)\\n        print('Final pressure:', P2, 'atm')",
        "explanation": "This calculation is based on Boyle's Law, which states that for a given amount of gas at constant temperature, the product of pressure and volume is constant. The formula P1V1 = P2V2 is used, where P1 and V1 are the initial pressure and volume, and P2 and V2 are the final pressure and volume.",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the difference between specific heat capacity and latent heat?",
        "answer": "Specific heat capacity is the amount of heat required to raise the temperature of a unit mass of a substance by one degree Celsius, while latent heat is the heat absorbed or released by a substance during a phase change (e.g., melting, vaporization) at constant temperature. Specific heat capacity is associated with temperature changes, while latent heat is associated with phase changes.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "A pump delivers water at a rate of 0.05 m^3/s against a head of 20 meters. Calculate the power required by the pump, assuming 100% efficiency.",
        "answer": "\\n        import numpy as np\\n        m_dot = 0.05\\n        h = 20\\n        rho = 1000\\n        g = 9.81\\n        P = rho * g * m_dot * h\\n        print('Power required by the pump:', P, 'W')",
        "explanation": "The power required by the pump can be calculated using the formula P = ρghQ, where ρ is the density of the fluid, g is the acceleration due to gravity, h is the head, and Q is the volumetric flow rate.",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "Explain the difference between entropy and enthalpy.",
        "answer": "Entropy is a measure of the disorder or randomness of a system, while enthalpy is a measure of the total energy of a system. Entropy increases in irreversible processes, indicating an increase in disorder, while enthalpy change is related to heat exchange in a system at constant pressure.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "Calculate the Reynolds number for water flowing through a pipe with a diameter of 0.1 m at a velocity of 2 m/s. The kinematic viscosity of water is 1 × 10^-6 m^2/s.",
        "answer": "\\n        import numpy as np\\n        D = 0.1\\n        v = 2\\n        nu = 1e-6\\n        Re = (v * D) / nu\\n        print('Reynolds number:', Re)",
        "explanation": "Reynolds number (Re) is a dimensionless quantity used to predict flow patterns in different fluid flow situations. It is calculated using the formula Re = (v * D) / ν, where v is the velocity of the fluid, D is a characteristic linear dimension (such as diameter), and ν is the kinematic viscosity of the fluid.",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the significance of the Mach number in compressible flow?",
        "answer": "The Mach number is a dimensionless quantity that represents the ratio of the speed of an object (or fluid) to the speed of sound in the surrounding medium. In compressible flow, the Mach number indicates whether the flow is subsonic (M < 1), sonic (M = 1), or supersonic (M > 1). It is crucial in determining the compressibility effects and shock wave formations in high-speed flows.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "A gas expands isothermally from an initial volume of 1 m^3 to a final volume of 2 m^3 against a constant external pressure of 100 kPa. Calculate the work done by the gas during the expansion.",
        "answer": "\\n        import numpy as np\\n        P_ext = 100e3\\n        V1 = 1\\n        V2 = 2\\n        R = 8.314\\n        T = 300\\n        W = -P_ext * (V2 - V1)\\n        print('Work done by the gas:', W, 'Joules')",
        "explanation": "The work done by the gas during an isothermal expansion can be calculated using the formula W = -P_ext * (V2 - V1), where P_ext is the external pressure, and V1 and V2 are the initial and final volumes, respectively. The negative sign indicates work done by the gas (expansion).",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the primary differences between adiabatic and isothermal processes?",
        "answer": "Adiabatic processes involve no heat exchange with the surroundings, resulting in changes in temperature without heat transfer. Isothermal processes occur at constant temperature, with heat exchange occurring to maintain the temperature constant. Adiabatic processes are typically faster than isothermal processes and can result in greater changes in temperature and pressure.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "A gas initially at a pressure of 2 atm and a volume of 5 m^3 expands adiabatically until its volume becomes 10 m^3. Calculate the final pressure of the gas.",
        "answer": "\\n        import numpy as np\\n        P1 = 2\\n        V1 = 5\\n        V2 = 10\\n        P2 = P1 * (V1 / V2)\\n        print('Final pressure of the gas:', P2, 'atm')",
        "explanation": "This calculation is based on the adiabatic process equation for an ideal gas, which states that P1V1^γ = P2V2^γ, where P1 and V1 are the initial pressure and volume, P2 and V2 are the final pressure and volume, and γ is the ratio of specific heats.",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "Explain how a converging-diverging nozzle works in the context of compressible flow.",
        "answer": "A converging-diverging nozzle is used to accelerate the flow of a compressible fluid (such as a gas) to supersonic speeds. It consists of a converging section followed by a diverging section. In the converging section, the flow accelerates due to decreasing cross-sectional area, reaching sonic conditions at the throat. In the diverging section, the flow expands further, reaching supersonic speeds. This nozzle design is essential for applications such as rocket propulsion and supersonic wind tunnels.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "Calculate the change in enthalpy when 1 kg of water at 100°C is converted to steam at 100°C. The latent heat of vaporization of water is 2257 kJ/kg.",
        "answer": "\\n        import numpy as np\\n        m = 1\\n        L = 2257e3\\n        ΔH = m * L\\n        print('Change in enthalpy:', ΔH, 'Joules')",
        "explanation": "The change in enthalpy (ΔH) during a phase change can be calculated using the formula ΔH = mL, where m is the mass of the substance undergoing the phase change and L is the latent heat of vaporization (or fusion). This formula represents the energy required or released during the phase change.",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the significance of the critical Mach number in aerodynamics?",
        "answer": "The critical Mach number is the speed at which airflow over a body first reaches the speed of sound (Mach 1) at any point. It is a critical parameter in aerodynamics because airflow behavior changes significantly as the critical Mach number is approached and exceeded. At speeds above the critical Mach number, shock waves form and flow becomes supersonic, leading to aerodynamic effects such as wave drag and compressibility drag.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "Describe how sound waves propagate through a medium.",
        "answer": "Sound waves are longitudinal waves that propagate by expanding or contracting. Expansions are known as rarefactions and contractions are called compressions. This wave is created by some sort of vibrating object that moves back and forth and compresses and expands zones of particles.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "When designing a fluid system where you want to maximize the exit fluid static pressure out of the system, what could you do to the tubes to ensure that they have small pressure drops? Assume that you can change the tubes and that the flow is laminar.",
        "answer": "To minimize the pressure drop through a pipe, there are a few things you could do. You can increase tube diameter or length which can reduce shear stress on your flow. Thus, it will decrease your pressure drop. What principle?",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why is it a reasonable assumption to say that sound waves are adiabatic? Also, just because they’re adiabatic does this mean that temperature is constant?",
        "answer": "Sound waves are adiabatic because they are so instantaneous that it can be assumed that heat can’t transfer which is the only condition for something to be adiabatic. However, just because heat can’t transfer doesn’t mean that the particle's temperature is constant. Sound waves undergo adiabatic compressions and rarefactions which can cause heating and cooling.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Say you have a subsonic flow (M > 0.3) through a tube with friction of a small diameter . Why can’t you make this tube as long as you want? Assume your system is adiabatic and you want to keep the gas velocity constant. Ignore tube pressure losses from friction.",
        "answer": "You can’t make these tubes as long as you want because the shear on the fluid will reduce its area and it will choke (M = 1). Fanno Flow happens when you have an adiabatic, compressible flow through a tube with friction.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why are normal shocks not isentropic?",
        "answer": "Normal shocks are characterized by sudden collisions between a supersonic flow and fluid particles.The shock creates a rapid compression zone that is inherently irreversible. For something to be considered isentropic, it must have no irreversibilities so normal shocks can’t be isentropic.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Describe the types of expansion out of a supersonic nozzle and explain the conditions by which each expansion type forms.",
        "answer": "When the ambient pressure is greater than the exit pressure of the flow, the flow is overexpanded and converges immediately after exiting the nozzle. When the ambient pressure is less than the exit pressure of the flow, the flow is underexpanded and forms diverges immediately after exiting the nozzle. When the ambient pressure equals the exit pressure, the flow is fully expanded.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Is it possible to create a cryogenic pump that operates at 100% efficiency? Explain why or why not using thermodynamics principles.",
        "answer": "Efficiency is the output work divided by the input heat. By the Kelvin Planck statement, it's impossible for a device to convert all of the heat into work. Losses always happen so a cryogenic pump could never operate at 100% efficiency.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Describe what shaft work is.",
        "answer": "Shaft work is the work contribution to a fluid from a rotating shaft that does work on the fluid through torque. Many fluids rely on shaft work for pressure through impellers or other types of turbomachinery.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Name the 3 conservation laws that are fundamental in thermodynamics and fluids and briefly describe them.",
        "answer": "The three conservation laws are energy, momentum, and continuity. Continuity says that mass flow rate is always constant in a system. Momentum relates the fluid's momentum and its force as well as inlet and exit pressures. Energy describes the relationship between heat into a system and work done by a system.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "The Merlin Engine by SpaceX is the most reliable rocket engine ever and is the engine for the Falcon 9 launch vehicle. Calculate the exit area of the nozzle given the following values: Expansion Ratio = 16, Cp = 6.0755 kJ/(kg * K), gamma = 1.13, mdot = 266 kg/s, T_0 = 2958 K, and P_0 = 9.7 MPa. You can assume that the flow is choked at the throat.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\n\n gamma = 1.4 # specific heat ratio\n exp_rat = 16 # expansion ratio\n Cp = 6.0755 # Cp at throat, [kJ/kg * K]\n P_0 = 9.7 * 1000000 # inlet stagnation pressure [Pa]\n mdot = 266 # mass flow rate [kg/s]\n T_0 = 2958 # inlet stagnation temperature [K]\n\n\n # Using a gas flow table, find non-dimensional mass flow rate at M = 1\n ndmfr = 1.2810\n\n\n # Solve for Throat Area\n A_t = (mdot * np.sqrt(Cp * T_0))/(P_0 * ndmfr)\n\n\n # Solve for Exit Area\n A_e = A_t * exp_rat\n\n\n print('Exit Area:', A_e, 'm^2')\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "You have an incompressible fluid flowing through a venturi. There are pressure transducers before the inlet and at the throat of the venturi which measure 800000 and 850000 Pa respectively. Calculate the throat velocity if the inlet velocity is 20 m/s. The fluid density is 786 kg/m^3.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nrho = 786 # density [kg/m^3]\nv1 = 20 # velocity, [m/s]\nP1 = 800000 # pressure [Pa]\nP2 = 850000 # pressure [Pa]\n\n# Use bernoulli's eqn. to find v2\nv2 = np.sqrt(((P1 - P2) + 0.5 * rho * v1**2)*(2/rho))\n\nprint('Throat Velocity', v2, 'm/s')\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "A pitot static probe measures ambient pressure as 101,325 Pa and static pressure inside the probe as 89,000 Pa. If air density is 1.25 kg/m^3, calculate the airplane velocity. Assume no wind.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nP1 = 101325 # air pressure [Pa]\nP2 = 98000 # static pressure in probe [Pa]\nrho = 1.3 # density [kg/m^3]\n\n# Use Bernoulli's Eqn.\nv = np.sqrt((2 * (P1 - P2))/rho)\n\nprint('Airplane Velocity', v, 'm/s')\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "You’re designing a tube for gas to flow through to pressurize a tank. The gas is moving at M = 0.45 and is therefore compressible. The tube diameter is 0.25” and has a friction factor equal to. Assume adiabatic. Calculate the tube length needed to choke your flow.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nM = 0.45 # mach number\nD = 0.25 # diameter [m]\nCf = 0.034 # friction factor\n\n# Lookup fanno flow coefficient in the gas flow table for M = 0.45\nffc = 1.5664\n\n# Solve for Lmax\nLmax = (ffc * D)/(4 * Cf)\n\nprint('Tube Length:', Lmax, 'm')\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "You’re designing a system where you want to greatly increase temperature. You do this with a normal shock and you want to characterize your temperature rise after your shock. Plot this temperature as a function of mach number. T1 = 3100 K and gamma = 1.13.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\nimport matplotlib.pyplot as plt\n\nT1 = 3100 # Temperature [K]\ngamma = 1.13 # specific heat ratio\n\n# create mach number vector\nM = np.linspace(1, 5, 100)\n\n# solve for temp post shock\nT2 = T1 * ((1 + ((gamma - 1)/2) * M**2) * (((2*gamma)/(gamma - 1)) * M**2 - 1))/(M**2 * (((gamma + 1)**2)/(2*(gamma - 1))))\n\n# plot\nplt.plot(M, T2)\nplt.xlabel('Mach Number')\nplt.ylabel('Temperature [K]')\nplt.title('Mach Number vs. Temperature [K]')\nplt.show()\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "You’re designing a kerosene line that is 6 ft long and can be minimum 0.25”. It goes directly from your main fuel valve to your combustion chamber in a rocket engine so you want to minimize your pressure drop across this tube to less than 20 psid. Plot different tube sizes vs. pressure drop and find the smallest tube. You can assume your flow is laminar. Dynamic viscosity = 1.92E-3 kg/m*s, rho = 800 kg/m^3, and mdot = 7 kg/s.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\nimport matplotlib.pyplot as plt\n\n\nmu = 1.92 * 10**-3 # dynamic viscosity [kg/m*s]\nrho = 800 # density [kg/m^3]\nmdot = 7 # mass flow rate [kg/s]\nlength = 6 * 0.3048 # length [m]\nmin_psid = 20 # pressure drop [psid]\n\n\n# create tube size vector\nt_d = np.linspace(0.25, 1.5, 100)\n\n\n# solve for velocity vec\nv = mdot/(rho * (((t_d * 0.0254)**2 * np.pi)/4))\n\n\n# Calculate pressure drop\ndp = ((8 * mu * v * length)/(((t_d * 0.0254)/2)**2)) * 0.000145038\n\n\n# plot\nplt.plot(t_d, dp)\nplt.plot(t_d, min_psid * np.ones(len(v)))\nplt.xlabel('Tube Diameter [in]')\nplt.ylabel('Pressure Drop [psi]')\nplt.title('Tube Diameter [in] vs. Pressure Drop [psi]')\nplt.show()\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "The BE-3 turbopump uses 8.9 MW of heat and does 6.9 MW of work on its propellants. Calculate the efficiency of this turbopump.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\nimport matplotlib.pyplot as plt\n\nQ = 8.9 # Heat [MW]\nW = 6.9 # Work [MW]\n\n# calc efficiency\neff = W/Q\n\nprint('Turbopump Efficiency:', eff*100, '%')\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Can you explain efficiency and what is necessary for a process to achieve maximum efficiency in a heat engine?",
        "answer": "Efficiency is defined as the fraction of heat input that is turned into actual work, also equal to 1 - (heat output)/(heat input). There must be a limit to efficiency as a consequence of the Kelvin-Planck Statement, which states that “It is impossible to construct a cyclic device whose sole effect is to produce positive work whilst receiving heat from a single reservoir.” In other words, you cannot achieve 100% efficiency, where all heat from a single source is converted to work. Maximum efficiency is achieved when the process is reversible, that is, when the system and surroundings can be returned to their initial states. A reversible process will not greatly depart from equilibrium, meaning that it is a quasi-equilibrium process that generally occurs slowly. In the case of a reversible process, the efficiency is equal to 1 - (final temperature)/(initial temperature). This relationship can be derived using the Clausius Inequality.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "Why are constant volume lines always steeper than constant pressure lines on T-s diagrams?",
        "answer": "To answer this question, we must first define specific heat capacity, which is the heat required to raise the temperature of one kilogram of a substance by one degree Kelvin. We define them at both constant pressure (c_p) and at constant volume (c_v). For a given gas, the value of c_p is always greater than the value of c_v, because increasing volume requires work, which takes up some of the energy used to raise the temperature in a constant pressure process; consequently, more energy is required for a temperature increase when volume changes and pressure is constant. For a perfect gas at constant pressure, Tds = c_pdT, so the gradient of the T-s curve equals T/c_p. Similarly, for a perfect gas at constant volume, Tds=c_vdT, and the gradient is T/c_v. Since c_p is always greater than c_v, T/c_v will always be greater than T/c_p, resulting in a steeper slope.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "How can one tell if a process is isentropic, and how does evaluating such a process differ from evaluating a process with a change in entropy?",
        "answer": "An isentropic process, as the name implies, is characterized by its zero change in entropy (s_2=s_1). An isentropic process is adiabatic, meaning that the system and surroundings exchange no heat (Q=0); this is often achieved by performing the process almost instantaneously or using insulating walls. An isentropic process must also be reversible, meaning that the system and surroundings can be returned to their initial states. An example of a statement of an isentropic process is “A mass of air is compressed rapidly within a cylinder by a piston. You may assume the compression is reversible.” An advantage of evaluating isentropic processes is that one can apply the isentropic changes, which relate temperature, pressure, density, volume, and specific volume (assuming the substance is an ideal gas).",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "Can you explain Fanno Flow and why crossing from one branch to another on the T-s diagram is not possible?",
        "answer": "Fanno Flow is the model of flow through a very long pipe with friction. As length increases, this friction decreases the effective area, increasing velocity in subsonic flows and decreasing velocity in supersonic flows. In both cases, this leads to a choked flow at a certain length L. This choke occurs at maximum entropy, and it represents a discontinuity on the T-s diagram. One cannot “cross over” from the supersonic to subsonic branch, or vice versa, because moving along the other curve would result in a decrease in entropy, which is not possible for the moving flow subject to friction.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "Can you explain the difference between Couette Flow and Poiseuille Flow and what happens when they are combined?",
        "answer": "Both models consider steady, viscous flow with straight streamlines parallel to the plates. between two parallel plates. The main assumptions are that the flow is incompressible and the plates are very wide and very long. In Couette Flow, one of the plates moves parallel to the other plate with some velocity (v), and the pressure gradient is zero. This yields a linear fluid velocity profile with boundary conditions stating that at the stationary plate, the velocity of the fluid equals zero, and at the moving plate the fluid velocity is equal to the plate velocity. In contrast, Poiseuille Flow occurs between two stationary plates and is induced by a constant pressure gradient. The resulting fluid velocity profile is parabolic equal to zero at the plates and reaching a maximum at half the distance between the plates. Combining the two models, that is, having both a moving plate and a nonzero pressure gradient, yields a parabolic fluid velocity profile with different boundary conditions. Note that if the pressure gradient opposes the moving plate’s velocity, the fluid velocity near the stationary plate may reverse.",
        "explanation":"",
          "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill."
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the point of measuring both static and stagnation pressure with a pitot tube in incompressible flow? What makes static pressure different from stagnation pressure?",
        "answer": "A pitot tube measures static pressure from an opening that is oriented perpendicular to the direction of the flow. This measurement does not take the fluid’s velocity into account, so it is the “actual” pressure that you would experience if you were moving at the same velocity as the flow. If a question asks you about pressure, you may assume that it is referring to static pressure. The stagnation pressure of the flow is measured by an opening that faces the flow, creating a stagnation point where the velocity is zero. It represents the pressure of the fluid if it were brought to rest with no mechanical losses. Knowing both of these values allows you to calculate the flow’s velocity with Bernoulli’s equation: p_1 + rho*(v_1)^2 = p_2 + rho*(v_2)^2, where p_1 is the static pressure, rho is the density, v_1 is the flow velocity, p_2 is the stagnation pressure, and v_2 is the velocity at the stagnation point, which is zero. Please note that we neglected the effects of gravity, and since the flow is incompressible, the density is equal at both points.",
        "explanation":"",
          "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill."
      },
      {
        "question": "On the Oblique Shock Tables, why are there two rows for a given turning angle theta, and which row should be used?",
        "answer": "The two rows represent the values for weak and strong shocks at a given turning angle, with weak being the row appearing first from top to bottom and the strong last for a given theta. A weak shock is more likely to happen, and it is characterized by a smaller wave angle beta and a supersonic Mach number behind it. Conversely, strong shocks are associated with larger wave angles and have subsonic flow behind them. These are far less common, so when solving a problem involving oblique shocks, it is usually safe to assume the shock was weak and use the higher row corresponding to the given theta. Additionally, if you have a problem with multiple shocks, the earlier shocks must be weak, because a strong shock makes the proceeding flow subsonic and thus negates the possibility of subsequent shocks.",
        "explanation":"",
          "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill."
      },
      {
        "question": "Why do expansion fans alter the flow properties (pressure, Mach number, etc.) opposite to normal and oblique shocks?",
        "answer": "A large difference between expansion fans and oblique shocks has to do with entropy. An expansion fan is modeled as a continuous expansion region with infinitesimal Mach waves. Because these waves are continuous, the change in entropy across an expansion fan is isentropic, whereas the discontinuity present in an oblique shock causes an increase in entropy. In expansion fans, Mach number increases, density and static pressure decrease, and stagnation pressure remains constant. However, in oblique shocks, the wave “turns into itself,” resulting in a drop in Mach number and stagnation pressure, and an increase in density, static pressure, and entropy.",
        "explanation":"",
          "reference":"https://www1.grc.nasa.gov/beginners-guide-to-aeronautics/centered-expansion-fan/#:~:text=Across%20a%20shock%20wave%2C%20the,Expansion%20fans%20are%20isentropic. , John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill."
      },
      {
        "question": "Can you elaborate on the two-property rule in thermodynamics and when it is applied?",
        "answer": "The two-property rule states that two independent, intensive properties must be specified to define the state of a substance. An intensive property is one that is not dependent on the system size, like specific volume. A property is independent if it can be held constant while the other changes; for example, specific volume and temperature are always independent and can therefore be used to define a system. This rule is applied to simple compressible systems of pure substances: substances that have uniform and unchanging chemical composition. This model neglects the effects of gravity, motion, surface tension, and electricity.",
        "explanation":"",
          "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
      },
      {
        "question": "A gas of density 1.7 kg/m^3 flows through a pipe with a volume flow rate of 0.12 m^3/s. The pipe has an inlet section diameter of d_1 of 21 cm and an outlet section diameter d_2 of 9 cm. Assuming an ideal incompressible fluid flow, calculate the flow velocities at the pipe's inlet and outlet, i.e., V_1 and V_2, respectively.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nQ = 0.12 # Volumetric flow rate ((m^3)/s)\nd_in = 0.21 # Inlet diameter (m)\nd_out = 0.09 # Outlet diameter (m)\npi = 3.14\n# Calculate inlet and outlet areas\nA_in = (1/4) * pi * (d_in **2)\nA_out = (1/4) * pi * (d_out ** 2)\n \n# Calculate inlet and outlet velocities\nv_in = Q / A_in # Inlet velocity\nprint('Inlet velocity:', v_in, 'm/s')\nv_out = Q / A_out # Outlet velocity\nprint('Outlet velocity:', v_out, 'm/s')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the initial and final velocities of a flow going through a pipe with variable area. We assume the flow is inviscid and incompressible (density is constant), and thus utilize the equation Q = Av, where Q is the volumetric flow rate, A is the cross-sectional area, and v is the velocity. Additionally, continuity applies, so Q_in = Q_out.",
        "reference": "https://eaglepubs.erau.edu/introductiontoaerospaceflightvehicles/chapter/worked-examples-fluid-flows/"
      },
      {
        "question": "A garden hose attached with a nozzle is used to fill a 10-gal bucket. The inner diameter of the hose is 2 cm, and it reduces to 0.8 cm at the nozzle exit. If it takes 50 s to fill the bucket with water, determine (a) the volume and mass flow rates of water through the hose, and (b) the average velocity of water at the nozzle exit",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nvGallon = 10 # Volume (gallons)\nt = 50 # Time to fill (s)\nrho = 1000 # Density of water (kg/m^2)\npi = 3.14 # Constant\nd = .008 # Diameter of hose nozzle (m)\nr = d / 2 # Radius of hose nozzle (m)\narea = pi*(r**2) # Area of hose nozzle (m^2)\n\n# Convert gallons to m^3\nvMeter = vGallon / 264.2\n\n# Volumetric flow rate\nQ = vMeter / t\n\n# Mass flow rate\nmDot = Q * rho\nprint('Volumetric flow rate:', Q, 'm^3/s')\nprint('Mass flow rate:', mDot, 'kg/s')\n\n# Average velocity\navgVelocity = Q / area\nprint('Average velocity:', avgVelocity, 'm/s')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the volumetric flow rate using the formula Q = V / t, where Q is the volumetric flow rate and V is the volume filled in time t. The mass flow rate is calculated with the formula Mdot = Q * rho, where rho is the density of water in kg / m^2. Assuming that water is incompressible and the flow through the hose is steady, we calculated Vavg = Q / A, where A is the cross-sectional area of the hose nozzle. Please note that units were converted to SI units where applicable (ie cm to m)",
        "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2006) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
      },
      {
        "question": "A piston-cylinder device initially contains air at 150 kPa and 27°C. At this state, the piston is resting on a pair of stops and the enclosed volume is 400 L. The mass of the piston is such that a 350-kPa pressure is required to move it. The air is now heated until its volume has doubled. Determine (a) the final temperature and (b) the work done by the air.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\np1 = 150000 # Initial pressure (Pa)\np2 = 350000 # Final pressure (Pa)\nt1_celcius = 27 # Initial temperature (Celcius)\nt1 = t1_celcius + 273.15 # Convert initial temperature to Kelvin\nv1_liter = 400 # Initial volume (L)\nv1 = v1_liter/1000 # Convert volume to m^3\nv2 = 2 * v1 # Final volume (m^3)\n\n# Use ideal gas law to calculate final temperature\nt2 = (t1 * p2 * v2) / (p1 * v1)\nprint('Final temperature:', t2, 'K')\n\n# Calculate work done using P*delta(V)\nw = p2 * (v2-v1)\nprint('Work done:', w, 'J')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the change in temperature of work done by air that is heated to move a piston. Since we are given the initial and final pressure and volume, we can make use of the ideal gas relations to find the final temperature: (P1 * V1) / T1 = (P2 * V2) / T2, where P1 and P2 are the initial and final pressures, V1 and V2 are the initial and final volumes, and T1 and T2 are the initial and final temperatures. Please note that the temperature is given in degrees Celcius and must be converted to Kelvin. The work was then found by using the definition of P-V work: W = P2 * (V2 - V1), where W represents the work done by the gas in Joules. Note that we assume air acts as an ideal gas, changes in potential and kinetic energy are negligible, and that no shaft work is present.",
        "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2006) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
      },
      {
        "question": "Air at 10°C and 80 kPa enters the diffuser of a jet engine steadily with a velocity of 200 m/s. The inlet area of the diffuser is 0.4 m^2. The air leaves the diffuser with a velocity that is very small compared with the inlet velocity. Determine (a) the mass flow rate of the air and (b) the change in specific enthalpy of the air leaving the diffuser.",
        "answer":"\nimport numpy as np\n\nT1_celcius = 10 # Initial temperature (Celcius)\nT1 = T1_celcius + 273.15 # Convert T1 to Kelvin\np1 = 80000 # Initial pressure (Pa)\nA_in = 0.4 # Inlet area (m^2)\nv1 = 200 # Initial velocity (m/s)\nv2 = 0 # Final velocity << v1 (m/s)\nR = 287 # Gas constant for air (J/(kg*K))\ncp = 1005 # Specific heat of air at constant pressure (J/(kg*K))\n\n# Calculate specific volume using ideal gas law\nspecific_volume = (R * T1) / p1 # Specific volume (m^3/kg)\nrho = 1 / specific_volume\n\n# Calculate mass flow rate\nmDot = rho * v1 * A_in\nprint('Mass flow rate:', mDot, 'kg/s')\n\n# Calculate change in specific enthalpy\ndelta_h = - (((v2**2)-(v1**2))/2) # Steady Flow Energy Equation\nprint('Change in specific enthalpy:', delta_h, 'J/kg')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the mass flow rate and change in specific enthalpy of subsonic flow through a nozzle. To begin, we assume that this is a steady-flow process, so the mass flow rate in equals the mass flow rate out. We also assume a negligible change in potential energy, that the kinetic energy at the exit is zero due to the low velocity, and that air behaves as an ideal gas. The mass flow rate was found by first finding the specific volume using ideal gas relations (nu = (R * T) / P) and using it to find the density (rho = 1 / nu), where nu is the specific volume, R is the gas constant for air, T is the temperature, P is the pressure, and rho is the density; then, mass flow rate was found using rho * v1 * A_in, where v1 is the initial velocity and A_in is the inlet area. The change in specific enthalpy was found by algebraic manipulation of the Steady Flow Energy Equation: h1 + ((v1 ** 2) / 2) = h2 + ((v2 ** 2) / 2), where h1 and h2 are the initial and final enthalpies, and v1 and v2 are the initial and final velocities, respectively. Please note again that we assumed v2 = 0.",
        "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2006) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
      },
      {
        "question": "A rigid tank contains a hot fluid that is cooled while being stirred by a paddle wheel. Initially, the internal energy of the fluid is 800 kJ. During the cooling process, the fluid loses 500 kJ of heat, and the paddle wheel does 100 kJ of work on the fluid. Determine the final internal energy of the fluid. Neglect the energy stored in the paddle wheel.",
        "answer":"\nimport numpy as np\n\nU1 = 800000 # Initial internal energy (J)\nQ = -500000 # Heat lost to surroundings from system (J)\nW = -100000 # Work done on system by paddle (J)\n\n# Calculate change in internal energy\ndelta_U = Q - W\nU2 = delta_U + U1\nprint('Final internal energy:', U2, 'J')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the final internal energy of a system with heat loss and work input using the First Law equation Q - W = U2 - U1, where Q and W are the heat input and work output respectively, and U2 and U1 are the final and initial internal energies. Please note that for this problem, Q is negative because heat is lost to the system, and W is negative because work is done on the system. We assume the kinetic and potential energy changes are zero and that no boundary work is being done by the system since the container is rigid.",
          "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2006) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
        
      },
      {
        "question": "Air enters a diffuser shown in with a velocity of 200 m/s. Determine (a) the speed of sound and (b) the Mach number at the diffuser inlet when the air temperature is 30°C.",
        "answer":"\nimport numpy as np\n\nv = 200 # Velocity (m/s)\nT_celcius = 30 # Temperature (Celcius)\nT = T_celcius + 273.15 # Convert temperature (K)\ngamma = 1.4 # Specific heat ratio of air\nR = 287 # Gas constant for air (J/kgK)\n\n# Calculate speed of sound (m/s)\na = (gamma * R * T) ** (1/2)\nprint('Speed of sound:', a, 'm/s')\n\n# Calculate Mach number\nM = v/a\nprint('Mach number:', M)\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the speed of sound in air for the given conditions using the equation a = (gamma * R * T) ** (1/2), where a is the speed of sound, gamma is the specific heat ratio, R is the gas constant, and T is the temperature. The Mach number is then calculated using M = v/a, where v is the velocity and a is the speed of sound for the given conditions. To perform these calculations, we assume that air behaves as an ideal gas.",
          "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2006) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
      },
      {
        "question": "Air enters a converging-diverging nozzle at 1.0 MPa and 800 K with a negligible velocity. The flow is steady, one-dimensional, and isentropic with gamma = 1.4. For an exit Mach number of Ma = 2 and a throat area of 20 cm^2, determine the temperature and pressure at the throat.",
        "answer":"\nimport numpy as np\n\np0 = 1000000 # Inlet stagnation pressure (Pa)\nT0 = 800 # Inlet stagnation temperature (K)\npStar_p0 = 0.5283 # Static to stagnation pressure ratio at Mach 1 (found on table)\nTstar_T0 = 0.8333 # Temperature ratio at Mach 1 (found on table)\n\n# Use values from table to find pressure and temperature at throat\npStar = pStar_p0 * p0\nprint('Static pressure at throat', pStar, 'Pa')\nTstar = Tstar_T0 * T0\nprint('Temperature at throat', Tstar, 'K')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the pressure and temperature conditions at the throat of a converging-diverging nozzle. Please note that some values used in the calculation must be found on Gas Flow Tables. The throat temperature was found by the equation T = (T / T0) * T0, where (T / T0) is the temperature ratio at Mach 1 found on the table and T0 is the given stagnation temperature. The static pressure in the throat was similarly found by p = (p / p0) * p0, where (p / p0) is the pressure ratio at Mach 1 and p0 is the given stagnation pressure. To calculate this, we assume that the flow is steady, one-dimensional, and isentropic, and that air is an ideal gas.",
          "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2006) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
      },
      {
        "question": "The 2017 Ford GT features a structure in its bodywork referred to as a 'flying buttress' in architecture. On the vehicle, it appears as a tunnel, formed by a bridge over a dip in the bodywork. If the mass flow rate through the flying buttress is 3.592 kg/s when the car is moving 80 kilometers per hour, the velocity of air at the smallest cross section of the tunnel is 1.5 times the entrance, and the density of air is 1.293 kg/m^3, determine the area of the smallest point of the flying buttress.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nm_flow = 3.592  # Mass flow rate (kg/s)\nv1 = 80  # Air velocity at tunnel entrance (km/h)\nrv = 1.5  # Ratio of velocity at point 2 to point 1\nrho = 1.293  # Density (kg/m^3)\n\n# Convert v1 into m/s\nv1 = (v1 * 1000) / 3600\n\n# Apply the mass flow rate equation to find area 1 (m_flow = rho*A*v)\nA1 = m_flow / (rho * v1)\n\n# Apply principle of conservation of mass (rho*A1*v1 = rho*A2*v2)\nA2 = (A1 * v1) / (v1 * rv)\n\nprint('Smallest cross-sectional area in the flying buttress:', A2, 'm^2.')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code utilizes conservation of mass in control volumes, which states that the mass flow rate into the volume must be equal to out of the volume. This means that using any 2 points in an enclosed wind tunnel as an entrance and exit for a control volume, their mass flow rates will be equal. The formula m_flow = rho*A*v allows us to find the cross-sectional inlet area, which then lets us set up an equation from m_flow1 = m_flow2 to find A2. Alternatively, one can use the given information to calculate v2, then use the mass flow rate equation to find A2 acknowledging conservation of mass.",
        "reference": "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Flying_buttress"
    },
    {
        "question": "Water flows through a pipe that decreases in radius towards the end. Along a certain streamline in the water, the initial flow velocity is 3 meters per second, at a pressure of 1 bar. At the end of the pipe, flow reaches a pressure of 0.8 bar. What is the flow velocity along the streamline the end of the pipe? Assume water density to be 1000 kg/m^3.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nv1 = 3  # Initial flow velocity (m/s)\nP1 = 1 # Initial flow pressure (bar)\nP2 = 0.8 # Final flow pressure (bar)\nrho = 1000 # Water density (kg/m^3)\n\n# Convert pressure into pascals\nP1 = (P1 * 100000)\nP2 = (P2 * 100000)\n\n# Apply the Bernouli's equation to find the velocity along the streamline at the end of the pipe (P1+((1/2)*rho*(v1^2)) = P2+((1/2)*rho*(v2^2)))\nv2 = (((P1+(1/2)*rho*(v1**2)-P2)*2)/rho)**(1/2)\n\nprint('Flow velocity at the end of the pipe:', v2, 'm/s.')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code utilizes Bernoulli's equation to find the flow velocity along a streamline. The pipe decreasing in radius can both throw people off by suggesting use of an equation involving cross-sectional area, or serve as a hint that flow properties will change. The phrase 'along a streamline' suggests that Bernoulli's equation should be used, because along a streamline, the result of bernoulli's equation stays constant regardless of changes in flow velocity or pressure.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Due to mineral buildup in a house's water pipes, there has been a 250 Pa drop in water pressure to the taps. If the bulk velocity of the water flow is 5 m/s, the pipe is 5 centimeters wide, and the total distance of pipe from the water resevoir to the sink is 200 meters, determine the friction generated by the mineral buildup in the pipes. Assume friction is 100% caused by mineral buildup, and that without it the pipes would have been frictionless. Also assume a straight pipe.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\ndP = 250  # Drop in water pressure (Pa)\nL = 200 # Pipe length (m)\nD = 5 # Pipe diameter (cm)\nV = 5 # Bulk velocity (m/s)\n\n# Convert pipe diameter into meters\nD = D*0.01\n\n# Apply the Hagen-Poiseuille equation to find the friction in the pipe (dP = (8*mu*V*L)/(R^2)) where mu is the friction\nmu = (dP * (D/2)**2)/(8*V*L) \n\nprint('Friction in pipe caused by mineral buildup:', mu, 'N')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code applies the Hagen-Poisseuille equation, which states that the pressure losses in a pipe with friction is proportional to the flow velocity, pipe length, friction force, and pipe radius. It rearranges this relationship using the given information in the question to find the force of friction in the pipe.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "0.5 kg of air in a piston is brought isobarically from 5 celcius to 10 celcius isobarically in a piston. If the c_p = 1010 J/(kg*k) and R = 287 J/(kg*k) for air, find the change in internal engergy, dU, of the air in the piston.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\ncp = 1010 # Isobaric specific heat capacity of air (J/(kg*K))\nR = 287 # Specific gas constant of air (J/(kg*K))\nT1 = 5 # Initial temperature of air in piston (C)\nT2 = 10 # Final temperature of air in piston (C)\nm = 0.5 # Mass of air in piston (kg)\n\n# Find dh, the change in specific enthalpy (dh = cp * dT)\ndh = cp * (T2-T1)\n\n# Find Q, the heat introduced, acknowledging the process is isobaric (Q = m*dh)\nQ = m * dh\n\n# Find W utilizing ideal gas relations (W = p*dV, dV = (m*R*(T2-T1))/p)\nW = m * R * (T2-T1)\n\n# Calculate the change in internal energy (dU = Q-W)\ndU = Q-W\n\nprint('Change in internal energy:', dU, 'J')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code utilizes isobaric (constant pressure) equations for Q (Q=m*dH) and W (W=p*dV), as well as the ideal gas relation (pV=mRT). Most importantly, it relates the equation for work to the ideal gas relation to find the work throughout the process without knowing the pressure. This allows us to find the change in internal energy (U=Q-W).",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "A prototype railgun uses pressure to fire a projectile. Within the barrel are two chambers, one with high air pressure and a volume of 1 liter and one evacuated. When a burst disc between the chambers is burst, the air in the high-pressure chamber is rapidly pulled to the evacuated chamber, which propels the projectile. If the volume of the high-pressure chamber contains 0.5 kg of air, the two chambers rapidly come to equilibrium, and there is a 231 J/K change in entropy, determine the volume of the evacuated chamber.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\nimport math\ne = math.e\n\nV1 = 1 # Volume of high-pressure chamber (J/(kg*K))\nR = 287 # Specific gas constant of air (J/(kg*K))\ndS = 231 # Change in entropy (J/K)\nm = 0.5 # Mass of air in chamber (kg)\n\n# Given adiabatic process with no work, dU = m*cv*dT=0, meaning dT=0, resulting in\nT2=T1\n\n# Find ratio of total volume to V1 (V_rat=(Vtot/v1)=e^(dS/(m*R))\nV_rat = e ** (dS/(m*R))\n\n#Find volume of evacuated chamber (V2 = V_tot-V1)\nV2 = (V_rat*V1) - V1\n\n\nprint('Volume of the evacuated chamber:', V2, 'L')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code utilizes the formula for the change in entropy to find the volume of a chamber in a system. The bursting of a barrier to join the chambers results in no work being done, while the process occuring rapidly results in no heat transfer. This results in no temperature change, making the entropy formula completely based on volume.",
        "reference": "https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=s2yIMJ4iayg"
    },
    {
        "question": "A plane is flying through the air at mach 1.5. Using the moving plane as a reference point, If the temperature of the environment is 290 K, and the air at some point in front of the bow wave is slowed to 300 m/s, determine the temperature of the air at the same point.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nT1 = 290 # Environmental temperature (K)\ngamma = 1.4 # Specific heat capacity ratio (cp/cv) of air\nv2 = 300 # Velocity at point 2 (m/s)\nM1 = 1.5 # Mach number of environmental air\n\n# Calculate the stagnation temperature of the enviroment (T01/T1 = 1+((gamma-1)/2)*M1^2)\nT01 = (1+((gamma-1)/2)*(M1**2))*T1\n\n# Calculate the temperature where airspeed is V2 (T01=T1+((v1^2)/2cp)=T2+((v2^2)/(2*cp))\nT2 = T01-((v2**2)/(2*cp))\n\n\nprint('Temperature at second point: ', T2, 'K')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code utilizes two different formulas for stagnation temperature, one using mach number and the other using temperature and velocity. The temperature and velocity equation with different conditions can be related using T01 = T1+((v1^2)/2cp) = T2+((v2^2)/(2*cp).",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "A plane flies through the air with a mach number of 2. Air is deflected off of the 10 degree cockpit at an angle of 39.31 degrees. If the pressure of the air is 0.5 Bar at the plane's altitude, calculate the air pressure and mach number downstream of the shock.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\nimport math\n\nM1 = 2 # Mach number of air relative to plane\ntheta = 10 # Angle of cockpit relative to direction of airflow (Degrees)\nbeta = 39.31 # Oblique shock angle relative to airflow (Degrees)\np1 = 0.5 # Air pressure at plane's altitude (bar)\ngamma = 1.4 # Ratio of specific heat capacities\n\n# Calculate the normal mach number relative to shock (Mn1 = M*sin(beta))\nbeta_radians = math.radians(beta)\nMn1 = M1 * math.sin(beta_radians)\n\n# Calculate pressure downstream of shock ((1+((2*gamma)/(gamma+1))*(Mn1^2-1)*p1)\np2 = ((1+((2*gamma)/(gamma+1))*((Mn1**2)-1)*p1)\n\n# Calculate downstream Mach number (M2 = Mn2/(sin(beta-theta)))\nangle_radians = math.radians(beta-theta)\nM2 = (((1+((gamma-1)/2)*(Mn1**2))/(gamma*(Mn1**2)-((gamma-1)/2)))**(1/2))/(math.sin(angle_radians))\n\nprint('Pressure downstream of shock: ', p2, 'Bar. Mach number downstream of shock: ', M2, '.')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code utilizes the oblique shock relations to find the pressure and mach number downstream of the shock, utilizing the formulas listed in the notes above the corresponding lines of code.",
        "reference": "https://www.aerodynamics4students.com/gas-dynamics-and-supersonic-flow/table8.php"
    },
    {
        "question": "Imagine a jet ejecting mass onto some flat surface. When calculating force acting on the surface by the jet, why can mass flow out of the control volume be ignored?",
        "answer": "Assuming the fluid is frictionless, the force on the surface by the jet is completely perpendicular to the surface. Because the surface acts as a wall that mass can't go past, all mass flow out of the control volume has a velocity parallel to the surface, with no element normal to the surface. As a result, the equation F = ((mfr)*(v))_out-((mfr)*(v))_in has a value v_out of 0, which makes the mass flow rate (mfr) out of the volume negligible.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "A pipe carries water from a lake to a power generator inside a dam. If the pipe diameter decreases along its length, how would the velocity and pressure be affected downstream?",
        "answer": "According to the mass flow rate equation m_flow = rho*A*v, as the diameter decreased, pipe area would decrease, thus according to conservation of mass the water velocity must increase. However, according to Bernoulli's equation (disregarding gravity), p + (1/2)*rho*(v^2) stays constant along a streamline. As a result, due to the increase in velocity, pressure would fall.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "A large boat moves out of a ferry port with solid, stationary walls. As the boat continues moving, what can one say about the velocity of water between the hull of the ship and the wall of the port? There are no waves or external sources of water flow disruption in the port.",
        "answer": "The velocity of water increases linearly the closer it is to the ship, until it approximately matches the ship's speed when in direct contact. This is a display of couette flow and shows the existence of varying levels of shear stresses in the water between the wall and the boat's hull.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "What are 4 assumptions that can be made of the fully restrained slow heating of an ideal gas by an external source to a higher temperature?",
        "answer": "1. Process is isochoric and thus has no work. 2. The process is quasi-equilibrium as it is heated slowly, allowing the temperature to evenly change throughout. 3. All change in internal energy must stem from heat transfer. 4. Gas pressure increases according to the ideal gas law pV = mRT.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "A gas is slowly cooled down in a piston that keeps the gas at a constant pressure. The piston is well-insulated. What is the change in entropy throughout this process?",
        "answer": "Because the piston is well-insulated, this is an adiabatic process. Furthermore, because the process is quasi-equilibrium and maintains constant pressure via piston, it is reversible. These two conditions mean that the process is isentropic, so the change in entropy is zero.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "How does a refrigerator follow the clausius statement of thermodynamics?",
        "answer": "The clausius statement states that one can't transfer heat from a colder reservoir to a hotter reservoir. Conceptually, a refrigerator uses a refrigerant to absorb heat from the inside of the fridge, which is the colder reservoir. This heat as well as some external work input is used to produce work via compression, and the excess heat from this process is expelled to the environment. This is how the refrigerator is able to transfer heat from a cold to a hot reservoir.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "A wind tunnel with a converging and diverging section is choked at the throat. It is applied in a situation where the pressure in the converging section decreases. What can be said of the goal of its application, in relation to it's Mach number?",
        "answer": "Given a decrease in pressure at the converging section, one can infer that the Mach number at the inlet is less subsonic. As a result, the goal of its application is presumably to increase the wind speed to sonic or supersonic speeds, where the Mach number is more than 1.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the reason, function, and drawback for the section of a supersonic wind tunnel that comes after the non-choked diffuser?",
        "answer": "At the exit of a supersonic wind tunnel, the air pressure has significantly decreased due to shocks. Because of this, a compressor is necessary to bring this air back to the pressure required at the inlet, to maintain constant and consistent flow conditions in the wind tunnel. However, this compression causes an increase in heat of the air.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "How does the roughness of walls impact the effectiveness of airflow in underground tunnels, and how might this be a problem? (Hint: what compressible fluid mechanics concept involves a long tunnel with friction?)",
        "answer": "A rough underground tunnel is a real-life example of fanno-flow. The roughness of the walls increases friction on airflow, which results in slowed airflow closer to the wall. Furthermore, in most practical non-experimentation situations, wind entering the tunnel would be subsonic. In fanno-flow, the slowed airflow near the wall causes the air near the center of the tunnel to progressively increase in speed and decrease in pressure until it is choked. These high wind speeds and low air pressure are the problem, especially if in a tunnel with human workers.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Assume a submarine on a different planet is at a depth of 300m, and takes a pressure reading of 6450 kPa. Given that the acceleration due to gravity is 20 m/s, and the ocean density is 820 kg/m^3, find the atmospheric pressure on this planet.",
        "answer": "\nh = 300 # Depth (m)\nrho = 820 # Density (kg/m^3)\ng = 20 # Acceleration due to gravity (m/s^2)\np = 6450000 # Total Pressure (Pa)\n\n# Rearrangement of fluid pressure equation\npA = p - rho * g * h\npA = pA / 1000\n\nprint('Atmospheric Pressure: %f kPa' % pA)\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates atmospheric pressure by using a rearrangement of the fluid pressure equation at a certain depth. The equation used is p_i = p_a + rho * g * h, where 'p_i' is total pressure, 'p_a' is atmospheric pressure, 'rho' is density, 'g' is acceleration due to gravity, and 'h' is depth.",
        "reference":""
    
    },
    {
        "question": "We are given an oil pipeline for which we observe a pressure loss of 1kPa over a 4km section. The pipeline has a constant radius of 0.5m, and the oil flows at a velocity of 3 m/s. Calculate the viscosity of the oil.",
        "answer": "\ndeltaP = 1000 # Change in pressure (Pa)\nL = 4000 # Length of Pipe (m)\nr = 0.5 # Radius of pipe (m)\nV = 3 # Flow velocity (m/s)\n\n# Rearrangement of Hagan-Poiseuille pressure loss equation\nmu = deltaP * r**2 / (8 * V * L)\n\nprint('Viscosity of the oil: %f kg/(m*s)' % mu)\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the viscosity of a fluid by using a rearrangement of the hagan-poiseuille pressure difference equation. The equation is delta-p = 8 * mu * V * L / R^2, where 'delta-p' is the change in pressure, 'mu' is the viscosity, 'V' is the velocity, and 'L' is the length of pipe.",
        "reference":""
    
    },
    {
        "question": "We have a heat engine that taps geothermal reservoirs in the earth's crust to generate electricity. If the engine has access to a heat source of 150 degrees celsius, and the atmospheric temperature is 20 degrees celsius, calculate the maximum efficiency of the engine.",
        "answer": "\nt1 = 150 + 273.15 # Heat source temperature (Kelvin)\nt2 = 20 + 273.15 # Atmospheric Temperature (Kelvin)\n\n# Maximum thermal efficiency equation\neta = 1 - (t2 / t1)\n\nprint('Maximum efficiency: %f' % eta)\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the maximum efficiency of a heat engine by using the maximal efficiency equation. Note that the process must be reversible to reach this efficiency (called Carnot Efficiency). The equation used is eta = 1 - T2/T1, where eta is the efficiency, T2 is the external temperature, and T1 is the source's temperature.",
        "reference":""
    
    },
    {
        "question": "We are given an ideal gas at a pressure of 10kPa, and at a temperature of -20 degrees celsius. Calculate the density of the gas. Assume the gas has a molar mass of 4 g/mol, and note that our specific ideal gas constant is R = 2.1.",
        "answer": "\np = 10000 # Pressure (Pa)\nR = 2.1 # Ideal gas constant (J/(g * K))\nT = -20 + 273.15 # Temperature (Kelvin)\n\n# Rearranged ideal gas equation\nrho = p / (R * T)\n\nprint('Gas Density: %f g/m^3' % rho)\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the density of an ideal gas by using a rearranged form of one of the ideal gas equations. The ideal gas equation used is p = rho * R * T, where 'p' is the pressure, 'rho' is the density, 'R' is the gas constant, and 'T' is the temperature.",
        "reference":""
    
    },
    {
        "question": "During open heart surgery, surgeons use a cardiac bypass machine which conducts shaft work on the blood to continue circulation. Given that our shaft power is 20W, the density of blood is 1050 kg/m^3, and the volumetric flow rate is 0.2 kg/s, calculate the shaft work conducted by the bypass machine.",
        "answer": "\nP = 20 # Power (W)\nrho = 1050 # Density (kg/m^3)\nQ = 0.2 # Volumetric Flow Rate (kg/s)\n\n# Rearranged shaft power equation\nw = P / (rho * Q)\n\nprint('Shaft Work: %f J' % w)\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates shaft work by using a rearranged form of the equation for shaft power. The equation used is P = rho * Q * w, where 'P' is shaft power, 'rho' is density, 'Q' is volumetric flow rate, and 'w' is shaft work.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "We have a pitot tube attached to an airplane that outputs a stagnation pressure of 35kPa and a static pressure of 19 kPa. Given a gamma value of 1.4, calculate the aircraft's mach number.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\np0 = 35000 # Stagnation Pressure (Pa)\np = 19000 # Static Pressure (Pa)\ngamma = 1.4 # Heat Capacity Ratio\n\n# Pitot-Static Tube Mach Number Equation\nM_Squared = 2/(gamma - 1) * ((p0/p)**((gamma - 1)/gamma) - 1)\nM = np.sqrt(M_Squared)\n\nprint('Mach Number: %f' % M)\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the mach number by using the pitot-static equation which relates stagnation and static pressure to mach number. The equation is M^2 = 2/(gamma - 1) * ((p0/p)**((gamma - 1)/gamma) - 1), where 'M' is mach number, 'gamma' is the heat capacity ratio, 'p0' is the stagnation pressure, and 'p' is the static pressure.",
        "reference":""
    
    },
    {
        "question": "We have a supersonic aircraft in a wind tunnel. The temperature inside the tunnel is -10 degrees celsius, and the airspeed is approximately 650 m/s. Assuming a gamma value of 1.4 and an R value of 287, calculate the mach angle.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nT = -10 + 273.15 # Temperature (Kelvin)\ngamma = 1.4 # Heat Capacity Ratio\nR = 287 # Ideal gas constant\nv = 650 # Velocity (m/s)\n\n# Mach Cones and Mach angle equation\na = np.sqrt(gamma * R * T)\nmu = np.arcsin(a / v)\n\nprint('Mach Angle: %f radians' % mu)\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the mach angle by using the equation for calculating mach angle using mach cones. The equation is mu = sin^-1(at/vt), where 'mu' is the mach angle, 'a' is the speed of sound, 't' is the time elapsed (note that this term cancels), and 'v' is the velocity. We also calculate 'a' with the equation a = sqrt(gamma * R * T), where 'a' is the speed of sound, 'gamma' is the heat capacity ratio, 'R' is the ideal gas constant, and 'T' is the temperature.",
        "reference":""
    
    },
    
    {
        "question": "How does a pitot tube measure airspeed just using pressure?",
        "answer": "A pitot tube is a device that measures airspeed by comparing the static and stagnation pressures of the airflow. It takes readings from a forward facing probe (stagnation pressure) and a side-facing probe (static pressure). The difference in pressures can then be used to calculate relative velocity using the equation p_stagnation - p_static = 1/2 * density * velocity^2.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why does a velocity gradient form when shear stress is applied to a viscous fluid flow?",
        "answer": "Viscosity is a measure of the amount of internal friction within a fluid. Since this is not effectively infinite in a fluid (like a solid), the shear stress has a larger effect on the fluid closest to where the stress is applied. Shear stress is a measurement of the force per area acting parallel to a fluid. As we travel further away from the stress point, we have less shear stress transferred due to the finite amount of friction. This causes the fluid to form a velocity gradient instead of moving as one single mass, where the velocity is maximal at the point the stress is applied.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Can you elaborate on what causes the Magnus effect?",
        "answer": "The magnus effect is a phenomenon where a rotating cylinder/sphere in fluid will generate lift. This force will be in the direction of the side rotating with the airflow, as the cylinder is creating the same effect as an airfoil. Since the top and bottom of the cylinder are rotating in opposite directions, one side is accelerating the airflow over it, and one side is slowing it down due to the shear stress applied to the flow by the skin of the cylinder. This results in a pressure differential, where the side rotating against the stream (lower airspeed) has a higher pressure than the side rotating with the stream, and thus generates a lifting force.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "What does it mean when a thermodynamic process is reversible?",
        "answer": "Assume we have a system that undergoes a process in a certain direction (such as heat flowing from top to bottom). This process is reversible if we are able to change the direction so that we can have heat flow back from the bottom to the top. We know that this is possible when the system passes through infinite infinitessimally small steps, each of which are in thermodynamic equilibrium (or extremely close to equilibrium). The process can be considered quasi-equilibrium, which means that when we increment our process, we allow enough time to pass for everythign to stabilize again in the system.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why can't we return to certain system states adiabatically?",
        "answer": "An adiabatic process is one in which no heat is added or removed from the system. If we reach a certain system state by conducting work (such as heating water in a kettle), it is not possible to return to our initial state without removing the energy we added to the system. Note that if we achieve a state of higher temperature, but also decrease the volume of our system correspondingly, we can adiabatically return to our initial state. The only scenario where we cannot is if we needed to add or remove energy to reach the current state.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the characteristics of isentropic flow?",
        "answer": "Isentropic flow is defined as any flow where entropy remains constant. Entropy is defined as the amount of disorder in a system. Isentropic flow has no heat transfer within the flow as well, due to the definition of entropy, which means that the flow is also generally adiabatic (no heat transferred). Since the system is isentropic, we also know that the flow is reversible, as the flow is always at thermodynamic equilibrium. Finally, we know that the flow is steady, which means that there are no losses due to friction, turbulence, or any other disturbances that could cause a change in entropy.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "What causes the condensation over an airfoil at high angles of attack (assuming flow is subsonic)?",
        "answer": "When an airfoil is held at high angles of attack, assuming that the flow stays attached, it will generate significantly more lift. If the flow over the airfoil stays attached, we know that the pressure differential between the top and bottom of the airfoil increases drastically, as the air travels a much shorter distance over the top versus the bottom. This is due to bernoulli's principle, as we know that pressure and airspeed are inversely related (p + 1/2 * rho * v^2 = constant). This significant drop in pressure will decrease the temperature over the airfoil as well, simply due to the ideal gas law (PV = nRT), as volume is constant in this scenario. Therefore, the drastic drop in pressure will result in condensation forming, as the cooler air cannot hold as much water vapor, causing condensation to form over the airfoil.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why does a converging nozzle accelerate subsonic flow but decelerate supersonic flow?",
        "answer": "A converging nozzle is simply a nozzle in which the diameter decreases as we travel down the nozzle. When subsonic flow travels through a converging nozzle, we know that the flow will accelerate due to the continuity of mass flow. This states that assuming we have no external losses, the mass flow rate is equal at any point in a flow (m_dot = density * velocity * Area). Thus, as the area decreases, the velocity increases. However, when we have supersonic flow, our molecules downstream are unable to react to the change in flow properties as the nozzle converges. This causes the molecules to build up in a very high pressure wave (also known as a shock). This shock will cause a large amount of energy to be lost by our flow, as the high pressure and temperature will resist the flow. This will cause the downstream velocity to decrease even though the nozzle is converging.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why do rocket engines use smaller nozzles at sea level and larger nozzles in a vacuum?",
        "answer": "A nozzle works optimally when its exit static pressure (p_exit) is equivalent to the atmospheric pressure (p_atm). However, if we have a nozzle that results in p_exit > p_atm, the flow is considered underexpanded. This means that as the flow exits the nozzle, some of it will be directed horizontally outwards, as the flow will expand to match the atmospheric pressure. Likewise, if we have a nozzle that results in p_exit < p_atm, we consider the flow overexpanded. This causes some of the flow to be directed horizontally inwards, as the flow will compress to math the higher atmospheric pressure. Both of these scenarios will result in efficiency losses, as not all of our flow is pointed in the direction of our desired thrust. Therefore, rockets generally use a smaller nozzle at sea level, since the atmospheric pressure is higher and we don't want to expand the flow as much. Likewise, the vacuum stage of a rocket will use a large nozzle since we would like to expand the flow as much as possible, as atmospheric pressure is effectively 0.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    
    
    
    {
        "question": "Given a heat engine with a heat transfer value of 100 J between the heat reservoir and itself (Q1), graph the relationship between efficiency and the heat transfer between the engine and the cold reservoir (Q2).",
        "answer": "\nimport matplotlib.pyplot as plt\nimport numpy as np\n\nq1 = 100 # Heat Reservoir Heat Transfer (J)\nq2 = np.linspace(0, 100, 500) # Cold Reservoir Heat Transfer Values (J)\n\nx = q2\ny = 1 - x / q1 # equation for efficiency\n\nfig = plt.figure(figsize = (5, 5))\n\nplt.plot(x, y)\nplt.xlabel('Q2 (Joules)')\nplt.ylabel('Efficiency')\nplt.title('Heat Engine Efficiency')\n\nplt.show()\n        ",
        "explanation": "We can graph this relationship by simply using the equation for efficiency. The equation is eta = 1 - Q2/Q1, where 'eta' is efficiency, 'Q2' is the heat transfer between the engine and cold reservoir, and 'Q1' is the heat transfer between the heat reservoir and engine.",
        "reference":""
    
    },
    {
        "question": "Given a pipe that contains supersonic Fanno flow, graph the relationship between mach number and the skin friction coefficient of the pipe. Assume that the pipe's diameter is 0.5m, the length is 30m, and the gamma value is 1.4.",
        "answer": "\nimport matplotlib.pyplot as plt\nimport numpy as np\n\nD = 0.5 # Diameter (m)\nL = 30 # Length (m)\ngamma = 1.4 # Heat Capacity Ratio\nM1 = np.linspace(1.0, 5.0, 500) # Mach Numbers in the supersonic regime\n\nrightSide = (1 - M1**2)/(gamma * M1**2) + (gamma + 1)/(2 * gamma) * np.log((((gamma + 1) / 2) * M1**2) / (1 + ((gamma - 1) / 2) * M1**2)) # Right hand side of skin friction equation\n\nx = M1\ny = rightSide * D / (4 * L) # Isolate skin friction coefficient in equation\n\nfig = plt.figure(figsize = (7, 5))\n\nplt.plot(x, y)\nplt.xlabel('Mach Number')\nplt.ylabel('Skin Friction Coefficient')\nplt.title('Skin Friction Coefficient vs Mach Number')\n\nplt.show()\n        ",
        "explanation": "We can graph this relationship by using a rearranged form of the equation for the skin friction coefficient. The equation used is (4 * c_f * L)/D = (1 - M^2)/(gamma * M^2) + (gamma + 1)/(2 * gamma) * np.log((((gamma + 1) / 2) * M^2) / (1 + ((gamma - 1) / 2) * M^2)), where 'c_f' is the skin friction coefficient, 'L' is the pipe length, 'D' is the pipe diameter, 'gamma' is the heat capacity ratio, and 'M' is the mach number.",
        "reference":""
    
    },
    {
        "question": "What are stagnation pressure and temperature and why are they important in analyzing compressible flow through nozzles?",
        "answer": "Stagnation pressure is measured when the fluid is brought to zero velocity by a steady isentropic process with no external work. Likewise, stagnation temperature is the temperature under the same conditions. These properties are important in assessing flow conditions which can be used to analyze phenomena such as shock waves and flow choking.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "How does the concept of entropy relate to the second law of thermodynamics?",
        "answer": "Entropy represents the inability of a systems thermal energy to yield useful mechanical work. It's directly related to the second law of thermodynamics, as the law states that the total entropy of an isolated system always increases over time since not all heat can be transformed to work. Entropy helps characterize the direction of spontaneous processes and the efficiency of energy conversion.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "If you have a supersonic converging-diverging nozzle with a shock in the throat, how would you move the shock to the exit plane?",
        "answer": "You would decrease the exit static pressure. This is because the pressure ratio plays a crucial role in determining the position of the shock wave: a lower exit static pressure results in a lower pressure ratio across the nozzle.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "How and why are the units of enthalpy the same as energy, but enthalpy is not energy?",
        "answer": "Enthalpy is a measure of the total energy content of a system, incorporating both its internal energy and the energy required to overcome pressure-volume work. While the units of enthalpy are the same as energy (joules), enthalpy is not simply energy but rather a form of it. It is distinct from internal energy in that it accounts for both the system's molecular motion and the work done against external pressure.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "In what way do reversible and irreversible processes differ in terms of energy losses and efficiency?",
        "answer": "Entropy represents the inability of a systems thermal energy to yield useful mechanical work. It's directly related to the second law of thermodynamics, as the law states that the total entropy of an isolated system always increases over time since not all heat can be transformed to work. Entropy helps characterize the direction of spontaneous processes and the efficiency of energy conversion.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "How and why does the curvature of streamlines affect the application of Bernoulli's principle?",
        "answer": "According to Bernoulli's principle, when velocity increases, pressure decreases, and vice versa. So changes in velocity along curved streamlines directly influence the pressure distribution. The curvature of streamlines results in a pressure gradient across the streamlines and in regions where the streamlines curve more sharply (i.e. the center), the velocity of the fluid increases, leading to lower pressure according to Bernoulli's principle.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "Why is the pressure gradient equal to 0 in a Couette flow and how is this important?",
        "answer": "The pressure gradient in Couette flow is zero because the flow is driven solely by the shearing motion of the plates, rather than by pressure differences. Since there is no driving pressure gradient in the horizontal direction, then the momentum equation involving viscosity is equal to 0.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the relationship between the Mach angle and the angle of oblique shocks, and how do variations in these angles affect the Mach speed and flow?",
        "answer": "The relationship between the Mach angle and the oblique shock angle is described by the Prandtl-Meyer equation, which relates the angle of a Mach wave to the local Mach number of the flow. Higher Mach angles and larger oblique shock angles lead to greater flow deflection and pressure recovery downstream of the shock wave. This results in a reduction in Mach speed and increased deceleration of flow.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the effect of friction on flow velocity on subsonic and supersonic Fanno flow and why can the lower and upper branches of a Fanno flow not be transversed by the same flow?",
        "answer": "In subsonic Fanno flow, friction serves to reduce the effective area and increase the flow velocity, but in supersonic flow, the flow velocity is decreased due to friction-induced heating. On a T-S diagram, the flow starting on the upper branch is in subsonic flow, and moving downstream to the sonic state means that as entropy increases, enthalpy decreases, velocity increases, and static pressure decreases. In contrast, if the flow starts on the lower branch in supersonic flow, moving downstream means that as entropy increases, enthalpy increases, velocity decreases, and static pressure increases. These irreversible changes in flow properties exhibit why you can not transverse both branches without violating the 2nd law.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "A piston system containing 1.25 kg of N2O is initally at 298 K and 1.00 bar. The system then goes through a process where heat transfer adds 101 kJ to the gas, and simultaneously the piston is moved in such a way that the product of pressure and volume in the cylinder is unchanged. After the process has ended, the pressure of the N2O in the cylinder is 0.130 bar. N2O has a molecular weight of 44. (a) What is the entropy change of the gas due to this process. (b) Was this process reversible.", 
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np \n\n# Note: The problem indicates that pV is constant during the heat addition and thus temperature also remains constant.\n\nm = 1.25 # Mass of the gas (kg)\nR = 8314/44 # Gas constant \nT1 = 298 # Inital temperature (K)\np1 = 1*(10**5) # Inital pressure (N/m^2)\np2 = 0.130*(10**5) # Final pressure (N/m^2)\n\n# First law of thermodynamics in the 'Tds' equations: Tds = du + pdv leads to ds = du/T + mR(dv/v)\n\n# Integrating the first law leads to the equations for entropy for a perfect gas: s2 - s1 = cvln(T2/T1) + Rln(v2/v1)\n\n# Using Boyle's gas law: p1v1 = p2v2 and noting that T1 = T2 which cancels out the cv term\ndelta_s = m*R*np.log(p1/p2)\n\nprint('The entropy change is', round(delta_s, ndigits=3), 'J/k')\nif delta_s != 0:\nprint('This process is not reversible as we can see that the entropy change is', delta_s, 'Thus per the definition of irreversible processes it is not possible to attain or reverse the direction of process by extracting heat from the system')\n    ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the entropy change in a perfect gas. It uses the Tds formulas and its specific properties. Through these calculations we are able to decide whether or not the system is reversible",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Air flows isentropically through a duct where the area is changing from point 1 to 2, with no heat transfer or shaft work. The area ratio is (A2/A1 = 2.5), the flow starts at M1 = 0.5, and 4 bar. Find the Mach number and pressure at the second point in the duct.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np \n\ngamma = 1.4\nmach_1 = 0.5\n\nA2_A1 = 2.5\nA1star_A2star = 1.0 # isentropic\n\nA1_A1star = (1.0/mach_1) * ((1 + 0.5*(gamma-1)*mach_1**2) / ((gamma + 1)/2))**((gamma+1) / (2*(gamma-1)))\nprint(f'A1/A1^* = {A1_A1star:.4f}')\n\nA2_A2star = A2_A1 * A1_A1star * A1star_A2star\n\nprint(f'A2/A2star = {A2_A2star:.4f}')\n\n# Using the tables we can see that at A2/A2_A2star, M = 0.17 and at A1_A1star, M = 0.18. Using these values we must interpolate to find the precise M2\n\nmachs = np.array([0.17, 0.18])\nareas = np.array([3.46351, 3.27793])\nmach_2 = (machs[0] * (areas[1] - A2_A2star) + machs[1] * (A2_A2star - areas[0])) / (areas[1] - areas[0])\n\nprint(f'M2 = {mach_2:.4f}')\n    ",
          "explanation": "This code utilizes the relations held by the isentropic tables. By using ratios, such as the area ratio here we can figure out the stagnation pressure ratio for calculations and eveuntally the mach number.",
          "reference": "https://kyleniemeyer.github.io/gas-dynamics-notes/compressible-flows/isentropic.html,"
    
      },
      {
        "question": "A turbine produces shaft power from a gas that enters the turbine with a static temperature of 628 K, a velocity of 143 m/ and a stagnation pressure of 14 atm. The gas exits the turbine with a stagnation temperature of 275 K and a stagnation pressure of 0.95 atm. The gas passing through the turbine has a molecular weight of 16 and a specific heat ratio of 1.45. What is the stagnation pressure of the gas entering the turbine. Assuming the turbine is adiabatic, is it also reversible?",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nT1 = 628 # Temperature (K)\ng = 1.45 # Gamma\nv1 = 143 # Velocity 1 (m/s)  \nR1 = 8.314  # Gas constant (J/mol*K)\nmw = 16 # Molecular Weight (kg/mol)\n\n# Calculate the specific gas constant\nR = R1/mw\n\n# Use the specific heat derivation \nCp = ((g*R)/(g-1)) * 1000\n\n# Apply the formula for stagnation temperature \nT01 = T1 + (v1**2)/(2*Cp)\n\nprint('The stagnation temperature entering the turbine:', T01, 'K')\n\nT_out = 275 # Temperature (K)\nT0_in = T01 \nP0_in = 14 * (101.325) # Stagnation pressure in (pa)\nP0_out = 0.95 * (101.325) # Stagnation pressure out (pa)\n\n# Change of entropy is 0\ndelta_S = 0\n\n# Using the isentropic temperature vs. pressure relations\nP = (P0_out/P0_in)**(1/g)\nT = (T_out/T0_in)**(1/(g-1))\n\nif round(P, ndigits=3) == round(T, ndigits=3):\nprint('Yes, it is reversible')\nelse:\nprint('No, it is not reversible')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the stagnation temperature enetering the turbine with the given values and proves the process is reversible. It makes use of the fact that the process is adiabatic to then utilize the isentropic relations to show that it is reversible.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "A venturi with a throat to inlet ratio of 0.75 is mounted to the side of an airplane fuselage. The airplane is in flight at standard sea level. If the static pressure at the throat is 2050 lb/ft^2, what is the velocity of the airplane?",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nimport math\n        \n# The flow is incompressible and is assumed to be uniform, allowing us to use Bernoulli's equation.\n        \np1 = 2050 # Static pressure (lb/ft^2) \np2 = 2116 # Sea level air pressure (lb/ft^2)\nrho = 0.002377 # Sea level density (slugs*ft^3)\nA1 = 1 \nA2 = 0.75\n        \n# Apply the principle of continuity (A1*v1 = A2*v2) to get v2 = (A1 * v1) / A2\n        \n# Derive Bernoulli's Equation to isolate the variable v1 and utilize continuity, p1 + 1/2(rho)(v1^2) = p2 + 1/2(rho)(v2^2)\nv1 = math.sqrt((2*(p2-p1))/(rho*(((A1/A2)**2)-1)))\n        \nprint(f'v1 = {v1:.3f}')\n    ",
        "explanation": "This code makes use of the principle of countinuty for incompressible flow, where mass flow rate remains constant. Utilizing this principle, we are able to sub the cross sectional areas and v1 for v2 in Bernoulli's equation. Ultimately allowing us to solve for the velocity of the airplane.",
        "reference": "https://scorec.rpi.edu/~kjansen/AeroD/Fall_09/Homework_Solutions/HW_3.pdf (Problem 1)"
    
      },
      {
        "question": "Consider an oblique shock that forms in air at an angle 45 degrees. The conditions before the shock are 40 Celsius, 1.2 bar, and a Mach number of 3.0. What are the Mach number and flow direction after the shock?",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np \n\nmach1 = 3.0\ngamma = 1.4\nbeta = 45 * np.pi/180\n\n# Calculate the oblique shock deflection from shock angle and Mach\n\ntheta = np.arctan((2.0/np.tan(beta)) * ((mach1**2 * np.sin(beta)**2 - 1) /(2 + mach1**2 * (gamma + np.cos(2*beta)))))\n\nprint(f'Deflection angle = {theta*180/np.pi: .2f}°')\n\nmach_1n = mach1 * np.sin(beta)\n\n# Calculate Mach number after a normal shock \n\nmach_2n = np.sqrt((mach_1n**2 + 2/(gamma - 1))/(2 * gamma * mach_1n**2/(gamma - 1) - 1))\nmach2 = mach_2n / np.sin(beta - theta)\nprint(f'Downstream Mach number = {mach2: .3f}')\n  ",
        "explanation": "This code utilizes the normal mach number componenets seen by a moving observor to calculate the angle for the oblique shock. Calcualting the oblique shock deflection required us to use the impliction definition of beta(theta,mach). From there we were able to use the normal componenets of a normal shock to evaluate the mach number and flow direction of the oblique shock.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
      "question": "A supersonic air flow at M1 = 2.4 and p1 = 1 bar encounters a normal shock. Compute the Mach number in the post-shock flow M2 as well as the relative variation in the stagnation pressure and specific entropy. Plot the downstream mach number to the upstream mach number too.",
      "answer": "\nimport numpy as np \n\nfrom matplotlib import pyplot as plt \n\nM1 = 2.4 # Mach number downstream\nP01 = 1 # Stagnation pressure (bar)\ngamma = 1.4\n\n# Use the quadratic equation for M1 in terms of M2:\n\nM2 = (((2+(gamma-1)*(M1**2)))/(2*gamma*(M1**2)+1-gamma))**(1/2)\nprint(f'M2 = {M2: .3f}')\n\n# Apply the normal shock relations to obtain P1\n\nP1 = 1 + ((2*gamma)/(gamma+1))*(M1**2-1)\n\n# Employ the equation used for pressure ratio across a shock\n\nP02 = ((((gamma+1)*(M1**2))/(2+(gamma-1)*(M1**2)))**(gamma/(gamma-1)))/(((2*gamma)/(gamma+1))*(M1**2)-((gamma-1)/(gamma+1)))**(1/(gamma-1))\n\n# Now use the relative variation in the stagnation pressure formula:\ndelta_P0 = (P01-P02)/P01\n\nprint(f'delta_P0 = {delta_P0: .3f}')\n\n# Specific entropy can be found through S1-S2/Cv = -ln[(P2/P1) * (P1/P2^gamma)]\n\nP2 = (((gamma+1)*(M1**2))/((gamma-1)*(M1**2)+2))\n\nspecific_entropy = -np.log(P1/(P2**gamma))\n\nprint(f'specific_entropy = {specific_entropy: .3f}')\n\ngamma = 1.4\nmach1 = np.linspace(2.4, 5.4, num=10, endpoint=True)\nmach2 = np.sqrt((mach1**2 + 2/(gamma-1))/(2*gamma*mach1**2/(gamma-1) - 1))\n\nplt.plot(mach1, mach2)\nplt.xlabel(r'$M_1$')\nplt.ylabel(r'$M_2$')\nplt.title('Downstream Mach number versus upstream Mach number for normal shocks')\nplt.grid(True)\nplt.tight_layout()\nplt.show()\n        ",
      "explanation": "This equation uses the normal shock relations to figure out the required mach number, stagnation pressure and specifc entropy. It also plots the downstream mach versus the upstream mach number to showcase how the mach number upstream (M1) will always be greater than the mach number downstream (M2) for a normal shock.",
        "reference": "https://web.stanford.edu/~jurzay/ME355_files/HW2.pdf (Problem 1)"
      },
      {
      "question": "A system executes a power cycle while receiving 1050 kJ by heat transfer at a temperature of 525 K andndischarging 700 kJ by heat transfer at 350 K. There are no other heat transfers. a. Determine if the cycle is internally reversible, irreversible, or impossible. b. Determine the thermal efficiency. Compare this value with the maximum possible efficiency.",
      "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nQh = 1050 # Energy received by heat reservoir (KJ)\nQc = 700 # Energy lost to cold reservoir (KJ)\nTh = 525 \nTc = 350 \n    \n# To determine if the cycle is internally reversible, irreversible or impossible, consider the Clausius Inequality,\n# where Qh/Th = (1050 KJ)/(525K) = 2KJ/Kg and Qc/Tc = 2 KJ/kg leading to Qh/Th - Qc/Tc = delta_S\ndelta_S = 2 - 2 \n    \n# Note since Qc < 0 since heat leaves the system. We're also assuming that the temperature at the boundaries to the system where the heat is added/removed is the same as the adjacent reservoir. \n# Thus, we see that the cycle is internally reversible\n    \n# The thermal efficiency is mu = 1 - Qc/Qh \n    \nmu = 1 - Qc/Qh \n    \nprint(f'mu = {mu: .3f}')\n    \nmu_max = 1 - Tc/Th\n    \nprint(f'mu_max = {mu_max: .3f}')\n    \n# The cycle is operating at the maximum possible efficiency since it is internally reversible.\n    ",
      "explanation": "This code utilizes the Clausiuus Inequality to exhibit the cycle is reversible, it accounts for the heat being taken in and extracted. The thermal efficencies being the same further exhibit the cycle being reversible",
      "reference": "https://engineering.purdue.edu/~wassgren/notes/NotesOnThermodynamicsFluidMechanicsAndGasDynamics_Wassgren.pdf (Page 274)"
      },
      {
        "question": "A cylinder rotates about its axis and lies perpendicular to the flow direction, explain the Magnus effect on the cylinder in terms of fluid velocity and experienced pressure. Note that the flow is incompressible and uniform.",
        "answer": "The Magnus effect influences the flow velocity by combining the velocity at the cylinder's surface with that of the fluid velocity of the flow on one side of the object while simultaneously reducint the velocity from the other side of the cylinder. From the resulting change of fluid velocity on the different sides of the cylinder and the known Bernoulli's principle explaining a faster fluid results in lower pressure, it can be discerned that the side of the cylinder with the faster fluid velocity will possess a lower pressure than the side of the cylinder with much slower fluid velocity (which would possess a higher pressure).",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magnus_effect#:~:text=The%20Magnus%20effect%20is%20an,the%20object%20is%20not%20spinning."
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the difference between Eulerian and Lagrangian description for moving fluid particles? Which of the two uses advection in their respective equation?",
        "answer": "Lagrangian descriptions for fluid particles focuses on observing each particle as an individual, analyzing the properties of said particle at different times. Eulerian descriptions looks at the entire field of particles rather than individual points. Properties of the fluid and particles are looked at with respect to location and time instead of individual particles. Eulerian descriptions also use advection in their equation to describe particles.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Describe how the Coanda effect plays a role in the streamline positions across the top of an airfoil when faced by a jet of fluid.",
        "answer": "The Coanda effect explains that this jet of fluid possesses a pressure below that of the atmosphere, which results in the moving fluid to attach itself closer to the top of the airfoil as the jet flows across it. This appears as though multiple streamlines wrap closer to the top of the airfoil and follow the physical dimension of it until the tail.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the key characteristic of the following thermodynamic processes: Isochoric, isobarich, isothermal. What is the derivation for each process' external work?",
        "answer": "An isochoric process is one with constant volume, and with an absence of stirring in the process, the work performed is equal to 0. An isobaric process is one with constant pressure, and experiences work through a 'pdV' integral equal to 'mR(T2-T1)'. An isothermal process in one in which the temperature remains constant, and experiences work through a 'pdV' integral equal to 'mRT[Ln(V2/V1)].'",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Which ways can fluid equilibrium be disturbed, note that this is in the absence of margnetic and electric fields. Explain at least one of these types of equilibrium.",
        "answer": "Fluid equilibrium is disturbed mechanically, compositionally, chemically, or thermally. Mechanical equilibrium is based in the unifromity between pressure and velocity.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question":"How do turbines and compressors work together to produce shaft work?",
        "answer":"The two work to produce shaft work by using the turbine to create a pressure gradient that falls across the system, extracting work and applying it through the compressor to increase the pressure of the fluid. The work exchange is achieved with airfoil-shaped blades within the compressor-turbine system. ",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question":"Do the following properties increase, decrease, or remain constant across a shock wave: static temperature, statice pressure, work, heat, total enthalpy, density, and total temperature.",
        "answer": "A shock wave does no work and has no added heat, meaning they remain constant. Additionally the total enthalpy and total temperature across a shock are constant. Static pressure, static temperature, and density increase across the shock wave. Note that in the case of a shock that the total pressure downstream will always be less than the total pressure upstream, thus a pressure loss across the shock. ",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "How do the following properties change across an oblique shock and expansion fan: Mach, density, static pressure, enthalpy, and stagnation pressure.",
        "answer":"For oblique shocks, the mach downstream is less than the mach upstream, the density downstream is greater than the density upstream, the pressure downstream is greater than the pressure upstream, the total enthalpy downstream is greater than the total enthalpy upstream, the stagnation pressure downstream is less than the stagnation pressure upstream. For expansion fans, the mach downstream is greater than the mach upstream, the density downstream is less than the density upstream, the pressure downstream is less than the pressure upstream, the total enthalpy downstream is less than the total enthalpy upstream, the stagnation pressure downstream is equal to the stagnation pressure upstream. ",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question":"Describe the model for Fanno flow, elaborating any assumptions regarding the model and considerations.",
        "answer":"The Fanno flow model is used to consider compressible flows that experience friction, particularly in things like pipes or tubes. Assumptions about this flow include that the flow is steady, one-dimensional, is adiabatic, and, in the case of a duct/tube, the area is constant. Fanno flow is considered to be an irreversible process due to the effects of friction. Note that said friction is modeled to be similar to shear stress acting on the walls of the duct/tube. ",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Calculate the mass flows out of the tank with two inlets and one outlet. There are two liquids, possessing densities 300 kg/m^3 and 500 kg/m^3, respective to inlet 1 with an area of 0.5 m^2 and inlet 2 with an area of 1 m^2. Inlet 1 has a uniform fluid velocity of 4.4 m/s while inlet 2 has a uniform fluid velocity of 2.7 m/s.",
        "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n      \n      rho1 = 300 # Density of fluid 1\n      rho2= 500 # density of fluid 2\n      A1= 0.5 # area of inlet 1\n      A2= 1 # area of inlet 2\n      v1= 4.4 # velocty of fluid in inlet 1\n      v2= 2.7 # velocity of fluid in inlet 2  \n\n      # mass flow rates for each respective inlet\n      m1= rho1*v1*A1\n      m2= rho2*v2*A2\n\n      #conservation of mass states that the sum of mass flow rates in equal the mass flow rate out\n      m_out= m1+m2\n      print('The mass flow rate of the outlet in the system is'+ str(np.around(m_out)) + 'kg/m^3')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the outlet mass flow rate of the system, using the law of conservation of mass and known mass flow rate equation: m= pAv, where p = density (rho) of the fluid, A = Area of the opening, and v= velocity of the fluid.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Find the difference in pressure within a pipe that is 5000 meters long and a diameter of 2.5 meters. The fluid has a viscosity of 0.0035 kg/(m*s) and travels at velocity of 38 m/s.",
        "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n      \n      L= 5000 # length of pipe\n      v= 38 #bulk velocity of the fluid\n      mew= 0.0035 # viscosity of the fluid\n      d = 2.5 # diameter of the pipe\n\n      # utilize the Hagen-Poiseuille equation to calculate pressure loss through a pipe\n      m1= rho1*v1*A1\n      delta_P = (8*L*v*mew)/((d/2)**2)\n\n      print('The pressure loss across the pipe equals to ' + str(np.around(delta_P)) + ' Pa')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the pressure loss through a lengthy pipe using the Hagen-Poiseuille equation, using known information about the pipe's length, radius, experienced viscosity of the fluid, and speed of the fluid.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "A cyclic, nuclear powerplant uses nuclear reactions and the atmosphere to generate electricity. The efficiency of the system comes from using a hot reservoir created by the nuclear reaction and a cold reservoir created by the atmosphere around the reactor. Calculate the thermal efficiency of this reactor if the nuclear reaction produces a temperature of 205 degrees Celsius and the atmosphere has a temperature of 15 degrees Celsius.",
        "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n      \n      Th= 205  # temperature of hot reservoir in Celsius\n      Tc= 15   # temperature of cold reservoir in Celsius\n\n\n      # Convert the temperatures from Celsius to Kelvin\n      Th= Th+ 273.15\n      Tc= Tc+ 273.15\n      # Calculate the efficiency of the heat exchanger using the equation \n      Eta= 1 - (Th/Tc)\n      print('The efficiency of this powerplant is ' + str(np.around(Eta)))\n      ",
        "explanation": "The efficiency of a heat engine like the one in this example is solved using code that converts the temperature from Celsius to Kelvin and calculates the efficiency of the engine using the equation: Eta= 1- (temperature of hot reservoir)/(temperature of cold reservoir).",
        "reference": "https://phys.libretexts.org/Bookshelves/University_Physics/University_Physics_(OpenStax)/Book%3A_University_Physics_II_-_Thermodynamics_Electricity_and_Magnetism_(OpenStax)/04%3A_The_Second_Law_of_Thermodynamics/4.03%3A_Heat_Engines#:~:text=steam%2Dengine%20trains.-,Figure%204.3.,working%20substance%20through%20a%20cycle."
      },
      {
        "question": "Find the required rate of heat supplied by the heat exchanger to extract 4000 watts of energy from the cold space of a freezer. The freezer takes in heat at 750 degrees Celsius and has a cold space with a temperature of -20 degrees Celsisu. Additionally, heat is reject from the freezer at 10 degrees Celsius",
        "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n      \n      T1= 750 # Temperature of hot reservoir\n      T2= -20 # Temperature of cold reservoir\n      T3= 10 # Temperature of heat expelled to environment\n\n      # Convert all temperatures from Celsius to Kelvin \n      T1= 750+ 273.15\n      T2= (-20)+ 273.15\n      T3= 10+ 273.15\n      # Use the Claussius inequality equation to calculate the minimum heat supply rate\n      # Q1/T1 + Q2/T2 - (Q1+Q2)/T3 <= 0\n      # Solving for Q1, we get: Q1/Q2 >= ((1/T2)-(1/T3)) / ((1/T3)-(1/T1))\n      Q1= [((1/T2)-(1/T3)) / ((1/T3)-(1/T1))] * Q2\n\n      print('The minimum rate of heat supply from the source of heat is ' + str(np.around(Q1)) + 'Watts ')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the minimum heat supply for a freezer and from the heat source using the Claussius equation set-up.",
        "reference": "" 
      },
      {
        "question": "Find the flow conditions downstream of a shock (mach and pressuce) with the given upstream properties: mach upstream is 2.2, the pressure upstream is 68,000 pascals. Assume gamma is 1.4.",
        "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n      \n      M1= 2.2 # mach upstream\n      P1 = 68000 # pressure in pascals upstream\n      gamma= 1.4\n\n\n      # First calculate the mach downstream using the known normal shock equation for mach relations\n      M2_squared= (1+((gamma - 1)/2)*M1**2)/(gamma*M1**2 - ((gamma - 1)/2))\n      M2= np.sqrt(M2)\n\n      # Next calculate the pressure downstream using the known normal shock equations for pressure ratio relations\n      P2_P1_ratio= (((2*gamma)/(gamma +1))*M1**2) - ((gamma-1)/(gamma+1))\n      P2= P2_P1_ratio* P1\n      print('The mach downstream of the shock is ' + str(np.around(M2)) + ' and the pressure downstream of the shock is ' + str(np.around(P2))+ ' Pa')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code checks the downstream conditions for mach and pressure using the given mach and pressure upstream and using the known relations for these properties in terms of normal shocks.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Calculate the mach value of a fluid through a nozzle experiencing a temperature of 455 degrees Kelvin and a speed of 227 m/s.",
        "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n      \n      Temp = 455 # temperature of the fluid in the nozzle\n      v = 227 # speed of the fluid in the nozzle\n      R= 287 # gas constant\n\n      #assume gamma is 1.4 for this problem\n      gamma = 1.4\n      # Use the equation for mach: M= v/a and noting that a = sqrt(gamma*R*Temp) gives us:\n      a= np.sqrt(gamma*R*Temp)\n      M= v/a\n\n      print('The mach speed for this fluid is' + str(np.around(M)) + 'within the nozzle')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the mach speed of a fluid in a nozzle using the given temperature and fluid speed, as well as using assumptions about the values of gamma and the gas constant.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "A gas with a gamma value of 1.22 is compressed asiabatically to a fourth of its intiial volume. Calculate the pressure and temperature after the compression if the inital values are 50000 pascals and 225 degrees Kelvin. Additionally assume that this adiabatic process is reversible.",
        "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n      \n      gamma= 1.22 # gamma value of the gas\n      T1= 225 # intiial temperature of the gas before the process\n      P1 = 50000# initial pressure of the gas before the process\n      V1= 1 # initial volume of the gas\n      V2 = 0.25 # volume of the gas after compression\n\n\n      # Acknowledge that the adiabatic process is also reversible and thus isentropic. With this isentropic relations may be used:\n      P2_P1_ratio = (V1/V2)**gamma\n      P2= P1* P2_P1_ratio\n      T2_T1_ratio = (V1/V2)**(gamma-1)\n      T2= T1*T2_T1_ratio\n\n      print('The gas has a temperature of ' + str(np.around(T2)) + ' degrees Kelvin and a pressure of '+ str(np.around(P2)) + 'Pa' )\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the resulting temperature and pressure of an isentropic process using the relations known for this sort of process and applying the equations to solve.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Which orientation of a pressure-measuring inlet with respect to the flow direction corresponds to which type of pressure being measured and why?",
        "answer": "If the fluid flows perpendicular to the inlet and it is facing the flow, stagnation pressure is measured because the fluid's velocity is brought to zero. If the fluid flows parallel to the inlet, static pressure is measured because the fluid is in motion, and according to Bernoulli's Principle, the static pressure of a fluid decreases along a streamline as its velocity increases.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "When does a heat engine operating between two thermal reservoirs achieve its highest possible efficiency?",
        "answer": "A heat engine operating between two thermal reservoirs with temperatures T1 and T2 achieves its highest possible efficiency (n) when the ratio of T1 to T2 equals the ratio of heat transfer (Q1) from T1 to heat transfer (Q2) to T2. In this case, T1 is the warmer reservoir and T2 is the cooler reservoir, and the system is reversible.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "Why don't the values of stagnation properties change during an isentropic process?",
        "answer": "During an isentropic process, there is no energy loss, as it is also adiabatic and reversible. This means that static and dynamic properties can change, but overall stagnation properties will remain unchanged during an isentropic process.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "When can Bernoulli's Principle be applied and why?",
        "answer": "Bernoulli's Principle can only be applied along a streamline in steady, inviscid, and incompressible flow. It can be applied across streamlines only when they are parallel to each other and the flow is still steady, inviscid, and incompressible. This is because Bernoulli's Principle is a relationship between static pressure and velocity, which assumes constant density and no energy losses.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "What are the characteristics of flow experiencing an adverse pressure gradient?",
        "answer": "In viscous flow experiencing an adverse pressure gradient, the force originating from pressure differences in a pipe or other fluid vessel is directing the fluid in the opposite direction from which one of the surfaces of the vessel is moving. This causes the fluid and streamlines close to the moving surface to flow in the same direction that this surface is moving due to friction. As this momentum diffuses outward, the force generated from the pressure difference in the pipe becomes the driving force of the fluid, causing the flow to shift in this direction. This is an example of both Couette Flow and Poiseuille Flow occurring in opposite directions.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "What happens as you increase the pressure difference between the entrance and exit of a converging-diverging nozzle?",
        "answer": "This is done by decreasing the static pressure at the exit. If the flow entering the nozzle is subsonic, it will be choked at the throat if the ratio of exit static pressure to inlet stagnation pressure is 0.5283 or below. As you decrease this ratio, the location of the normal shock in the diverging section moves farther and farther down the nozzle towards the exit until it reaches the exit. This is assuming the flow is inviscid, and does not affect the flow conditions before the throat.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "What are the main characteristics of an expansion fan and why are these characteristics observed?",
        "answer": "An expansion fan consists of supersonic flow reaching a sharp convex corner where a series of Mach waves form a so-called fan. After the expansion fan, the Mach number increases, the static pressure, temperature, density, and enthalpy decrease, and the stagnation properties remain the same. The Mach number increases because the area of the flow increases, which is commonly observed for supersonic flow. The stagnation properties remain the same because the flow is isentropic, which stems from the fact that the changes across each individual Mach wave are minuscule. The overall flow property changes across an expansion fan are opposite from the overall flow property changes across normal and oblique shocks.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prandtl%E2%80%93Meyer_expansion_fan"
      },
      {
        "question": "What does the wedge angle (theta) causing an oblique shock affect?",
        "answer": "For a given Mach number, there exists a maximum wedge angle (max theta) beyond which the oblique shock becomes a detached bow shock that occurs before the wedge. For a wedge angle below this maximum wedge angle, there are two possible types of shocks: strong shocks and weak shocks. Strong shocks have a higher wave angle than weak shocks and strong shocks reduce the Mach number by more. Weak shocks are more common than strong shocks and are almost always chosen over strong shocks in AE 2010.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the use of the polytropic process equation?",
        "answer": "The polytropic index (n) of the equation explains what type of process is occurring during compression or expansion. When n equals gamma, the process is isentropic. When n equals 1, the process is isothermal. When n equals 0, the process is isobaric. When n equals infinity, the process is isochoric. When n is in between 1 and gamma, the process is non-adiabatic and there is some heat transfer.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "A fluid with a density of 1.125 kg/m^3 travels at 10 m/s through a main, cylindrical pipe with a diameter of 0.25 m that splits into two smaller pipes with a diameter of 0.1 m. The pressure at the end of these smaller pipes is the ambient pressure, 101325 Pa. The pressure upstream of the split is 3 bar and the velocity of the fluid exiting the pipes is 50 m/s. What is the force that the walls of the pipe exert on the fluid?",
        "answer": "\n  import numpy as np\n\n  rho = 1.125 # Density (kg/m^3)\n  p1 = 300000 # Inlet Pressure (Pa)\n  p2 = 101325 # Outlet Pressure (Pa)\n  A1 = (3.1415/4)*(0.25**2) # Inlet Area (m^2)\n  A2 = (3.1415/4)*(0.1**2) # Outlet Area (m^2)\n  v1 = 10 Inlet velocity (m/s)\n  v2 = 50 Outlet velocity (m/s)\n\n  # Apply Steady Flow Momentum Equation\n  F = (p1*A1) - (p2*A2) - (p2*A2) + (rho*(v2**2)*A2) - (rho*(v1**2)*A1)\n\n  print('Force exerted on the fluid:', F, 'N')\n      ",
          "explanation": "This code utilizes the Steady Flow Momentum Equation, which is a statement on Newton's 2nd Law, F=ma. It ",
          "reference": "https://www.homepages.ucl.ac.uk/~uceseug/Fluids2/Problems_2_Slides.pdf"
    
      },
      {
        "question": "A diverging nozzle with circular cross-sectional area contains water (density equals 1000 kg/m^3) flowing at a speed of 5 m/s at the inlet. The radius at the exit is 3 times the radius at the inlet. What is the velocity of the water at the outlet?",
        "answer": "\n  import numpy as np\n\n  rho = 1000 # Density (kg/m^3)\n  r1overr2 = 1/3 # Ratio of exit radius to inlet radius\n  v1 = 5 # Inlet Velocity (m/s)\n  pi = 3.1415 # pi\n\n  # Apply continuity equation\n  v2 = (rho * v1 * pi * (r1overr2)**2)/(rho * pi)\n\n  print('The water's exit velocity:', v2, 'm/s')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code utilizes the continuity equation that states that mass must be conserved when entering or exiting a control volume. This is expressed as mass flow rates at the inlet and exit equaling each other.",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "A perfect gas is compressed in a thermally insulated piston adiabatically and reversibly to a temperature of 500 K. Its molar mass is 28.02 g/mol and has a constant pressure specific heat capacity (cp) of 1039 J/(kg*K). Its initial pressure and temperature is 50000 Pa and 280 K. What is the final pressure of the gas?",
        "answer": "\n  import numpy as np\n\n  T1 = 280 # initial temperature (K)\n  T2 = 500 # final temperature (K)\n  p1 = 50000 # initial pressure (Pa)\n  cp = 1039 # constant pressure heat capacity (J/(kg*K))\n  M = 0.02802 # molar mass of unknown gas (kg/mol)\n  Rbar = 8.3145 # universal gas constant (J/(mol*K))\n\n  # Find the specific gas constant (R)\n  R = Rbar/M\n\n  # Find the gas's value of gamma (y)\n  y = cp/(cp-R)\n\n  # Apply isentropic gas relation\n  p2 = p1 * ((T2/T1)**(y/(y-1)))\n\n  print('Final pressure of the gas:', p2, 'Pa')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code uses three equations: the specific gas equation, an equation for gamma, and an isentropic gas relation between pressure and temperature. First, the molar mass of the gas is used to find the specific gas constant which is then used to find gamma by substituing (cp-R) for cv (cv is the constant volume specific heat capacity). Since the process is adiabatic and reversible, it must be isentropic, so the isentropic gas relationship is then applied to find p2.",
        "reference": "https://learncheme.com/quiz-yourself/interactive-self-study-modules/adiabatic-reversible-expansion-and-compression/adiabatic-reversible-expansion-and-compression-example-problems/"
      },
      {
        "question": "Air initially at 50 degrees Celsius flows over a wedge at a speed of 700 m/s. An oblique shock is formed at the start of this wedge, and the wave angle (beta) is measured to be 40 degrees. What is the wedge angle (theta)? Assume a gamma (y) value of 1.4 and an R value of 287.",
        "answer": "\n  import numpy as np\n\n  T1 = 50 # initial temperature (degrees Celsius)\n  v1 = 700 # initial velocity (m/s)\n  B = np.deg2rad(40) # wave angle (radians)\n  y = 1.4 # gamma value\n  R = 287 # gas constant for air (J/(kg*K))\n\n  # Find the speed of sound before the shock to find the Mach number\n  a = np.sqrt(y * R * (T1 + 273.15))\n  M1 = v1/a\n\n  # Find the wedge angle (theta)\n  theta = np.arctan((2/np.tan(B)) * ((((M1**2)*(np.sin(B))**2)-1)/(((M1**2)*(y+np.cos(2*B)))+2)))\n  theta = np.rad2deg(theta)\n\n  print('Wedge angle:', theta, 'degrees')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code utilizes the equation for wedge angle, which is used to find the wedge angle for various Mach numbers in the oblique shock tables. First, the Mach number needs to be found by finding the speed of sound using the equation a = sqrt(y*R*T1). Then, the values are plugged into the equation. This means that this problem can also be solved using the oblique shock tables instead of using this equation. This problem assumes the oblique shock is weak and that the gas is perfect.",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "A perfect gas flows steadily through a vertically oriented turbine which triples the velocity of the air from the inlet to the outlet. Its inlet is located 30 meters above its outlet and its constant pressure specific heat capacity (cp) is 910 J/(kg*K). The temperature of the gas at the inlet is 25 degrees Celsius and at the outlet its temperature is 97 degrees Celsius. Calculate the specific work done on the gas if the velocity at the inlet is 100 m/s and there is no heat loss. Account for changes in potential and kinetic energy.",
        "answer": "\n  import numpy as np\n\n  cp = 910 # constant pressure specific heat capacity (J/(kg*K))\n  T1 = 25 # initial temperature (degrees Celsius)\n  T2 = 97 # final temperature (degrees Celsius)\n  dz = -30 # change in height (m)\n  v1 = 100 # initial velocity (m/s)\n  v2overv1 = 3 # ratio of final velocity to initial velocity\n  g = 9.81 # gravitational constant (m/s^2)\n\n  # Convert temperatures to Kelvin\n  T1 = T1 + 273.25\n  T2 = T2 + 273.15\n\n  # Express change in specific enthalpy in cv times dT\n  dh = cp * (T2-T1)\n\n  # Apply steady flow energy equation after dividing through by m dot\n  w = dh + 0.5*(((v2overv1*v1)**2) - v1**2) + g*dz\n\n  print('Specific work done on the gas:', w, 'J/kg')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code utilizes the steady flow energy equation and some assumptions to make it more practical. Since the gas is perfect, the change in enthalpy can be expressed as cp times the change in temperature, and the statement of no heat loss means that the process can be considered adiabatic. This problem takes into account the changes in velocity and height, which affect the kinetic and potential energies of the system. Many problems only account for the change in internal energy, but with large changes in velocity and height, it is necessary to include these other forms of energy in the equation.",
        "reference": "https://www.studocu.com/en-gb/document/imperial-college-london/engineering-materials/steady-flow-energy-problems/14305523 (Example 2)"
      },
      {
        "question": "A gas flows through a converging-diverging nozzle and the flow is choked at the throat. The static pressure before the shock is 0.5 bar and the static pressure after the shock is 3 bar. Using the normal shock relations, find the ratio of density after the shock to density before the shock. Assume a gamma (y) value of 1.333",
        "answer": "\n  import numpy as np\n\n  p1 = 50000 # static pressure before shock (Pa)\n  p2 = 300000 # static pressure after shock (Pa)\n  y = 1.333 # gamma value\n\n  # Find Mach number before shock\n  M = np.sqrt(((p2/p1)+((y-1)/(y+1))) * ((y+1)/(2*y)))\n\n  # Find density ratio\n  rho2overrho1 = ((2/(y+1)) * (1/(M**2))) + ((y-1)/(y+1))\n\n  print('Ratio of density after the shock to density before the shock:', rho2overrho1)\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code utilizes the normal shock relations for static pressure before and after a shock and density before and after a shock. First, the static pressure ratio is used to find the Mach number before the shock, and then this is used to find the density ratio. This process can also be done using the normal shock tables. This question assumes there is no friction.",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "A perfect gas flows through a pipe that has a section that adds heat from an external source. Assume gamma (y) is 1.4 and the specific gas constant is 300 J/(kg*K). This causes both the temperature and pressure of the gas to triple. In another section of the pipe, there is a high amount of friction resulting in irreversible specific entropy increase of 40 J/(kg*K). Find the net increase in specific entropy throughout these sections.",
        "answer": "\n  import numpy as np\n\n  y = 1.4 # gamma value\n  R = 300 # specific gas constant (J/(kg*K))\n  T2overT1 = 3 # ratio of T2 to T1\n  p2overp1 = 3 # ratio of p2 to p1\n  ds_irrev = 40 # increase in specific entropy from the irreversible friction (J/(kg*K))\n\n  # Find cp from gamma (y) and R\n  cp = (y*R)/(y-1)\n\n  # Find change in specific entropy from external heat source\n  ds_rev = (cp*np.log(T2overT1)) - (R*np.log(p2overp1))\n\n  # Find the net change in specific entropy\n  ds_net = ds_irrev + ds_rev\n\n  print('Net increase in specific entropy:', ds_net, 'J/(kg*K)')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code utilizes an equation derived from the specific Tds equations. This code first finds cp from gamma (y) and the specific gas constant to find the change in specific entropy for the reversible addition of heat from an external source. There is also a source of entropy from the irreversible process of frictional losses that is added to the first specific entropy change to get the net change in entropy for this process of a perfect gas flowing through a pipe. This assumes that there isn't friction in the part of the pipe with the external heat source.",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question" : "What is the significance of the 0th law of thermodynamics? Why is it the 0th law if it is important?",
        "answer" : "The 0th law essentially says that temperature is an important indicator of thermal equilibrium. The 0th defines temperature as the following: if two bodies with the same temperature were to touch one another, no heat exchange would occur.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "https://www.vedantu.com/question-answer/mention-the-significance-of-zeroth-law-class-11-physics-cbse-5f224ae5c022a73b14d72501"
        },
       
       {"question": "For a steady flow that is adiabatic and reversible, why is the work defined by mass x cp x delta T and not m x cv x delta T?",
        "answer": "The first law for a closed system states that delta U = Q - W. For an adiabatic system we see that delta U = -W and derive that W = -cp x delta T. The steady flow energy equation however, is for an open system where we choose a control volume.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
        },
       
       {
        "question" : "A frictionless piston-cylinder device contains 10 lbm of steam at 60 psia and 320F. Heat is now transferred to the steam until the temperature reaches 400F. If the piston is not attached to a shaft and its mass is constant, determine the work done by the steam during this process.",
        "answer" : "\n    import numpy as np\n    \n    # We assume that the pressure remains constant and that the expansion process is quasi-equilibrium\n    # for a constant pressure process, W = P delta V\n    P0 = 60 # pressure \n    # V = mv since we can look up the specific volumes.\n    v1 = 7.4863 #specific volume at the given pressure and temperature\n    v2 = 8.3548\n    m = 10\n    conversionFactor = 5.404\n    W = round((m * P0 *(v2-v1))/conversionFactor,3) \n    print('The work done by the steam during this process is',W, 'Btu') \n    ",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "Michael Boles and Yunus Cengel (2010) Thermodynamics an Engineering Approach. Chapter 4.1 Moving Boundary Work, Example 4-2."
            },
           
       {
        "question": "A piston-cylinder device contains a liquid-vapor mixture of water at 300K. During a constant pressure process, 750 kJ of heat is transferred to the water. As a result, part of the liquid in the cylinder vaporizes. Determine the entropy change of the water during this process.",
        "answer": "\n    import numpy as np\n    \n    # Assume that no irreversibilities occur within the sustem boundaries within the process.\n    # Take all the water (liquid and vapor) in the cylinder as the system.\n    T = 300 # temperature in Kelvins\n    Q = 350 # heat in kJ\n    delta_S = round(Q/T,2) \n    print('The entropy change of the system is',delta_S,'kJs/K.')\n    ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the change in entropy using the definition of change in entropy delta_S = heat divided by temperature.",
        "reference" : "Michael Boles and Yunus Cengel(2010) Thermodynamics an Engineering Approach. Chapter 7.1 Entropy, Example 7-1."
        },
       
       {
        "question": "Can you give an example of a reversible adiabatic process and an irreversible adiabatic process?",
        "answer": "A reversible adiabatic process could be the expansion of steam in steam turbines. An example of an irreversible adiabatic process could be the expansion of a gas into a vacuum. For example, imagine a vacuum in a lab that gets ruptured and air gets in. Because the gas enters so suddenly, there is no time for heat exchange and because of entropy, the ruptured chamber cannot go back to a vacuum.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
        },
       
       {
        "question": "Why should I care about the Navier-Stokes Equations?",
        "answer": "The Navier-Stokes Equations can describe the flow incompressible fluids taking into account viscosity. The equation is too complex to completely solve in three-dimensional fluid flows but supposing they can be solved, the Navier-Stokes equations pose to be a powerful tool in predicting flows. The question of whether smooth, reasonable solutions to the Navier-Stokes equations in three dimensions was designated as a Millennium Problem in 2000 and a reward of $1 million USD is attached to its solution",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
        },
       
       {
        "question": "The flow velocity in the test section of a low-speed subsonic wind tunnel is 100 mph. The test section is vented to the atmosphere, where atmospheric pressure is 1.01 x 10^5 N/m^2. The density in the flow is the standard sea level value of 1.23 kg/m^3. The contraction ratio of the nozzle is 10-to-1. Calculate the resevoir pressure in the atmosphere.",
        "answer": "\n     import numpy as np\n         \n     # First we must convert our units to the proper ones. \n     V_mph = 100 # given velocity, in miles per hour\n     V_ms = (V_mph * 1609) / 3600 # velocity converted to meters per second\n     rho = 1.23 # density in kg/m^3\n     A_2 = 10\n     A_1 = 1 # area ratio is given to be 10-to-1\n     p2 = 1.01 * 10**5 # athmospheric pressure in N/m^2\n     p1 = round(p2 + ((rho*(V_ms)**2)/2)*(1-(A_1/A_2)**2),2)\n     p1_atm = round(p1/(1.01*10**5),2) # conversion to atmospheres of pressure\n     print('The pressure of the resevoir is', p1, 'N/m^2 or in atm,', p1_atm, 'atm.')\n     ",
        "explanation": "This code uses Bernoulli's principle and equation (3.31) from Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, 6th edition by John Anderson.",
        "reference": "John Anderson, (2017) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, Sixth Edition, McGraw-Hill. Chapter 3.3 Incompressible Flow in a Duct: The Ventury and Low-Speed Wind Tunnel, Example 3.6"
        },
       
       {
        "question": "What is the difference between the Magnus effect and the Coanda effect? Which one is responsible for the floating screwdriver experiment?",
        "answer": "The Coanda effect describes a flow that attaches itself to a curved serface. Imagine a stationary cylinder with a jet of fluid moving around it. As the fluid makes contact with the curved surface, it will \"attach\" itself to the surface and separate further downstream, well after it leaves contact with the cylinder. By contrast, the Magnus effect applies to a cylinder that is rotated in transverse flow and the rotation of the cylinder causes a lift force. The floating screwdriver, as seen in this video by Applied Science: https://youtu.be/jAYP6pWrdkc?si=PZWaAYBoJ9IE_TZp , we can see that the cylinder is not really rotating and is thus acting as a stationary cylinder, thus the Coanda effect is responsible for the flotation of the screwdriver.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
        },
       
       {
        "question": "What is the speed of sound on Venus?",
        "answer": "\n     import numpy as np\n     import math\n     \n     # The speed of sound is defined by the equation a = sqrt(gamma * R * T)\n     # Assumptions: The atmosphere of Venus is comprised of ideal gases, the temperature of the surface is 740K and atmospheric pressure is 9.32 Mpa\n     gamma = 1.233 # the atmosphere of Venus is mostly comprised of carbon dioxide 96.5% CO2 thus we use gamma for CO2 at roughly 400 C (670 K)\n     T = 740 # average surface temperature in kelvins\n     R = 188.92 # again because the atmosphere is 96.5% carbon dioxide, we assume R to be the value associated with CO2. Units are in J/kg K\n     a = round(math.sqrt(gamma * R * T),2)\n     print('The speed of sound on the surface of Venus is', a,'m/s.')\n     ",
        "explanation" : "This code calculates the speed of sound using the sqrt(gamma R T) definition, since the surface of Venus experiences winds that are upwards of 100 m/s, this code also assumes that all the gases are ideal.",
        "reference": "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carbon_dioxide_(data_page) , https://www.engineeringtoolbox.com/individual-universal-gas-constant-d_588.html"
        },
       
       {
        "question": "Why are weak shocks more common than strong shocks?",
        "answer": "Weak shocks are characterized by the mach number post shock remaining above 1. These shocks are preferred in nature as in a weak shock, the angle beta is smaller which is more typical. Strong shocks typically would require the mach number M1 to be very large and for beta to be large compared to a weak shock. This is simply less common in nature as nature does not enjoy a large increase in velocity of a fluid so rapidly.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
        },
       
       {
        "question": "Consider an oblique shock wave with beta = 35 and a pressure ratio p2/p1 = 3. Calculate the upstream Mach number.",
        "answer": "\n     import numpy as np\n     import math\n     \n     # Use of a table wil help with solving this problem.\n     beta = 35 # given angle in degrees\n     beta_radians = math.radians(beta)\n     p2 = 3\n     p1 = 1 # given ratio is 3/1\n     # Using a table of values, find that when p2/p1 = 3, Mn_1 = 1.64\n     Mn_1 = 1.64 # Mach value rounded to nearest hundredth, found by using table and pressure ratio\n     M1 = round(Mn_1/math.sin(beta_radians),2)\n     print('The Mach number upstream is', M1,'.')\n     ",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "John Anderson, (2017) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, Sixth Edition, McGraw-Hill. Chapter 9 Oblique Shock and Expansion Waves, Example 9.4"
        },
       
       {
        "question": "What is the speed of sound through water",
        "answer": "The speed of sound is defined as a = sqrt(gamma * R * T) but water is not a gas, thus that equation cannot be used. Interestingly, gamma for water is 1.0 but there cannot be a constant R for a non gas. From the NOAA (National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration) the speed of sound in water is roughly 1500 m/s)",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
        },
       
       {
        "question": "What can Bernoulli's equation be used for?",
        "answer": "Bernoulli's equation holds for inviscid, incompressible flows, flows along a streamline in rotational flow, and throughout every point in irrotational flow.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
        },
       
       {
        "question" :"Consider the inviscid, incompressible flow of air along a streamline. The air density along the streamline is0.002377 slug/ft^3, which is standard atmospheric density at sea level. At point 1 on the streamline, the pressure and velocity are 2116 lb/ft^3 and 10 ft/s respectively. Further downstream, at point 2 on the streamline, the velocity is 190 ft/s. Calculate the pressure at point 2",
        "answer": "\n     import numpy as np\n     \n     # This question is prefectly laid out to apply Bernoulli's equation. The flow is incompressible, inviscid and along a streamline thus we can use Bernoulli's equation.\n     p1 = 2116 # pressure upstream at point 1 in lb/ft^2\n     rho = 0.002377 # this is the air density in slug/ft^3\n     V1 = 10 # velocity at point 1 in ft/s\n     V2 = 190 # velocity at point 2 in ft/s\n     p2 = round(p1 + rho*(V1**2-V2**2)*0.5,2)\n     print('The pressure at point 2 is', p2, 'lb/ft^2.')\n     ",
        "explanation": "This code uses Bernoulli's equation to solve for the pressure downstream.",
        "reference": "John Anderson, (2017) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, Sixth Edition, McGraw-Hill. Chapter 3.2 Bernoulli's Equation, Example 3.2"
        },
       
       {
        "question": "Consider the isentropic flow through a convergent-divergent nozzle with an exit-to-throat ratio of 2. The resevoir pressure and temperature are 1 atm and 288 K, respectively. Calculate the Mach number, pressure, and temperature at both the throat and the exit for the cases where (a) the flow is supersonic at the exit.",
        "answer": "\n     import numpy as np\n     \n     # Recognizing that the flow is supersonic at the exit means that the M1 at the throat is 1.\n     M1 = 1\n     p0 = 1 # stagnation pressure in atm\n     T0 = 288 # stagnation temperature\n     p_t = 0.528*p0 # Find the pressure using the ratio of p_star and p0 when M = 1, 0.528 and multiply by p0 recognizing that p_star is the same as p_t\n     T_t = 0.833*T0 # Look up the ratio of T_star/T0 to find that it is 0.833 when M = 1\n     # Recognizing that the area ratio is 2, look at the value tables, for example Appendix A from Fundamentals of Aerodynamics Sixth Edition, find that M_e = 2.2 when A_e/A_star = 2\n     M_e = 2.2\n     p_e = p0/10.69 # when M_e = 2.2 p_e/p0 = 1/10.69 and since p0 = 1 atm, we multiply.\n     T_e = T0/1.968 # When M_e = 2.2, T_e/T0 = 1/1.968 and T0 = 288\n     print('The Mach number at the exit is', M_e,'. The pressure and temperature are', p_t, ' atm and',  T_t,' K respectively.')\n     ",
        "explanation": "Use a table to look up the relevant values according to the area ration, pressure ratio or temperature ratio given and the fact that at the throat, M = 1",
        "reference": "John Anderson, (2017) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, Sixth Edition, McGraw-Hill. Chapter 10 Compressible Flow Through Nozzles, Diffusers, and Wind Tunnels, Example 10.2"
        },
       
       {
       "question": "Can sound waves ever propogate non-adiabatically?",
       "answer": "Sound does not always travel adiabatically. From Wikipedia: 'The medium in which a sound wave is travelling does not always respond adiabatically, and as a result, the speed of sound can vary with frequency.' These frequencies however, are far outside of what the human ear can perceive, thus for almost all practical applications, the speed of sound is simply  sqrt(gamma R T)",
       "explanation":"",
       "reference":""
       },
       {
        "question": "Bob had a flat tire on one of the wheels of his car. After the car mechanic patched up the leakage, he proceeded to pump up the tire. While the mechanic was pumping the tire, Bob noticed that the pressure meter on the pump rose from 0 to 40 psi. He exclaimed, 'How was my tire reading 0 psi at first?! There is no way my tire was in a vacuum state at the beginning! Your pump meter is broken!' Was the mechanic's pressure meter broken?",
        "answer": "The pressure meter was not broken. The pressure reading was gauge pressure, it is zero at atmospheric pressure. Bob was thinking of absolute pressure where the value is zero at vacuum state.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Fireman is puttin off a fire using a water hose. Water flows through a hose at a constant velocity with a convergin nozzle at the end. Given the water is incompressible fluid, does the flow increase or decrease in velocity at the exit of the hose? Explain using conservation of mass.",
        "answer": "Flow increases in velocity at the exit of the nozzle. Since mass is conserved, mass flow rate in equals to mass flow rate out. Since the mass flow rate is rho*v*A, if A decreases and rho holds constant due to incompressibility, v has to increase.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "It's Evan's first time in the Aviation Museum, as he is excitely walking around the MD-11 plane, he noticed there are some pins sticking out from the nose of the aircraft under the cockpit window for measuring wind speed. If you are the tour guide, how would you explain this feature to Evan? Make sure to include the name of this feature and the principle the operation is based on.",
        "answer": "This is a pitot tube, and it is operating based on Bernoulli's principle (p + 1/2*rho*v^2 = Stagnation Pressure). There are two holes on this tube, one in the front and one on the side. the hole in the front makes head on collision with the incoming air flow. Therefore the pressure it measures is called stagnation pressure. The hole on the side doesn't make head on collision witht he airflow, therefore it measures the pressure called static pressure. If we subtract static pressure from the stagnation pressure. We have the 0.5*rho*v^2 term. Since we can determine what density of the air is at the moment, we can calculate the velocity of the aircraft at the moment.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Imagine you leave a pan of water outside under the bright sun. Soon after the sunlight heats up the pan from bottom and the water starts boiling. Since this is a cast iron pan, as you touch the pan handle you can feel the heat of the pan. Explain all three mechanism of heat transfers using this senario",
        "answer": "The process of sun heating up the pan is through radiation. Where the sun's heat travels through vacuum in the form of radiation. As the pan heats up on the bottom, the bottom part of the water heats up and rise. Therefore, over time, water got heated up uniformly through convection. At last, the heat transfers from the pan body to the pan handle through conduction as the cast iron pan is made from solid iron.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Which law of thermodyamics leads to the development of Clausius inequality? Explain this law and Clausius inequality.",
        "answer": "Second law of thermodynamics can be expressed in terms of Kelvin-Planck statement, which states that it is impossible to construct a heat engine that operates in a complete cycle and extracts heat from a single reservoir, converting it entirely into work. Buidling off of Second Law, Clausius inequality states that total heat transfer divided by the temperature at which the heat transfer occurs is always less than or equal to zero. Equality holds only for reversible processes, while for irreversible processes, the inequality is strict (less than zero).",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Imagine two rooms are separated by a door. One room is fill with balloons and other one is empty. Upon opening the door, the ballon of one room rushed to the empty room, until two rooms are in equilibrium of ballons. In order to restore to the original condition, you have to physically go in and move the ballons from the second room to the first. Using the terms of thermodynamics, explain this process.",
        "answer": "This senario represents an irreverable process. The ballon flow from one room to the other symbolizes the process. In order to return to the original state of the process, work needs to be done to the system (you picking up the ballons and moving them back to the orignal room).",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "In a recent trip to Kennedy Space Center, Amanda was walking in the Rocket Garden where she saw different rockets. One thing in common is the iconic bell shape nozzles these rocket have. Could you explain the design of these A de Laval nozzles (converging-diverging) nozzles in terms of increasing the speed of propellant flow out of the nozzles?",
        "answer": "A de Laval nozzle is the application of speeding up the fluid to a supersonics speed. In the converging section of the nozzle, the fluid speeds up to a subsonic speed. At the throat of the nozzle, the fluid reaches sonic. In other words, the nozzle is 'choked.' Upon entering the diverging section of the nozzle, the supersonic fluid go accelerated even more as the diverging nozzle speeds up supersonics flow while converging nozzle speeds up subsonic flow.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "When suerpsonics air flows along the surface of an object where the surface turns sharply downwards at a certain degrees. What type of shock is formed? Is the flow through it isentropic? Why?",
        "answer": "An expansion fan is formed. The process is isentropic (stagnation pressure and stagnation temperature doesn't change across the shock). It is an isentropic process because the flow makes infinitesmally small angle d(theta) turns, making the process gradual and adiabatic, unlike normal shocks.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "A flow is flowing though a pipe with friction. Explain what happens if the inital velocity of the flow is subsonic and supersonic. And why the phenomenon you described happens? Assume the pipe is long enough.",
        "answer": "If the intial flow is subsonic, the flow will reach the speed of sound (choked). If the inital velocity of the flow is supersonic, the flow will slow down. The phenomenon happens because the friction causes inconsistency of flow velocity across the cross sectional area of the tube, forming a converging nozzle. Which speeds up the subsonics flow and slows down the supersonics flow.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "The Reaction Control System (RCS) uses compressed nitrogen (Density = 1.251 kg/m^3) to propel spacecraft and correct their orientation in space (vacuum). The gauge pressure behind the converging RCS nozzle is 690,000 Pa. Consider the system to be at a steady state. Nitrogen is ejected from the nozzle at a rate of 80 m/s. Consider the nozzle to have a circular cross-section throughout. The diameter of the nozzle inlet is 5 cm, and the outlet diameter is 2 cm. Calculate the moment exerted on the spacecraft's center of mass (given that the moment arm is 1 m). Assume the nozzle is frictionless on the inside",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nrho = 1.251                     # kg/m^3\np_1 = 690000+101325             # N/m^2 \nA_in = np.pi/4 * 0.05**2        # m^2\nA_out = np.pi/4 * 0.02**2       # m^2\nv_out = 80                      # m/s\nv_in = (A_out / A_in) * v_out   # m/s\nR_arm = 1                       # m\n\n# Apply Steady Flow Momentum Equation (F = MassFlowrRateOut*v_out - MassFlowrRateIn*v_in) and principle of continuity (A1*v1 = A2*v2)\nF = rho * A_in * v_in * (v_out - v_in) - p_1 * A_in\nM = F*R_arm\nprint(str(np.round(M,3))+' N*M')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code utilizes the principle of continuity and steady flow momentum equation for incompressible flow, which states that the mass flow rate remains constant and net force is the difference in inlet-outlet mass flow rate times velocity. The equation A1*v1 = A2*v2 and F = MassFlowrRateOut*v_out - MassFlowrRateIn*v_in expresses this, where A represents cross-sectional area and v represents velocity. We have to be careful that the exit ambient pressure is zero Pa and we have to convert inlet gauge pressure to absolute pressure by adding the atmospheric pressure",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Imagine a T-shaped tube with the bottom of the T connected to a water reservoir with water density rho = 1000 kg/m^3, and atmospheric pressure exerting on the surface of the water. Airflow with density rho = 1.293 kg/m^3 is flowing at 100 m/s in the horizontal section of the T tube. How high will the water rise in the vertical section of the T tube? Assume the vertical section of the tube is long enough, and water won't flow into the horizontal section of the tube.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nrho_water = 1000                # kg/m^3\nrho_air = 1.293                 # kg/m^3\nv_air = 100                     # m/s\ng = 9.81                        # m/s^2\n\n# Apply Bernoulli's principle with two points, one in the moving air in the horizontal section of the tube and the second one in the still air region in the vertical section of the tube.\ndelta_p = 0.5*rho_air*v_air**2  # Pa, difference in static pressure of the moving air and the still air in the horizontal and vertical section of the tube\ndelta_h = delta_p/(rho_water*g) # m^2\nprint(str(np.round(delta_h,3))+' M')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This problem utilizes Bernoulli's equation for incompressible flow, which states that the total pressure along a streamline of incompressible flow remains constant. The equation p_1 + 1/2*rho*v_1^2 = p_2 + 1/2*rho*v_2^2 expresses this principle. Then we utilize fluids statics equation. The equation delta_p = rho*g*delta_h expresses this",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Continuing with the previous RCS thruster scenario, after the nitrogen thruster tank is depleted (0 Pa), a replenishing valve that connects the thruster tank to a reservoir tank (P = 690,000 Pa, T = 273 K) opens. The thruster tank is filled adiabatically until it matches the pressure of the reservoir. Assuming nitrogen behaves as a perfect gas with R = 0.2968 kJ/(kg*K) and gamma = 1.470, and given that the volume of the tank is 0.01 m^3, find the final temperature of the gas and its mass inside the thruster tank.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\ngamma = 1.470\nR = 0.2968          # kJ/(kg*K)\nP = 690000          # Pa\nT_initial = 273     # K\nV = 0.01            # m^3\n\n# First Law: Q - W = delta(U) = c_v*delta(T)\nT_final = gamma*T_initial\n\n# Ideal Gas Law: PV = mRT\nmass = P*V/(R*1000*T_final)\nprint('Raise in temperature: '+str(np.round(T_final,3))+' K, '+'mass: '+str(np.round(mass,3))+' kg')\n        ",
        "explanation": "We approach this problem by finding the work done by the reservoir tank to the control volume of the gas entering the thruster tank, which is p*delta(V). Then we can utilize First Law in Thermodynamics and set Q to be 0 due to adiabatic process and delta(U) to be m*c_v*delta(T). Since we know c_v - c_p = R and c_p/c_v = gamma, we can find T_final using these relationships. Finally, knowing T_final, we can utilize ideal gas law (PV = mRT) to find the mass inside the thruster tank",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "A cyclic machine is designed to take in heat from two heat sources: A at 1K and B at 1000K and reject the heat into the environment at 300K. If source A is supplying the machine with a power of 200 kW, will that be enough for the machine to remove heat from source B at a power of 5 kW?",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nT_A = 1000      #K\nT_B = 1         #K\nT_EN = 300      #K\nBDot = 5        #kW\nADot = (1./T_B - 1./T_EN)/(1./T_EN - 1./T_A) * BDot\nprint('No, the power supplied by A is not enough. The minimum power from A is '+str(np.round(ADot, 3))+' kW')\n\n        ",
        "explanation": "Since the machine is cyclic, the power input should equal the power output. In other words, ADot + BDot = ENDot. We can utilize the Clausius inequality, namely sum(dot(Q_i)/T_i) ≤ 0. With this inequality given, we can calculate the minimum power needed from source A to achieve the extraction power from source B.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "For a long cylindrical pipe with friction and a convergent-divergent nozzle installed at the front, given that the nozzle is choked and with the right back pressure, the nozzle is able to achieve an exit velocity of Mach 2. What is the maximum length of the pipe to accelerate/decelerate the flow, given the nozzle capability and a pipe skin coefficient of 0.1, and a diameter of 0.5m?",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nc_f = 0.1 \nD = 0.5 # m\nmach_lowBackPressure = 2\n\n# look up flowCapacity in given mach number\nflowCapacity = 0.7591\n\n# look up 4*c_f*L_{max}/D in given mach number\nLmaxConst_lowBackPressure = 0.305\n\n# look up same flowCapacity in subsonic flow condition\nmach_highBackPressure = 0.37;\n\n# look up 4*c_f*L_{max}/D in given mach number\nLmaxConst_highBackPressure = 2.93\n\n#calculate length\nL = LmaxConst_highBackPressure*D/(4*c_f)\n\nprint('The maximum length of the pipe is '+str(np.round(L, 3))+' M')\n\n        ",
        "explanation": "In this question, we should notice that when the nozzle is choked, the flow can be either supersonic or subsonic at the exit for the convergent-divergent nozzle, and these two flow conditions have the same flow capacity. However, the subsonic flow condition should have a higher length.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Continuing with the previous RCS thruster scenario, what is the maximum mass flow rate this nozzle can support? Given that c_p of N2 is 1040 J/(kg*K) when the tank temperature is 300K, and assuming gamma = 1.4.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nA_out = np.pi/4 * 0.02**2       # m^2\np_0 = 690000+101325             # N/m^2 \nT_0 = 300                       # K\nc_p = 1040                      # J/(kg*K)\n\n# the nozzle is choked at Mach 1\nMDot = 1.281*A_out*p_0/(np.sqrt(T_0*c_p))\nprint(str(np.round(MDot,3))+' kg/s')\n        ",
        "explanation": "The nozzle reaches the maximum mass flow rate when the flow is choked. Since P_0 at the tank is the same as P_0 at the nozzle, we can use a lookup table to find the flow capacity at Mach 1 and plug in the given constants to find the mass flow rate at that point, which is the maximum mass flow rate.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Imagine a convergent-divergent nozzle. The inlet stagnation pressure is 500,000 Pa, and the outlet stagnation pressure is 250,000 Pa. What is the strength of the shock at the divergent section of the nozzle? What happens to the position of the shock if we decrease the back pressure?",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\np0s = 250000 #Pa\np0 = 500000  #Pa\nratio = p0s/p0\n\n#find ratio on the lookup table\nstrength = 0.514 # mach number\nprint('Strength of shock is '+str(strength)+' Mach. If we reduce the back pressure, the shock will move backwards along the nozzle')\n        ",
        "explanation": "Given the pre-shock and post-shock stagnation pressure, we can use the ratio to find the Mach number when the shock occurs and determine the strength of the shock. If the back pressure is decreased, the flow reaches a higher velocity before the shock forms. In other words, the flow has more time to accelerate in the nozzle before the shock slows it down.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the difference in velocity profile of water and blood in a pipe, assuming viscous flow?",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\nimport matplotlib.pyplot as plt\n\nviscosity_1 = 1.0           # viscosity of the water\nvisocsity_2 = 4.0           # viscosity of honey\npressure_drop_1 = 1.0       # pressure drop across the pipe\npressure_drop_2 = 2.0       #\nradius = 5.0                # radius of the pipe\ny_center = 5.0              # center of the pipe\n\ny = np.linspace(0, 10, 100)\n\n# Calculate the velocity profile using the Poiseuille equation\n# 1. Comparing changes in visocisty\nvelocity_profile_1 = (pressure_drop_1 / (2 * viscosity_1)) * (radius**2 - (y - y_center)**2)\nvelocity_profile_2 = (pressure_drop_1 / (2 * visocsity_2)) * (radius**2 - (y - y_center)**2)\n\nplt.plot(velocity_profile_1, y, label='Water')\nplt.plot(velocity_profile_2, y, label='Blood')\nplt.xlabel('Velocity')\nplt.ylabel('Pipe length')\nplt.title('Velocity Profile of Poiseuille Flow with different viscosity')\nplt.legend()\nplt.grid(False)\nplt.axhline(y=0, color='black', linestyle='-', linewidth=2)\nplt.axhline(y=10, color='black', linestyle='-', linewidth=2)\nplt.show()\n        ",
        "explanation":"When we talk about viscous flow, we look at Poiseuille flow and the Poiseuille flow equation. When comparing the viscosity of blood to water, blood is approximately 4 times more viscous than water. hence, with a pipe of the same diameter and the same pressure drop along the pipe, the velocity of blood will be lower than that of water flowing through the same pipe. This visualization clearly shows the the Poiseuille flow variation for 2 fluids with different viscosities.",
        "reference": "https://hyperphysics.phy-astr.gsu.edu/hbase/Tables/viscosity.html"
    },
    {
        "question": "How do you determine the reservoir pressure and temperature to create a wind tunnel that has a Mach 2 flow at standard sea-level conditions at the exit?",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nM_exit = 2              # Mach no. at exit (no units)\np_exit = 1.01 * 10**5   # Pressure at exit (N/m^2)\nt_exit = 288.16         # Temperature at exit (K)\ngamma = 1.4             # gamma (no units)\n\n# Using stagnation temperature equation\nt_0 = t_exit * (1 + (gamma - 1)/2 * M_exit**2 )\nprint('Reservoir temperature:', t_0, 'Kelvin')\n\n# Using stagnation pressure equation\np_0 = p_exit * (1 + (gamma - 1)/2 * M_exit**2)**(gamma/(gamma-1))\nprint('Reservoir pressure:', p_0, 'N/m^2')\n                ",
        "explanation":"Clearly, this question requires the use of compressible flow equations. In the wind tunnel, we can assume that the there is steady and isentropic flow. We can then apply the stagnation temperature and pressure equations knowing the exit conditions are sea level conditions.",
        "reference": "Anderson, J. D., Jr. (2015). Introduction to flight. McGraw-Hill Education. Example 4.33"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider an airfoil where far upstream, the pressure, velocity, and density are 2116 lb/ft^2, 146.7 ft/s, and 0.002377 slug/ft^3, respectively. How would you find the velocity at point A, given the pressure at point A is 2070 lb/ft^2 ?",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nv_1 = 146.7         # velocity upstream (ft/s)\np_1 = 2116          # pressure upstream (lb/ft^2)\nrho = 0.002377      # density (slug/ft^3) constant, since incompressible\np_a = 2070          # pressure at poitn A (lb/ft^2)\n\n#Using Bernoulli's equation across a streamline: p_1 + (rho*v_1**2)/2 = p_a + (rho*v_a**2)/2 \nv_a = (2 * (p_1 - p_a)/rho + v_1**2)**0.5\nprint('Velocity at point A:', v_a, 'ft/s')\n                ",
        "explanation": "Since 146.7 ft/s is low enough compared to the speed of sound (1125 ft/s) to assume incompressible flow, we can use Bernoulli's equation here, since point A and the point far upstream are on the same streamline.",
        "reference": "Anderson, J. D., Jr. (2015). Introduction to flight. McGraw-Hill Education. Example 4.3"
    },
    {
        "question": "Air enters the diffuser of a jet engine operating at steady state at 18 kPa, 216 K, and a velocity of 265 m/s. The air flows adiabatically through the diffuser and is at a temperature of 250 K at the diffuser exit. Assuming an ideal gas model for air, what is the velocity of the air at the diffuser exit?",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\np_1 = 18            # pressure in (kPa)\nv_1 = 265           # velocity in (m/s)\nT_1 = 216           # Temperature inlet (K)\nT_2 = 250           # Temperature exit (K)\ncp = 1005           # J/(kg K)\n\n# Using steady flow energy equation: q - w = (h2 + v2^2/2 + gz2) - (h1 + v1^2/2 + gz1)\nv_2 = (2*cp*(T_1-T_2) + v_1**2)**0.5\nprint('Velocity at diffuser:', v_2, 'm/s')\n                ",
        "explanation": "Using the steady flow energy equation, Q = 0 since it is adiabatic, W = 0 as no work is done on the fluid, and there is a negligible change in altitude, hence simplyfing the equation to: h2-h1 = 0.5(v1^2 - v2^2). Assuming a calorically perfect gas, h2-h1 = cp*(T2-T1).",
        "reference":""
        },
    {
        "question": "A mercury U-tube manometer is inserted in a water pipe with varying diameter carrying water at 20 degrees Celsius. One end of the manometer is placed with its opening facing the incoming flow at a section of the pipe where diameter = 10cm. The other end of the manometer is placed with its opening perpendicular to the flow at a downstream section of the pipe where diameter = 6cm. If the pressure at the pipe with diameter = 10cm is 170 kPa and the difference in height of the manometer is 8cm, what is the flow rate? The density of mercury is 1360 kg/m^3, and that of water is 998.2 kg/m^3 at 20 degrees Celsius.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nD_1 = 10            # diameter upstream (cm)\nD_2 = 6             # diameter downstream (cm)\nrho_M = 1360        # density of mercury (kg/m^3)\nrho_W = 998.2       # density of water (kg/m^3)\np_1 = 170000        # pressure upstream at D_1 (Pa)\ndelta_h = 8         # manometer height difference (cm)\ng = 9.81            # acceleration due to gravity (m/s^2)\n\n# Using manometer height difference and pressure upstream, we can calculate pressure downstream\np_2 = p_1 - (rho_M - rho_W)* g * (delta_h * 10**-2)\nprint('Pressure downstream at D_2:',p_2,'Pa')\n\n# Using Bernoulli's equation, we can find the velocity downstream\nv_2 = (2*(p_1-p_2)/rho_W)**0.5\nprint('Velocity downstream:',v_2,'m/s')\n\n# Find flow rate using Q = V * A\nQ = v_2 * (D_2 * 10**-2)**2 * 3.14 /4\nprint('Flow rate:',Q,'m^3/s')\n        ",
        "explanation": "Firstly, we have to figure out the pressure downstream. Using the U-tube manometer heigh difference, we can find the pressure difference by subtracting the weight of the water from the weight of the mercury. Next, knowing that there is a pressure difference between upstream and downstream, we can use bernoulli's equation to calculate the velocity downstream. Using the downstream velocity and the diameter of the pipe downstream (6cm), we can multiply them together to get the flow rate through the pipe downstream.",
        "reference": "University of Iowa. Mechanics of Fluids and Transport. Fall 2007 Exam 1"
    },
    {
        "question": "The velocity and temperature of the flow ahead of a normal shock wave are 1215 m/s and 300 K, respectively. Calculate the velocity of the flow behind the shock.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\ngamma = 1.4         # gamma (no units)\nR = 287             # specific gas constant (J/kg K)\nv_1 = 1215          # velocity upstream (m/s)\nT_1 = 300           # temperature upstream (K)\n\n# Find speed of sound at T_1 = 300K\na_1 = (gamma * R * T_1)**0.5\n\n# Find mach number before normal shock\nM_1 = v_1 / a_1\nprint ('Mach number before normal shock:', M_1)\n\n# From gas properties table: at Mach number = 3.5:\nM_2 = 0.4512        # Mach number after normal shock\nT_21 = 3.315        # ratio of post shock temperature to pre shock\n\n# Calculate post shock temperature\nT_2 = T_21 * T_1\n\n# Calculate speed of sound at T_2\na_1 = (gamma * R * T_2)**0.5\n\n# Calculate velocity of flow using speed of sound and mach number\nv_2 = M_2 * a_1\n\nprint('Velocity of flow behind normal shock:',v_2,'m/s')\n        ",
        "explanation": "In this question, it is given that there a normal shock exists, hence the normal shock relations and tables will be used. Firstly, the mach number before the shock needs to be calculated. Using the temperature given, the speed of sound can be calculated, and used with the speed of the flow to calculate the Mach number of the flow before the shock. Using the Mach number and searching for the corresponding Mach number and Temperature ratios in the gas properties table, the post shock temperature can be calculated. Next, the speed of sound and hence the velocity of flow behind the normal shock can be calculated.",
        "reference": "Anderson, J. D., Jr. (2017). Fundamentals of Aerodynamics. McGraw-Hill Education. Example 8.18"
    },
    {
        "question": "Consider a low-speed subsonic wind tunnel with a resrvoir cross-sectional area A_1 = 2m^2 and a test-section cross-sectional area A_2 = 0.5m^2. The pressure in the test section is p_2 = 1 atm, and the density is constant at rho = 1.23 kg/m^3. What is the pressure required in the reservoir p_1 to achieve a flow velocity v_2 = 40m/s in the test section?",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nA_1 = 2             # reservoir cross-sectional area (m^2)\nA_2 = 0.5           # test-section cross-sectional area (m^2)\np_2 = 1.01 * 10**5  # pressure in test-section (N/m^2)\nrho = 1.23          # density (kg/m^3)\nv_2 = 40            # given desired test-section flow velocity (m/s)\n\n# Find velocity required in reservoir, using continuity: A1*V1 = A2*V2\nv_1 = v_2 * (A_2/A_1)\n\n# Using bernoulli's equation: p1 + 0.5*rho*v1^2 = p2 + 0.5*rho*v2^2 \n# Manipulated equation: p1 = p2 + 0.5*rho*(v2^2 - v1^2)\np_1 = p_2 + 0.5 * rho * (v_2**2 - v_1**2)\n\nprint('Pressure required at reservoir:',p_1,'N/m^2')\n        ",
        "explanation": "Since it is given that the scenario occurs in a low-speed subsonic wind tunnel, the fluid can be considered incompressible, and the continuity equation can be simplified to remove the density. The velocity required at the reservoir to achieve the desired flow velocity in the test-section can be calculated first using continuity equation. Next, Bernoulli's equation can be used across a streamline since the fluid is incomrpessible. Both velocities and the pressure at the test-section are known, and the pressure at the reservoir can be hence calculated.",
        "reference": "Anderson, J. D., Jr. (2015). Introduction to flight. McGraw-Hill Education. Example 4.21"
    },
    {
        "question": "What does the aera-velocity equation tell us about the change in flow velocity with changing area at different mach numbers?",
        "answer": "If the flow is subsonic (M < 1), for the velocity to increase, the area must decrease, like a converging nozzle. However, if the flow is supersonic (M > 1), for the velocity to increase, the area must increase, like a diverging diffuser.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "A piston–cylinder assembly contains a fixed mass of air. The air undergoes a finite process from state 1 to state 2. The piston moves such that the final volume of the air is several times larger than the initial volume. The process occurs at constant temperature. Describe what happens to the pressure and internal energy of the system, and if heat is added or removed to the system.",
        "answer": "Since the process occurs at constant temperature, we can conclude that the gas undergoes an isothermal process. In an isothermal process, the internal energy of the gas remains constant (delta U = 0) because the temperature does not change. This implies that the heat added to the gas (Q) is equal to the work done by the gas (W). In an expansion process, the work done by the gas is negative (W < 0) because the gas is doing work on the surroundings. Therefore, the heat added to the gas is negative as well, meaning heat is removed from the gas. As a result, the pressure of the system decreases as the gas expands and the volume increases.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "A pitot inserted in an airflow where static pressure = 1 atm measures measures a pressure = 2.714 atm. Is the flow supersonic or subsonic, and what is the Mach number of the flow?",
        "answer": "Firstly, we must determine if the flow is subsonic or supersonic. At Mach 1, P / P_0 = 0.528, and 1/2.714 = 0.36845 is LESS than 0.528, hence the flow is supersonic. This means the pitot tube is measuring the total pressure AFTER a shock wave, and using the gas properties table, P_0s / P = 2.714 corresponds to a Mach number of approximately 1.3",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the differences between stagnation pressure, static pressure, and dynamic pressure?",
        "answer": "Stagnation pressure, also known as total pressure, includes both the pressure due to the fluid's velocity (dynamic pressure) and the pressure exerted by the fluid molecules (static pressure). Stagnation pressure is the pressure that would be measured by a pitot tube facing directly into the flow, where the fluid is brought to zero speed by a steady isentropic process with no external work done. Static pressure is the pressure exerted by a fluid on a surface when the fluid is not in motion relative to the surface. Dynamic pressure is the pressure difference between the stagnation pressure and the static pressure, and it is the pressure that is used to calculate airspeed.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the magnus effect?",
        "answer": "The Magnus effect is a phenomenon where a spinning object experiences a sideways force perpendicular to both the direction of the fluid flow and the axis of rotation. The rotation of the object creates a difference in velocity between the fluid on one side of the object and the fluid on the other side. The fluid on the side moving in the same direction as the spin travels faster relative to the object, while the fluid on the opposite side moves slower. This velocity difference results in a pressure difference between the two sides of the object, and hence a sideways force.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the coanda effect?",
        "answer": "The Coanda effect describes the tendency of a fluid jet to adhere to and flow along a nearby surface, rather than detaching and flowing freely. When a fluid flows over a surface, it creates a thin layer of slow-moving fluid molecules close to the surface called the boundary layer. The boundary layer has lower velocity due to friction and lower pressure compared to the faster-moving fluid outside the boundary layer. As a result, the higher-pressure fluid outside the boundary layer pushes the jet towards the surface, causing it to adhere to and follow the contour of the surface.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "What are the assumptions made in using Bernoulli's equation?",
        "answer": "To apply Bernoulli's equation, the flow must be steady, incompressible, and inviscid (no friction by viscous forces). While no flow is really incompressible, flows with M<0.3 can be treated as incompressible, as the end result is usually within 5% compared to treating the M<0.3 flow as compressible.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "What happens to a shock wave when a supersonic stream encounters a physical object with an angle greater than the maximum deflection angle?",
        "answer": "If the phsyical geometry is such that the angle is greater than the maximum deflection angle, then no solution exists for a straight oblique shock wave. Instead, nature establishes a curved shock wave, detached from the corner or the nose of a body. This is also what causes a bow-wave to be observed in front of pitot-tubes in certain conditions.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why are expansion fans considered isentropic?",
        "answer": "Expansion fans typically occur adiabatically, meaning there is no heat transfer between the fluid and its surroundings during the expansion. There is usually no external work being done on or by the fluid. The expansion occurs due to a decrease in pressure or an increase in volume without any external force acting on the fluid. Without external work being done, the energy of the fluid remains constant, preserving the isentropic condition when we assume they are frictionless and reversible. ",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Define 'volumetric flow rate', and how it relates to continuity.",
        "answer": "Volumetric flow rate (Q) is a measure of how much volume of a fluid flows in a given interval of time, defined as Q = A*v, in the units of meters-cubed/second. Assuming constant density and incompressible flow, we can state that Q-dot_in equals Q-dot_out.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why can Bernoulli's principle not be used across shocks?",
        "answer": "Shocks are small regions in flow which contain near-instantaneous increases in static pressure, static temperature, and density, and cause pressure downstream of the shock to be less than pressure upstream. Shocks represent highly irreversible processes, as well as being compressible, thus violating some of the initial assumptions of Bernoulli's principle.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Explain the main mechanism through which Archimede's principle works.",
        "answer": "Archimede's principle states that a body submerged in a fluid will undergo a 'buoyant force' equal to the weight of the displaced fluid. When the object is submerged, the pressure forces due to the deeper fluid are higher than the pressure due to the shallower fluid. This pressure differential is the driving mechanism of Archimede's principle",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Explain why in a simple compressive system, if the fluid undergoes expansion but is unrestrained and adiabatic, the process is also isothermal.",
        "answer": "We can understand why this is by examining the Q-W=dU equation. When an expansion is unrestrained, there is zero p*dV work, and we assume no other work (stirring) because it is a simple compressive system. When we say a system is adiabatic, this means that the Q term = 0. Therefore, Q-W=dU becomes 0-0=dU=0 where dU=m*c_v*dT=0, thus dT=0 and the system is, by definition, isothermal.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Elaborate on how we can relate mass-flow rates in a steady-flow process.",
        "answer": "Steady-flow processes assume that the total mass within a control volume stays the same. We can derive an expression from this assumption which states the sum of mass-flow into the CV is equal to the sum of the mass-flow out of the CV. This is very useful for understanding the mass-flow rates of simple steady processes.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "What mechanisms cause the Magnus Effect, and how does it work?",
        "answer": "The Magnus Effect can be understood by imagining a ball spinning through fluid flow travelling perpendicular to the ball's axis of rotation. On either side of the ball, friction between the fluid and the ball imparts some momentum, relating to the direction of rotation. This causes fluid on one side of the ball to slow down, and on the other side to speed up. This change in velocity causes an inverse change in pressure (through Bernoulli's principle), and the resultant pressure differential generates a lift, or 'Magnus Force'.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why does flow tend to adhere to curved surfaces?",
        "answer": "This can be attributed to the 'Coandă Effect', which is where flow 'attaches' to a curved/cylindrical surface before later detaching. This behavior is complex, but can primarily be attributed to the relatively lower pressure formed close to the curved surface. The pressure gradient formed between the higher ambient pressure and lower pressure causes the flow to adhere to the curved surface.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Describe choked flow and its effects on a system.",
        "answer": "Choked flow is the condition in which a fluid passing through a conduit is unable to increase the mass flow rate (m-dot) by decreasing the static pressure at the exit. This typically occurs once the inlet/exit pressure ratio reaches a point at which the fluid flow reaches Mach 1 or sonic conditions. A further decrease of the exit pressure will increase the Mach number at the exit.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Describe Poiseuille Flow and the resultant shape of the flow.",
        "answer": "Poiseuille flow is the viscous flow of a fluid travelling between two plates. As a result of shear the fluid has less velocity closer to the plates. This forms a gradient where velocity is highest in the center, and lowest where the fluid contacts a plate.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "A water tank has an area of 5 m^2 and a height of 4m. It contains 3m of water (1000 kg/m^3) in height and is contaminated such that 10% of its total height is oil (850 kg/m^3), which floats on top of the water. What is the pressure at the bottom of the tank in kilopascals? (Assume atmospheric pressure = 1 atm)",
        "answer": "\n        #Values\n        heightTotal = 4\n        heightWater = 3\n        heightOil = heightTotal * 0.1\n        densityWater = 1000\n        densityOil = 850\n        atmosphericPressureAtm = 1\n        gravityConstant = 9.81\n\n        atmosphericPressurePa = atmosphericPressureAtm * 101325 #Conversion factor from atm to Pa\n        pressureFromWater = densityWater * gravityConstant * heightWater #rho * g * h\n        pressureFromOil = densityOil * gravityConstant * heightOil #rho * g * h\n\n        totalPressure = (atmosphericPressurePa + pressureFromWater + pressureFromOil)/1000\n        print(totalPressure, 'kilopascals')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the total pressure at the bottom of a tank, using the rho * g * h equations, as well as converting atmospheric pressure into Pascals.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "A test pilot is flying an experimental plane with two redundant pitot-static probe air-speed measurement systems. A discrepancy between the two probes causes the digital air speed gauge to read 'ERROR', and read out the raw values from the two probes. Probe one reads a stagnation pressure of 104,529 N/m^2 and a static pressure of 71,439 N/m^2. Probe two reads a stagnation pressure of 102,928 N/m^2 and a static pressure of 94,582 N/m^2. A callout from the traffic control tower tells the pilot that he is travelling at an air-speed of 225 knots. Determine which probe is faulty, assuming air has a density of 1.25 kg/m^3.",
        "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n\n        #Constants\n        rho = 1.25\n        measuredAirspeed = 225\n        p1Stag = 104529\n        p1Stat = 71439\n        p2Stag = 102928\n        p2Stat = 94582\n\n        #Derive airspeed equations then convert to knots from m/s (1.94384 conversion factor)\n        p1Airspeed = (np.sqrt((2*(p1Stag-p1Stat))/(rho)))*1.94384\n        p2Airspeed = (np.sqrt((2*(p2Stag-p2Stat))/(rho)))*1.94384\n\n        #Find which probe is closest to the ATC-recorded airspeed\n        if(np.abs(p1Airspeed-measuredAirspeed)>np.abs(p2Airspeed-measuredAirspeed)):\n            print('Pitot Probe 1 is faulty.')\n            print('Pitot Probe 2 is reading:', np.round(p2Airspeed,2), 'knots')\n        else:\n            print('Pitot Probe 2 is faulty.')\n            print('Pitot Probe 1 is reading:', np.round(p1Airspeed,2), 'knots')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the measured airspeed of both pitot-static probes, converts it into knots, and then compares to see which probe is closest to the ATC recorded airspeed.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "A tank of water is filled by an inlet with A_inlet=0.5m^2, at a volumetric flow rate of 1m^3/min. The tank is very large, but has weak supports, only able to support 12,500 kg of water. Assuming constant water density of 1000 kg/m^3, find at what time the total water mass reaches 90% of the support capacity, then graph the mass over time.",
        "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n        import matplotlib.pyplot as plt\n\n        maxWeight = 12500 #in kilograms\n        safeWeight = maxWeight * 0.9 #kg\n        density = 1000 #kg/m^3\n        inletArea=0.5 #m^2\n        volFlow = 1 #m^3/min\n\n        #Convert volumetric flow into SI units\n        volFlow = volFlow/60 #m^3/s\n\n        #Solve for mass-flow rate (m-dot = Q * rho), and time to fill to 90% capacity\n        mDot = volFlow * density #kg/s\n        timeToFill = safeWeight/mDot\n\n        #Generate Results\n        x_values = np.linspace(0, np.round(timeToFill), 25)\n        y_values = mDot*x_values\n\n        #Results and Plot\n        print('Time to fill to 90% load-capacity:', timeToFill, 'seconds.')\n\n        plt.plot(x_values, y_values, marker='o', linestyle='-')\n        plt.title('Plot of container mass-load')\n        plt.xlabel('Time (seconds)')\n        plt.ylabel('Mass of Water')\n        plt.grid(True)\n        plt.show()\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code converts the given values to SI units, finds the mass-flow rate, then charts and prints both the water mass over time and the time taken to fill to 90% load-capacity.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Given a pipe with an internal diameter of 6 inches, determine the length of pipe required to drop the pressure of the viscous fluid by 250 pascals. Assume viscosity (mu) = 0.00275 kg/(m*s) and the bulk velocity is 20 ft/s.",
        "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n\n        #Conversion of imperial units to SI\n        diameterImperial = 6\n        diameterMetric = diameterImperial / (3.281*12) #(meters) - Conversion factor from feet - meters = 1/3.281\n        radius = diameterMetric / 2 #(meters)\n        velocityImperial = 20\n        velocityMetric = velocityImperial / 3.281 #(meters/s)\n\n        #Constants\n        desiredPressureDrop = 250\n        viscosity = 0.00275\n\n        #Rearranged Hagen-Poiseuille Equation to solve for L\n        desiredLength = (desiredPressureDrop*(np.square(radius)))/(8*viscosity*velocityMetric)\n        print('The length of the pipe required to drop pressure by 250 Pa given these conditions is:', desiredLength, 'meters.')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code converts the given values to SI units, then solves for desired length in meters by rearranging the Hagen-Poiseuille equation for viscous flow.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "A climate control computer maintains the temperature inside of an Arctic research base. It does so by controlling a reversible cyclic heat pump which takes in heat from a geothermal heat source at 367 degrees Kelvin and the cold outdoors at 233 degrees Kelvin, rejecting heat to the interior of the base. If the pump extracts heat from the geothermal source at 1.35 kW and from the cold outdoors at a variable rate, plot the temperature the pump rejects to the base depending on that rate, and find the rate ideal for an output temperature of 300 degrees Kelvin.",
        "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n        import matplotlib.pyplot as plt\n\n        #Constants\n        geoTemp = 367 #Kelvin\n        coldTemp = 233 #Kelvin\n        geoRate = 1350 #Watts\n        maxRate = 2500-geoRate #Maximum output rate limit\n\n        #Testing Rates\n        coldRate = np.linspace(0,maxRate,100)\n        #Base output temperature, using the Clausius inequality, assuming reversible pump\n        baseTemp = ((geoTemp*coldTemp*geoRate)+(geoTemp*coldTemp*coldRate))/((geoRate*coldTemp)+(coldRate*geoTemp))\n\n        #Plot baseTemp vs coldRate\n        plt.plot(coldRate, baseTemp, marker='o', linestyle='-')\n        plt.title('Plot of base output temperature based on heat extraction rate from cold outdoors')\n        plt.xlabel('Cold extraction rate (Watts)')\n        plt.ylabel('Output Temperature (Kelvin)')\n        plt.grid(True)\n        plt.show()\n\n        #Find closest value and print\n        closestValue = 999999\n        closestIndex = -1\n        for i, value in enumerate(baseTemp):\n            if np.abs(value-300) < closestValue:\n                closestValue = np.abs(value-300)\n                closestIndex = i\n        if closestIndex != -1:\n            print('The control computer should set the outdoor heat extraction rate to', np.round(coldRate[closestIndex],2) , 'Watts.')\n        else:\n            print('Something has gone wrong. The result could not be calculated.')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code first finds the range of extraction rates to test given the restrictions of the question. It then creates an array of rates using linspace, then tests each of those arrays in a rearranged version of the Clausius Inequality, solving for output temperature assuming a reversible pump. It then plots the rates vs. output temperature, and then performs a simple check to find the ideal rate for a 300 degree Kelvin output temperature.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "The United States Navy is testing an experimental boat. The boat has a rectangular profile of 4 meters by 3 meters, and is 6 meters tall. If 40% of the boat's height sinks into water (assuming water density of 1000kg/m^3), calculate the upward buoyant force on the boat.",
        "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n        #Physical characteristics\n        waterDensity = 1000 #kg/m^3\n        gravityConstant = 9.81 #m/s^2\n        #Boat characteristics\n        length = 4 #m\n        width = 3 #m\n        height = 6 #m\n\n        #Calculations\n        submergedHeight = 6*0.4\n        submergedVolume = length * width * submergedHeight #m^3\n        buoyantForce = submergedVolume * waterDensity * gravityConstant\n\n        #Result\n        print('The upward buoyant force on the boat is: ', np.round((buoyantForce/1000),2), 'kilonewtons.')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the total submerged volume of the experimental boat. It then multiples the submerged volume with the density of water and the gravitational constant, all in SI units. This calculates the upward buoyant force on the boat given by Archimede's Principle.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Farmer John has a irrigation control system connected to his large rainwater tank. Currently, the rain (density 1000kg/m^3) is filling his empty tank at a rate of 0.0175 m^3/s, where the tank has a total volume of 200m^3. The tank has a small circular outlet pipe with a 10cm diameter, and the irrigation control system measures that the outlet water exit velocity is 0.2 m/s. If the rain is going to stop in 5 hours, determine whether or not John's tank will overflow, and chart the mass of the water in the tank.",
        "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n        import matplotlib.pyplot as plt\n\n        #Constants\n        density = 1000 #kg/m^3\n        tankVolume = 200 #m^3\n        Q_in = 0.0175 #m^3/s\n        outDiameter = 10 #cm\n        outVelocity = 0.2 #m/s\n        timeUntilClearSkies = 5*3600 #seconds\n\n        #Calculations\n        Q_out = (np.square((10/100)/2)*np.pi*outVelocity)\n        Q_net = Q_in - Q_out #m^3/s\n\n        #Graphing\n        time = np.linspace(0,timeUntilClearSkies,100)\n        volume = Q_net * time\n        mass = volume * density\n        plt.plot(time, mass, linestyle='-')\n        plt.plot([0,timeUntilClearSkies], [tankVolume*density,tankVolume*density], color='red') #Graph overflow line (in mass)\n        plt.title('Plot of time vs volume in tank.')\n        plt.xlabel('Time (seconds)')\n        plt.ylabel('Theoretical Tank Water Mass (kg)')\n        plt.grid(True)\n        plt.show()\n\n        #Print results\n        if(np.max(volume) > tankVolume):\n            print('Farmer John's tank has been flooded past its 200 m^3 capacity.')\n        else:\n            print('Farmer John's tank did not overflow.')\n        ",
        "explanation": "This code first calculates the net volumetric flow rate into the tank, by first finding the volumetric flow rate out of the outlet pipe, and subtracting that from the rate going in. It then graphs the mass of water in the tank against time, then outputs the result of whether John's tank will overflow or not. ",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Can you explain the components of a closed supersonic wind tunnel and the components of an open supersonic wind tunnel?",
        "answer": "A closed supersonic wind tunnel is one in which the flow is recycled, returned, or looped through the wind tunnel. An open wind tunnel is one in which air is pulled through a vacuum on one side and exits through a vacuum pump on the opposite side. Thus, the air is never reused or returned through the tunnel. In an open wind tunnel, there is a pump that drives air into a high pressure tank at the beginning of the wind tunnel. This subsonic air then flows from the high pressure tank to the nozzle. Through the converging section of the nozzle, it speeds up until it chokes, reaching Mach 1 at the throat of the nozzle. Then, it flows through the diverging section of the nozzle, accelerating to supersonic speeds, until it reaches the test, or working section, where the area stops changing and the flow speed remains constant. The test section is where the flow conditions are designed to be steady, so the user can test their designs in a controlled environment. Then, the air goes through a converging-diverging nozzle again at the end of the tunnel. This time however the converging nozzle slows down the supersonic flow, so it once again is choked at the throat, and the flow continues to slow down as it goes through the diverging section. The flow also undergoes a series of shocks in this part of the tunnel. Finally, the flow exits the tunnel through a vacuum pump that pulls air out of the tunnel. In a closed wind tunnel, the process is similar; however, the air isn’t driven by a vacuum entrance and exit. Instead, it is looped through the tunnel. Typically, there are five important parts of a closed-circuit supersonic wind tunnel. There is the compressor, heat exchanger, nozzle, working section, and the diffuser. The flow starts by going through the nozzle. The subsonic flow speeds up in the converging section, chokes, and then continues to accelerate to supersonic speeds in the diverging section. Then, it enters the working section. In the working section, the area is constant, so the flow speed does not change. The working section is used to test models. Then, the flow enters the diffuser, which has a converging area that slows down the supersonic flow. In the diffuser, the flow experiences shocks and as a result the stagnation pressure drops. To raise the stagnation pressure back to the ideal pressure, the now subsonic flow continues through the tunnel to a compressor. The compressor does shaft work on the flow, so the pressure rises. However, the temperature also rises isentropically as shaft work is added to flow. Because of this temperature rise, a heat exchanger is added later in the tunnel before the flow returns to the nozzle to take heat out of the air to maintain a steady temperature. Then, the air reaches the nozzle, and the process begins again.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Can you explain Bernoulli's equation and its applications in fluid mechanics?",
        "answer": "Bernoulli's equation describes the relationship between static pressure, velocity, and elevation in a flowing fluid. It was formulated by Daniel Bernoulli in the 18th century. The equation states that for steady, inviscid, incompressible fluids flowing along streamlines P + 1/2*rho*V^2 + rho*g*h = constant, where P is pressure, rho is density, V is velocity, g is the gravitational constant, and h is elevation. This equation can be used to determine how the velocity, elevation, or pressure change along a streamline as a result of changes in the other two variables. For example, if you measure the velocity of a flow at two points along a streamline, you can determine the change in pressure from point A to point B. However, this can only be applied along steady, inviscid, incompressible streamlines. This can be useful for pitot-static tubes, which are used to measure the pressure and velocity of the flow around an airplane, lift across airfoils, and flows through frictionless pipes. You cannot apply Bernoulli's equation across streamlines; you can only apply it along streamlines.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "What is a pitot-static tube?",
        "answer": "A pitot-static tube is a device used to measure the static and stagnation pressure at a point. These devices are commonly used on aircraft to determine the static pressure, and the velocity of the airflow. The pitot-static tube works by having two openings; one faces the flow and the other is perpendicular to the flow velocity. The pitot tube that faces the flow has a stagnation point, so the local velocity is 0; therefore, the static pressure that the tube records is the stagnation pressure of the fluid. The other pressure taps experience a local velocity equal to the flow velocity, so the static pressure they record is the static pressure of the flow. Using Bernoulli's equation, these two measurements can be used to find the velocity of the flow. Po = p + 1/2*rho*v^2. Since the pitot-static tube recorded the static pressure and the stagnation pressure, the static pressure can be subtracted from the stagnation pressure to find the dynamic pressure. Then we can set the dynamic pressure equal to 1/2*rho*v^2 and solve for v to find the velocity of the flow.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Explain the Steady Flow Energy Equation.",
        "answer": "The Steady Flow Energy Equation (SFEE) is a consequence of the first law of Thermodynamics, Q - W = 𝚫U. It describes the conservation of energy for a steady flow process in an open system, such as a fluid flowing through a pipe or a turbine. Mathematically, it is expressed as: dQ/dt + dW/dt + dm/dt*(h + v^2/2 + gz)in = dm/dt*(h + v^2/2 + gz)out, where dQ/dt is the rate of heat transfer, dW/dt is the rate of shaft work, dm/dt is the mass flow rate, h is the specific enthalpy, v is the velocity, g is the gravitational constant, and z is the elevation. The terms in the equation represent different forms of energy per unit mass: h represents the enthalpy of the fluid, which is the sum of its internal energy and the product of pressure and specific volume, 1/2*v^2 represents the kinetic energy per unit mass of the fluid, and gz represents the potential energy per unit mass of the fluid due to its elevation. The steady flow energy equation states that the total energy per unit mass entering a control volume (inlet) is equal to the total energy per unit mass leaving the control volume (outlet), accounting for any heat transfer and work done on or by the system. The steady flow energy equation can only be used for flows that are steady, meaning they don't change over time. Thus, we don't account for a change in internal energy. To solve problems using the SFEE, find the initial specific enthalpy, velocity, and specific potential energy and then find the ending specific enthalpy, velocity, and specific potential energy. Then, find the mass flow rate. Using these quantities, you can work out the required heat and work inputs. Often, the effects of velocity and potential energy will be ignored because they are insignificant compared to the effects of the change in enthalpy.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Explain the three conservation equations (mass, momentum, and energy)",
        "answer": "The three conservation equations—mass conservation, momentum conservation, and energy conservation—are fundamental principles in physics and engineering that describe the behavior of fluids and their interactions with their surroundings. The mass conservation equation, also known as the continuity equation, states that mass is conserved within a closed system or a control volume. This means the sum of the mass flow rates into and out of a control volume must be equal. Mathematically, it can be expressed as: Σdm/dt(in) = Σdm/dt(out), or Σrho1*v1*A1 = Σrho2*v2*A2 where rho1, v1, and A1 are the density, velocity, and area of the incoming flow and rho2, v2, and A2 are the density, velocity, and area of the outflowing flow. The conservation of momentum equation can best be expressed as Bernoulli’s equation in Euler’s form: p1 + rho1*v1^2 = p2 + rho2*v2^2 where p1 is the initial static pressure, rho1 is the initial density, and v1 is the initial velocity. This equation essentially states that momentum is conserved along a streamline and it can be used to relate the change in pressure to the change in velocity of fluid flows. This equation shows that the momentum of a system does not change when it is not acted upon by an outside force. The conservation of energy equation is the NSFEE energy equation. When the flow is steady and there is no heat or work input. This equation can be expressed as h1 + 1/2v2^2 + g*z1 = h2 + 1/2v2^2 + g*z2 where h is specific enthalpy, v is velocity, g is the gravitational constant, and z is the elevation. This equation shows that the energy of a system does not change when it is not acted upon by an outside force. These three equations together can be used to derive the normal shock equations and they form three fundamental laws for solving problems involving fluid flows.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Can you explain how to expel a shock from the nozzle?",
        "answer": "As you decrease the exit pressure of the flow from the nozzle, the shock moves further from the throat to the end of the nozzle. If you decrease the exit pressure enough, the shock can occur after the nozzle exit. Typically if the exit pressure is higher than ambient, the shock will occur within the nozzle, if the exit pressure is lower than ambient, there will be expansion fans at the nozzle end followed by shock further downstream, and if the flow is perfectly expanded, the shocks will be minimized.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Can you explain overexpanded vs underexpanded flow from nozzles?",
        "answer": "Overexpanded and underexpanded flow refer to the behavior of a fluid flow exiting a nozzle relative to the ambient conditions. In overexpanded flow, the pressure of the fluid leaving the nozzle is lower than the ambient pressure. This occurs when the exit pressure of the fluid is lower than the pressure of the surrounding environment. As a result, the flow expands further after exiting the nozzle, leading to a separation of the flow from the nozzle walls. This separation causes flow instability, shock waves, and decreased performance. Overexpanded flow is often associated with rocket nozzles operating at higher altitudes where ambient pressure is lower than at sea level. In underexpanded flow, the pressure of the fluid leaving the nozzle is higher than the ambient pressure. This occurs when the exit pressure is higher than the pressure of the surrounding environment. As a result, the flow does not fully expand to match the ambient pressure, leading to a supersonic flow at the nozzle exit. Underexpanded flow is characterized by shock waves forming at the nozzle exit, which can cause noise, vibration, and reduced efficiency. It is commonly observed in jet engine exhaust nozzles. In summary, overexpanded flow occurs when the exit pressure is too low relative to the ambient pressure, leading to flow separation and decreased performance, while underexpanded flow occurs when the exit pressure is too high relative to the ambient pressure, leading to shock waves and other issues. Both conditions can have detrimental effects on the performance and stability of the nozzle and the overall system. Perfectly expanded flow is when the exit pressure is equal to the ambient pressure. This allows for peak efficiency.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why is the zeroth law necessary?",
        "answer": "The zeroth law states, If two systems are each in thermal equilibrium with a third system, then they are in thermal equilibrium with each other. The zeroth law establishes a fundamental concept: temperature. The Zeroth Law establishes the concept of temperature and the ability to compare temperatures between different systems. It provides a basis for measuring and quantifying thermal equilibrium, which is essential for understanding heat transfer processes. The Zeroth Law is essential for analyzing heat transfer processes, such as conduction, convection, and radiation. It provides a basis for understanding the direction and magnitude of heat transfer between systems based on their temperature differences. In summary, while the Zeroth Law of Thermodynamics may seem simple, its necessity lies in its establishment of the fundamental concept of temperature and its role in defining thermodynamic equilibrium, enabling temperature measurement, and facilitating the analysis of heat transfer processes.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },  
    {
        "question": "How does the pressure change over a curved streamline?",
        "answer": "According to centripetal acceleration, we know that the acceleration of fluid moving around a curve is equal to the tangential velocity squared divided by the radius, a = -V^2/R. Further, we know that this acceleration must be driven by a pressure force, so we can say F = dp/dn*Volume. Additionally, F=ma can be re-written as F = rho*Volume*a. Therefore, combining these equations we get dp/dn*Volume = V^2/R*rho*Volume, or simplified, dp/dn = rho*V^2/R. Therefore, to find the pressure difference across curved streamlines, we can simply integrate dp = rho*V^2/R*dn from radius 1 to radius 2.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
       
    {
        "question": "Calculate the gauge pressure 12 m below the surface in a tank that has 10 m of water (density = 1000 kg/m^3) and 5 m of oil (density = 750 kg/m^3).",
        "answer": "\nclass Liquid:\n    def __init__(self, density, depth):\n        self.density = density\n        self.depth = depth\n\nliquid1 = Liquid(1000, 10)\nliquid2 = Liquid(750, 5)\nFluids = [liquid1, liquid2]\ndesired_depth = 12\npg = 0\ng = 9.81\nFluids = sorted(Fluids, key = lambda Liquid: Liquid.density)\n\nwhile desired_depth > 0:\n    for Fluid in Fluids:\n        if Fluid.depth <= desired_depth:\n            pg = pg + Fluid.depth*g*Fluid.density\n            desired_depth = desired_depth - Fluid.depth\n        else:\n            pg = pg + desired_depth*g*Fluid.density\n            desired_depth = desired_depth - desired_depth\n\nprint('The gauge pressure is', pg, 'Pa')\n            ",
        "explanation": "This solution takes advantage of the fact that hydrostatic pressure due to a fluid is equal to the density of the fluid times the acceleration due to gravity times the depth of the fluid. To find the pressure at a depth in a fluid we simply find the weight of the fluid above it per area. In this case, at a depth of 12 meters, we have 5 meters of oil and 7 meters of water. Therefore, p = rhowater*depthwater*g + rhooil*depthoil*g = 1000*7*9.81 + 750*5*9.81 = 105457.5 Pa.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Calculate the momentum flux of a fluid moving through a cylinder of radius R, with a velocity profile v(r) = Vo(1-(r/R)^2) where R = 1 m, density = 1000 kg/m^3, and Vo = 10 m/s.",
        "answer": "\nimport math\n\nR = 1\nrho = 1000\nVo = 10\n\nflux = math.pi/3*rho*(Vo**2)*R**2\n\nprint('The momentum flux is', flux, 'kg*m/s^2')\n\n            ",
        "explanation": "Momentum flux is equal to the integral of density times velocity squared times the area. In this case we can write v(r) = Vo(1-(r/R)^2) and da = 2*pi*r*dr and rho = 1000 kg/m^3 where Vo = 10 m/s and R = 1m. Solving the integral from r=0 to r=R of (Vo(1-(r/R)^2))^2*rho*2*pi*r*dr, we get pi/3*rho*Vo^2*R^2 = pi/3*1000*10^2*1 = 104.72 kN.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "An engine takes heat from a thermal reservoir at a rate of 2 kW at 102 degrees Celsius and from a cold place at 12 degrees Celsius and rejects heat to the environment at 30 degrees Celsius. Determine the minimum rate of heat transfer from the cold space.",
        "answer": "\nQ1 = 2\nT1 = 102\nT2 = 12\nT3 = 30\n\nT1 = T1 + 273.15\nT2 = T2 + 273.15\nT3 = T3 + 273.15\n\nQ2 = (T3*T2)/(T2-T3) * (Q1/T1 - Q1/T3)\n\nprint('The minimum rate of heat transfer from the cold place is ', Q2, ' kW')\n\n            ",
        "explanation": "In order to solve problems involving heat transfer in 3 body systems, we can use Clausius inequality and conservation of energy. First by conservation of energy we know that Q1 + Q2 + Q3 = 0. Therefore we can say that Q3 = -(Q1 + Q2). Next, the Clausius inequality tells us that Q1/T1 + Q2/T2 + Q3/T3 <= 0. Substituting for Q3, we get Q1/T1 + Q2/T2 -(Q1 + Q2)/T3 <=0. Substituting Q1 = 2 kW, T1 = 375.15 K, T2 = 285.15 K, T3 = 303.15 K, the maximum Q2 is 6.08 kW.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Air flows steadily through a converging-diverging nozzle. The area at the throat of the nozzle (where the flow is choked) is 1/2 the inlet area. Determine the Mach number at the inlet of the nozzle. Plot the Mach number as the area changes from inlet to throat.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy\nimport matplotlib.pyplot as pl\n\nM2 = 1\n\nMs = []\nfor i in range(1, 101):\n    Ms.append(i/100)\n\n#I ran a linear regression to find non-dimensional mass flow rate as a function of Mach Number. The result was the polynomial ndm(M) = 6.53763187e-01(M^4) + -1.64823282e+00(M^3) + 6.70739635e-02(M^2) + 2.20868819e+00(M) + 6.33202794e-05\ndef M2Ndm(M):\n    return 6.53763187e-01*M**4 + -1.64823282e+00*M**3 + 6.70739635e-02*M**2 + 2.20868819e+00*M + 6.33202794e-05\n\nndms = []\nfor M in Ms:\n    ndms.append(M2Ndm(M))\n\nndm2 = M2Ndm(M2)\nAratio = .5\n\nndm1 = ndm2*Aratio\n\narr = numpy.polyfit(ndms, Ms, 7)\ndef Ndm2M(ndm):\n    return arr[0]*ndm**7 + arr[1]*ndm**6 + arr[2]*ndm**5 + arr[3]*ndm**4 + arr[4]*ndm**3 + arr[5]*ndm**2 + arr[6]*ndm + arr[7]\n\nM1 = Ndm2M(ndm1)\n\nprint('The input Mach number at the inlet is', M1)\n\nfig, ax = pl.subplots()\nAs = []\nA2 = 1\nrelndms = []\nfor ndm in ndms:\n    if ndm > ndm1:\n    relndms.append(ndm)\n\nrelMs = []\nfor M in Ms:\n    if M > M1:\n    relMs.append(M)\n\nfor ndm in relndms:\n    As.append(ndm2/ndm*A2)\n\nax.plot(As, relMs)\nax.set_xlabel('Area Ratio')\nax.set_ylabel('Mach Number')\nax.set_title('Mach Number vs Area Ratio')\nax.text(As[0],M1,'inlet')\nax.text(1,M2,'throat')\n\n            ",
        "explanation": "To solve this problem, we use the gas flow properties tables. First, we use the table to find the non-dimensional mass flow rate at the throat where we know the mach number is 1. Looking at the table, we see that the non-dimensional mass flow rate is 1.2810 when the Mach number is 1. In this code, I use a regression fit model to find mach number from non-dimensional mass flow rate and vice versa created from the data in the table. Then we use the area ratio from throat to inlet to find the non-dimensional mass flow rate at the inlet. We know that the stagnation pressure is constant in the converging section of the nozzle and Cp, To, and mdot are constant as well, therefore we can take mdot*sqrt(Cp*To)/(Athroat*Po) = 1.2810 and multiply by Athroat/Ainlet to find the non-dimensional mass flow rate at the inlet. 1.2810 * 1/2 = .6405, so the non-dimensional mass flow rate at the inlet is .6405. Looking at the table, the corresponding mach number is around .304. I also included a plot to show how the mach number changes as the area changes from throat to inlet.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Air driven by a fan flows through a frictionless pipe from station A to station B. After reaching station B, the air flows through a curved section of pipe with an inner radius of 5 m and outer radius of 10 m. At station A, the velocity is 20 m/s and the pressure is 20 Pa. At station B, the velocity is 15 m/s. Assuming the air enters the curved section with uniform velocity and pressure, what is the pressure of the air on the outside of the curve as the air exits the bend? The density of air is 1.225 kg/m^3.",
        "answer": "\nimport math\n\nv1 = 20\np1 = 20\nv2 = 15\nrho = 1.225\nR2 = 10\nR1 = 5\n\np2 = p1 + .5*rho*(v1**2 - v2**2)\n\ndeltaP = rho*(v2**2)*math.log(R2/R1)\n\nfinal_pressure = p2 + deltaP\n\nprint('the pressure is', final_pressure, 'Pa')\n\n            ",
        "explanation": "To solve this problem we first find the pressure at station B using Bernoulli's equation and then we use the equation to find the change in pressure across curved streamlines. Bernoulli's equation tells us that p1 + 1/2*rho*v1^2 = p2 + 1/2*rho*v2^2 where p1 and v1 are the pressure and velocity at station A and p2 and v2 are the pressure and velocity at station B. Solving this for p2 with the values given v1 = 20 m/s, p1 = 20 Pa, rho = 1.225 kg/m^3, and v2 = 15 m/3, we find that p2 = 127 Pa. Next we find the pressure change across the curved section of the tube. To do this, we use the equation dp/dn = p*V^2/R and we integrate p*V^2/(R+n)dn to find the change in pressure from the inside to the outside of the curve. Then, we add this change in pressure to the pressure at station B, to find the pressure on the outside of the curve. This change is approximately 191 Pa, so the pressure on the outside of the curve is around 318 Pa.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "A piston-cylinder device contains 0.5 kg of air at an initial pressure of 200 kPa and a volume of 0.1 m^3. The air undergoes an isothermal compression process to a final volume of 0.05 m^3. Calculate the final pressure of the air if the temperature remains constant at 300 K. Plot the pressure vs volume diagram for this process.",
        "answer": "\nimport matplotlib.pyplot as pl\n\np1 = 200\nv1 = .1\nv2 = .05\n\np2 = (p1*v1)/v2\n\nprint('The final pressure is', p2, 'kPa')\n\nvs = []\nps = []\nvi = v1*1000\nvf = v2*1000\nfor v in range(int(vi),int(vf)):\n    v = v/1000\n    vs.append(v)\n    p = p1*v1/v\n    ps.append(p)\n\nfig, ax = pl.subplots()\nax.plot(ps, vs)\nax.set_xlabel('pressure')\nax.set_ylabel('volume')\nax.set_title('pressure vs volume')\nax.text(p1,v1,'A')\nax.text(p2,v2,'B')\n\n            ",
        "explanation": "This solution relies on the ideal gas law, PV = nRT. Because temperature in this process is constant, R is constant, and the amount of gas is constant, nRT is constant. Therefore, p1v1 = p2v2 because p1v1 = nRT and p2v2 = nRT. Substituting v1 = .1 m^3 and p1 = 200 kPa into the equation we find that pv = 20 kPa*m^3 for the duration of the process. We can plot p = 20/v from vi = .1 m^3 to vf = .05 m^3 to give a pressure vs volume diagram for this process. At vf = .05 m^3, p = 20/.05 = 400 kPa.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Air is flowing across steady, incompressible, streamlines. The pressure measured at station A is 200 kPa, and the pressure measured at station B is 100 kPa. Calculate the change in specific kinetic energy from station A to B.",
        "answer": "\n            p1 = 200\n            p2 = 100\n\n            KEChange = p1 - p2\n\n            print('The change in specific KE from station A to station B is', KEChange, 'kJ/m^3')\n            ",
        "explanation": "This solution uses Bernoulli's Equation, p1 + 1/2*rho*v1^2 = p2 + 1/2*rho*v2^2. Rearranging, we find that p1 - p2 = 1/2*rho(v2^2 - v1^2). Recognizing that 1/2*rho*(v2^2-v1^2) = the change in specific KE, we recognize that the change is equal to the pressure at station A, p1, minus the pressure at station B, p2. In this case, the change in specific KE is 200 kPa - 100 kPa = 100 kJ/m^3.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Give an example of a control volume.",
        "answer": "A secured tunnel with the same amount of mass going in as out. mass flux(in) = mass flux(out).",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "What causes shocks?",
        "answer": "When an object moves faster than the speed of sound, objects that react to changes in pressure can't, thereofre creating a build up of pressure and thus shocks.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Can Bernoulli’s principle hold across a shock wave explain your reasoning?",
        "answer": "No, Bernoulli's principle can only hold for incompressible flow. The total pressure decreases downstream of a shock.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Explain the outcome difference in a concave corner versus a convex corner for a mach wave.",
        "answer": "A concave corner will result in a oblique shock while a convex croner will lead to an expansion fan.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "In a pipe with a constriction causing velocity to increase, what happens to the pressure as the fluid moves from the wide section to the narrow section?",
        "answer": "The pressure decreases in the fluid flow from the wide section to the narrow section due to the increase in velocity.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "How does only backspin affect the trajectory of a golf ball for the magnus effect?",
        "answer": "Straight backspin on a golf ball generates lift, causing the ball to stay airborne longer and travel farther than a non-spinning ball.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "What type of flow occurs between two parallel plates when one plate is stationary and the other is moving horizontally?",
        "answer": "Couette flow, characterized by the shear stress and velocity gradients induced within the fluid.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "If heat is added to a closed system while no work is done and no heat is transferred out, what happens according to the first law of thermodynamics?",
        "answer": "The internal energy of the system increases leading to a rise in temperature within the system due to the added heat energy.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "When we talk about pressure in fluid mechanics, what's the difference between stagnation pressure and static pressure?",
        "answer": "Stagnation pressure is the total energy the fluid has considering both its resting pressure and the pressure it gains from its movement, while static pressure just looks at the pressure from the fluid sitting still.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "A glass of cola contains 4 inches or 0.1016m in height of cola. The bartender adds whiskey to the cup adding another inch to the height or 0.0254m. Calculate the gauge pressure at the bottom of the cup. Given cola density(1042 kg/m^3); whiskey density(1010 kg/m^3).",
        "answer": "\n  import numpy as np\n\nh_cola = 0.1016 #meters\nh_whiskey = 0.0253 #meters\ndensity_cola = 1.042 #kg/m^3\ndensity_whiskey = 1.01 #kg/m^3\ngravity = 9.98 #m/s^2\n\n#calculate the gauge pressure very simple\ngauge_presure = density_whiskey*gravity*h_whiskey + density_cola*gravity*h_cola #answer in Pa\n\n  \n  print('Gauge Pressure at the bottom of the cup:', gauge_presure, 'Pa')\n            ",
        "explanation": "This question requires a simple calculation of gauge pressure using two different objects one being poured on top of inside a cup.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Given air flowing steadily through a pipe at a speed of 50 m/s, with a decrease in pressure of -10,000 Pa, and the density of air being 1.125 kg/m^3, find the pressure at this other point using Bernoulli's equation.",
        "answer": "\n  import numpy as np\n\nv_inf = 50  # Velocity at both points m/s\ndelta_p = -10000  # Decrease in pressure from point 1 to point 2 Pa\nrho = 1.25   # Density of the fluid kg/m^3\np_2 = 0.5 * rho * v_inf**2 + delta_p # Calculate the pressure at point 2 using Bernoulli's equation\n  \n    print('Pressure at point 2:', p_2, 'Pa')\n            ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates pressure at a 2nd point given the pressure decrease and constant velocity using Bernoulli's equation.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Nitrogen gas at a volume of 2m^3 exterst a pressure of 500kPa. Determine the temperature of this nitrogen using the ideal gas law.",
        "answer": "\n  import numpy as np\n\nV = 2  # Volume in m^3\nP = 500000  # Pressure in Pa (500 kPa converted to Pa)\nR = 8.314  # J/(mol*K)\nn = P * V / (R * 1000) #number of moles\nT = P * V / (n * R) # Calculate the temperature using the ideal gas law\n  \n    print('The temperature of the nitrogen gas is:', T, 'K')\n            ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates temperature using the ideal gas law not a very hard question.",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "Given the upstream temperature of 500 K pressure of 200 kPa and Mach number of 2; determine the downstream temperature, pressure, and Mach number.",
        "answer": "\n  import numpy as np\nT1 = 500  # Upstream temperature in K\nP1 = 200000  # Upstream pressure in Pa (200 kPa converted to Pa)\nM1 = 2  # Upstream Mach number\ngamma = 1.4  # Specific heat ratio for air\n\n# Calculate downstream temperature using the normal shock relations\nT2 = T1 * ((2 * gamma * M1**2 - (gamma - 1)) / (gamma + 1))\n\n# Calculate downstream pressure using the normal shock relations\nP2 = P1 * ((2 * gamma * M1**2 - (gamma - 1)) / (gamma + 1))**(gamma / (gamma - 1))\n\n# Calculate downstream Mach number using the normal shock relations\nM2 = ((gamma + 1) * M1**2) / (2 + (gamma - 1) * M1**2)\n  \n    print('Downstream Temperature (T2):', T2, 'K')\n    print('Downstream Pressure (P2):', P2, 'Pa')\n    print('Downstream Mach Number (M2):', M2)\n            ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the downstream properties given a normal shock using the simple relations.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Given the density of water as 1000 kg/m³, determine its exit speed from a pipe if 8 kg/s enters and the mass flux out equals the mass flux in. Assume the cross-sectional area of the exit is half that of the entrance.",
        "answer": "\n  import numpy as np\nrho = 1000  # Density of water in kg/m³\nm_flux_in = 8  # Mass flux entering in kg/s\nA_in = 1  # Cross-sectional area of the entrance in m²\nA_out = 0.5 * A_in  # Cross-sectional area of the exit in m²\nv_out = m_flux_in / (rho * A_out) # Calculate the exit speed using the mass flux equation\n  \n    print('The exit speed of the liquid is:', v_out, 'm/s')\n            ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates exit velocity considering a control volume and mass flux.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "A kilogram of air heats up from 500 K to 700 K in a closed container without changing volume. Its specific heat at constant volume of 1000 J/(kg·K). Calculate the change in entropy.",
        "answer": "\n  import numpy as np\nm = 1  # Mass of air in kg\nT1 = 500  # Initial temperature in K\nT2 = 700  # Final temperature in K\nCv = 1000  # Specific heat at constant volume in J/(kg*K)\ndelta_S = m * Cv * np.log(T2 / T1) # Calculate the change in entropy using the Clausius inequality\n\n    print('The change in entropy is:', delta_S, 'J/K')\n            ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates change in entropy using the clausius inequality.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "An aircraft flying at Mach 3 encounters an oblique shock wave with an angle of 45 deg. Determine the Mach number and the angle of the flow behind the shock wave.",
        "answer": "\n  import numpy as np\ngamma = 1.4\nM1 = 3  # Upstream Mach number\ntheta = np.deg2rad(45)  # Angle of oblique shock in radians\n# Calculate the Mach number behind the shock using the oblique shock relations\nM2 = np.sqrt((1 + ((gamma - 1) / 2) * M1**2) / (gamma * M1**2 - (gamma - 1) / 2 * (np.sin(theta))**2))\nM2 = np.round(M2, 2)  # Round off to 2 decimal places\n# Calculate the angle behind the shock using the oblique shock relations\nbeta = np.arcsin((1 / M1) * np.sin(theta - np.arcsin(1 / M1)))\nbeta_deg = np.rad2deg(beta) # Convert angle from radians to degrees\nbeta_deg = np.round(beta_deg, 2)  # Round off to 2 decimal places\n\n    print('Mach number behind the oblique shock:', M2)\n    print('Angle behind the oblique shock (in degrees):', beta_deg)\n            ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates angle and mach number due to an oblique shock.",
        "reference":""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why might different fluids at the same velocities have different mach numbers?",
        "answer": "Mach number is defined as M =  V/a where a is the spead of sound. As the speed of sound varies from fluid to fluid, mach number will also.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
    
    },
    {
        "question": "An engineer designs a pitot static port to have a diameter of 2mm, but it is manufactured to 4mm. What assumptions must be made so that both design and manufacturing will work the same?",
        "answer": "Inviscid, incompressible and steady flow.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill pg.226"
    },
    {
        "question": "Assuming incompressible flow, what's the airspeed of a plane if the static port measures 1 bar and the pitot measures 1.2?",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nrho = 1.293 # density of air\np1 = 100000 # pressure at static port in pascal\np2 = 120000 # pressure at pitot tube in pascal\nv2 = 0\n            \n# Use bernoulli and solve for v1\nv1 = ((2 * (p2 - p1)) / rho) ** (1/2)\n\nprint('Airspeed is', v1, 'm/s')\n        ",
        "explanation": "The code uses Bernoulli's principle, knowing that veloity is zero at the pitot tube, solving for the velocity at the static part is possible.",
        "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill pg. 228"
    },
    {
        "question": "10kg of water is entering a tank per second. A whole is drilled at the bottom with a radius of 0.01m. Whats the velocity of the water pouring out?",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nmf = 10\na2 = 0.01 ** 2 * np.pi\nrho = 997 # density of water in kg/m^3\n\n#continuity\nv2 = mf / (a2 * rho)\nprint('Veloity is', v2, 'm/s')\n        ",
        "explanation": "Use the principle of contuinity, M1 = rho * A2 * v2",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "Air flows into a diverging nozzle. What is the gauge at position 2 if the nozzle entry has Area = 0.1 m^2 and velocity = 6 m/s and Area at position 2 = 0.3 m^2?",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\n#continuity to find v2\nrho = 1.293\na1 = 0.1\na2 = 0.3\nv1 = 6\nv2 = (a1 * v1)/a2\n\n#use Bernoulli to find p2 - p1\npg = (0.5 * rho)*(v2 ** 2 - v1 ** 2)\n\nprint('Gauge pressure at position 2 is', pg)\n        ",
        "explanation": "Assumptions revolving around Bernoulli's principle must be made. The sign will be negative as the pressure is lower than before, a simple implementation of contuinuity and Bernoulli's principle can be used to solve for gauge pressure",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why isn't there a normal component of velocity for streamlines?",
        "answer": "A streamline is defined as a line tangential to velocity direction. Therefore there cannot be a normal component as a streamline is already perfectly tangential.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "Why is the fastest velocity for a viscid fluid traveling through a pipe in the center of the pipes cross section?",
        "answer": "Shear forces within the fluid blobs are most present at the outermost of the pipe, where it makes contact with pipe walls. As the liquid is examined closer to the center, the shear forces show a trend of tapering off, the farther from a wall.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "A plane is flying at 10000ft. The pressure at a point on the wing is 0.5 bar. Ambient pressure is 1 bar. Ambient temp is 297k. Calculate the temperature at the moment on the wing",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\np1 = 0.5\npa = 0.7\nta = 297\ngamma = 1.4\n\n#the relationship between ambient pressure and temp and measured pressure and temp can be used\n\nt1 = ta * (p1 / pa) ** ((gamma - 1) / gamma)\n\nprint('Temp at the point on the wing is', t1, 'k')\n\n        ",
        "explanation": "Isentropic flow must be assumed, and then the relationship between pressure and temperature ratios can be used.",
        "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill pg. 540"
    },
    {
        "question": "Is air flow compressible at Mach = 0.2?",
        "answer": "Flow is almost always compressible at any speed. However, below M = 0.3, the variation in a calculation using incompressible vs compressible methods is less than 5%. So for all calculation purposes, no.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill pg. 585"
    },
    {
        "question": "The upstream conditions of a normal shock are as follows: Velocity = 600 m/s, Temp = 270 k. What is the velocity after the shock occurs? Assume gamma = 1.4",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nv1 = 600\nR = 287\nt = 270\ng = 1.4\n# find mach number\na = (g * t1 * R) ** (1/2)\nM1 = v1 / a\n\n# normal shock formula can be used or a normal shock table for m2\nM2 = ((1 + ((g - 1) / 2) * M1 ** 2) / (g * M1 ** 2 - ((g - 1)/2))) ** (1/2)\n\nv2 = M2 * (g * R * t) ** (1/2)\n\nprint('The velocity after the shock is', v2, 'm/s')\n        ",
        "explanation": "Using the mach formulas and tables we can calculate M1 and then use the normal shock table or equation to find M2. We know that total temperature remains constant, so velocity can be calculated after. Ratios could have been found using normal shock tables.",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "Expand on the zeroeth law. What problem did the zeroeth law solve?",
        "answer": "The zeroeth law provides a solution for multiple objects in equilibrium. It defines temperature as the property that multiple bodies will share if in equilibrium with each other. Mathmatically, if a = b and b = c then a = c.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "If a process is reversible and adiabatic, is it also isentropic?",
        "answer": "Yes, a reversible, adiabatic process results in no change in heat (Q), therefore, no change in entropy.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "A stirring rod is intorduced into a system of viscous fluid and turned on. Is any of the work converted to entropy?",
        "answer": "The shaft work from the stirring itself would not introduce and entropy. However, the friction between the stirrer and the fluid may introduce heat and therefore a change in entropy",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill. pg. 379"
    },
    {
        "question": "A 25 kg hot rock at 600 k is thrown into a lake. It comes to thermal equilibrium at 290 k with the surrounding water. What is the rock's change in entropy? Cv = 0.63 kJ/Kkg",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nt1 = 600\nt2 = 290\nm = 25\ncv = 0.63\n\n# use formula for entropy change\ndeltaS = m * cv * np.log(t2/t1)\nprint('The rocks change in entropy is', deltaS, 'kJ/K')\n        ",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference":"John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill. pg. 385"
    },
    {
        "question": "Elaborate on the two property rule, why does it exist?",
        "answer": "There are only two ways to change the state of a system, heat and work. Both require a change of at least two properties between pressure, volume, and temp. The ideal gas equation demonstrates this rather nicely, PV = nRT.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
    },
    {
        "question": "Calculate what a pitot tube would measure if the upstream flow is 700 m/s, 300 K and gamma = 1.4",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nv = 700\nt = 300\nm = v / ((287 * g * t) ** (1/2))\ng = 1.4\n\n#rayleigh pitot tube formula\noutput = (((((g + 1)**2) * m **2) / ((4 * g * m ** 2) - 2 * (g - 1))) ** (g / (g - 1))) *((1 - g + 2 * g * m ** 2)/(g + 1))\n\nprint('The pitot tube would measure a pressure ratio of', output)\n        ",
        "explanation": "Use mach formula to find mach number and then Rayleigh pitot tube formula.",
        "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill pg.605"
    },
    {
        "question": "Is it possible for an object to be immersed in fluid flow and have no stagnation points on its surface?",
        "answer": "No, any object fully immersed in fluid flow will have at least one stagnation point on its surface where the flow velocity is zero. It is possible for there to be more than one stagnation point on such an object, but it is impossible for there to be none.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "When solving for the velocity of a chaotic fast-moving fluid close to a wall would it be valid to employ Bernoulli’s equation?",
        "answer": "In this case using Bernoulli’s equation would be invalid. Bernoulli’s equation can only validly be used when the flow is steady, incompressible, and inviscid. The word chaotic indicates the fluid is turbulent, not steady. The fact that it is close to a wall indicates there would be non-negligible friction effects acting on the fluid.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "What differentiates the Navier-Stokes equations from Euler’s equations?",
        "answer": "Euler’s equations are derived from an application of Newton’s Second Law to inviscid flow. The Navier-Stokes equations take the viscosity terms into account.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the relationship between viscosity and shear stress?",
        "answer": "Viscosity is the proportionality coefficient that when multiplied by velocity gradient yields shear stress.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shear_stress"
      },
      {
        "question": "Can M ever not be equal to 1 at the throat of a channel?",
        "answer": "Yes. In the case that the change in velocity with respect to distance is equal to zero, acceleration is zero through the channel, and M can be not equal to 1 at the throat.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "Is Fanno flow an appropriate model for a steady, compressible flow through a long pipe with friction, and loses heat to the pipe through convective heat transfer?",
        "answer": "No. Although the Fanno flow model is valid for steady, compressible flow with friction through long pipes, the flow must also be adiabatic (Q=0) for Fanno flow to be an applicable model. The presence of convective heat transfer indicates that heat Q is non-zero and therefore the flow is not adiabatic. One must also confirm that the area of the duct is constant and assume flow is one-dimensional before applying the Fanno flow model.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "Is it possible for an oblique shock or a detached shock to form at the same turning angle?",
        "answer": "Yes. It is possible for an oblique shock or a detached shock to form at a concave corner of the same turning angle given different flow Mach numbers. Flows at lower Mach numbers have lower maximum turning angles, so a lower velocity flow can produce a detached shock going over the same corner that a higher velocity flow would produce an oblique shock going over.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "What differentiates Poiseuille flow from Couette flow and what is an example of a situation in which each one could be useful?",
        "answer": "Poiseuille flow is constant pressure gradient driven flow between two stationary plates. One example of a situation in which it could be useful for modeling axisymmetric flow through pipes. In contrast, Couette flow is velocity driven flow between a stationary and a moving plate. It could be useful for modeling for example bearing lubrication.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "If one puts a backspinning cylinder in transverse flow, what direction will the resulting lift force be in?",
        "answer": "Due to the Magnus effect, the resulting lift force will be in the upwards direction normal to the flow. This can be seen in the similarity of the pressure gradient and the shape of the streamlines around a cylinder to those of an airfoil with a positive angle of attack.",
        "reference": "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magnus_effect"
      },
      {
        "question": "Water having a density of 999 kg/m^3 travels along a curved streamline with a normal acceleration of -5 m/s^2. At a point when the local radius of curvature is 10 m, what is the component of the flows velocity tangent to the streamline and what is the pressure gradient across the streamline?",
        "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n\n      rho = 999 # Density (kg/m^3)\n      a_n = -5 # Normal Acceleration (m/s^2)\n      R = 10 # Local Radius of Curvature (m)\n\n      # Rearrange acceleration normal to streamline equation\n      v_s = np.sqrt((- a_n) * R)\n\n      # Formula for pressure gradient normal to a streamline\n      dpdn = rho * (-a_n)\n\n      print('Velocity tangent to streamline:', v_s, 'm/s. Pressure gradient accross the streamline:', dpdn, 'Pa/m.')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code utilizes the formula for acceleration normal to a streamline and for pressure gradient normal to a streamline. These two formulas can be expressed as a_n = - v_s^2 / R and dp/dn = rho * v_s^2 / R, where 'a_n' is the normal acceleration, 'v_s' is the tangential velocity, 'R' is the local radius of curvature, and 'dp/dn' is the pressure gradient, respectively.",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "A fluid (gasoline) of density 680 kg/m^3, a kinematic viscosity of 4.6E-7 m^2/s, and a mass flow rate 0.2 kg/s flows through a pipe. Calculate the pressure loss over 10 km of 0.5 m diameter pipe owing to friction.",
        "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n\n      rho = 680 # Density (kg/m^3)\n      nu = 4.6 * (10 ** (-7)) # Kinematic Viscosity (m^2/s)\n      mdot = 0.2 # Mass Flow Rate (kg/s)\n      L = 10000 # Length of Pipe (m)\n      D = 0.5 # Diameter of Pipe (m)\n\n      # Determine dynamic viscosity\n      mu = nu * rho\n\n      # Determine volumetric flow rate\n      Q = mdot/rho\n\n      # Apply Hagen-Poiseuille equation\n      delta_p = (8 * mu * Q * L)/(np.pi * ((D/2)**4))\n\n      print('Pressure loss:', delta_p, 'Pa')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code first takes kinematic viscosity and mass flow rate, and uses density to calculated dynamic viscosity and volumetric flow rate from them. Next it applies the Hagen-Poiseuille formula delta_p = (8 * mu * Q * L)/(pi * R^4) where 'delta_p' is the pressure loss, 'mu' is dynamic viscosity, 'Q' is volumetric flow rate, 'L' is the length of pipe, and 'R' is the radius of the pipe, respectively. Using this equation it determines the pressure loss over the given length of pipe.",
        "reference": "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hagen-Poiseuille_equation"
      },
      {
        "question": "A plate 2 m in length and 5 m in width is submerged in a fluid (water) with a density of 999 kg/m^3, and it is tilted down in such a way that the length edge is at a 20 degree angle with the surface of the fluid. What this the vertical force acting upon the plate. The acceleration due to gravity can be assumed to be 9.8 m/s^2.",
        "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n\n      rho = 999 # Density (kg/m^3)\n      L = 2 # Length of plate (m)\n      w = 5 # Width of plate (m)\n      alpha = 20 # Angle of plate from surface (degrees)\n      g = 9.8 # Acceleration due to gravity (m/s^2)\n\n      # The vertical force acting upon the plate is equivalent to the weight of the volume of the fluid above the plate\n      F_v = 0.5 * (L**2) * np.cos(alpha * np.pi / 180) * np.sin(alpha * np.pi / 180) * w * rho * g\n\n      print('The vertical force acting on the plate is:', F_v, 'N')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the vertical force acting on a plate submerged in fluid at an angle with the surface of the fluid. It does this by calculating the weight of the fluid above the plate, which is equivalent to the vertical force acting upon the plate. This can be found by multiplying together volume, density, and gravity, or equivalently using the following formula F_v = 0.5 * L * cos(alpha) * L * sin(alpha) * w * rho * g, where 'L' is length of plat, 'w' is width of plate, 'rho' is density of the fluid, and 'g' is acceleration due to gravity.",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "Calculate the mass flow rate through a convergent nozzle given an inlet stagnation pressure of 1 bar, an inlet stagnation temperature of 300K, a fluid (air) with an isobaric specific heat capacity of 1005 J/kgK, a flow velocity of at Mach 1.5, and a cross section nozzle area of 3 m^2. Assume gamma to be 1.4.",
        "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n\n      p0 = 1 # Inlet stagnation pressure (bar)\n      T0 = 300 # Inlet stagnation temperature (K)\n      cp = 1005 # Isobaric specific heat capacity (J/kgK)\n      M = 1.5 # Mach number\n      gamma = 1.4 # Heat capacity ratio\n      A = 3 # Area (m^2)\n\n      # Convert inlet stagnation pressure from units of bar to Pascal\n      p0 = 100000 * p0\n\n      # Determine the flow capacity (non-dimensional mass flow)\n      fmdot = (gamma / np.sqrt(gamma - 1)) * M * ((1 + (((gamma - 1) / 2) * (M**2)))**(-0.5 * (gamma + 1) / (gamma - 1)))\n\n      # Based on the flow capacity, determine the mass flow rate\n      mdot = fmdot * A * p0 / np.sqrt(cp * T0)\n\n      print('The mass flow rate is:', mdot, 'kg/s')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code determines the flow capacity using the following formula (gamma/sqrt(gamma-1))*M*((1+(((gamma-1)/2)* (M^2)))^(-0.5*(gamma+1)/(gamma-1))), where 'M' represents Mach number and 'gamma' represents heat capacity ratio respectively. Then it calculates the mass flow rate based on the determined flow capacity, recognizing that flow capacity is equal to mdot*sqrt(cp*T0)/(A*p0), where 'mdot' is mass flow rate, 'cp' is isobaric specific heat capacity, 'T0' is inlet stagnation temperature, 'A' is area, and 'p0' is inlet stagnation pressure, respectively.",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "A compressible, viscous flow enters a 4 meter diameter pipe at a mach number of 3. The skin friction coefficient is 0.002. What is the length of pipe necessary to choke the flow?",
        "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n\n      D = 4 # Diameter (m)\n      M = 3 # Mach number\n      gamma = 1.4 # Heat capacity ratio\n      cf = 0.002 # Skin Friction coefficient\n\n      # Determine Lmax\n      Lmax = (D/(4 * cf)) * (((1 - (M ** 2))/(gamma * (M ** 2)))+(((gamma + 1)/(2 * gamma)) * np.log((((gamma + 1)/2) * (M ** 2))/(1 + (((gamma - 1)/2) * (M ** 2))))))\n\n      print('The length of pipe necessary to choke the flow is:', Lmax, 'm')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code uses the formula relating Mach number to 4 * cf * Lmax / D (where 'cf' is skin friction coefficient, 'Lmax' is length from input Mach number required to choke the flow, and 'D' is pipe diameter, respectively) to determine Lmax.",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "A fluid (water) with a constant density of 999 kg/m^3 flows steadily through a pipe. The initial height is 10 m greater than the final height, and the initial velocity is 5 m/s. There is no pressure change, and acceleration due to gravity can be assumed to be 9.81 m/s^2. Assume not flow friction or viscous effects. What is the velocity at the final condition?",
        "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n\n      rho = 999 # Density (kg/m^3)\n      delta_z = 10 # Change in height (z) between the initial and final condition (m)\n      v1 = 5 # Initial Velocity (m/s)\n      delta_p = 0 # Change in pressue (p) between the initial and final condition (Pa)\n      g = 9.81 # Acceleration due to gravity (m/s^2)\n\n      # Apply Bernoulli's principle\n      v2 = np.sqrt(2 * (delta_p + (rho * g * delta_z) + (0.5 * rho * (v1**2)))/rho)\n\n      print('The velocity at the final condition is:', v2, 'm/s')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code applies Bernoulli's equation, which states that p + (rho * g * z) + (0.5 * rho * v^2) = constant, where 'p' is pressure, 'rho' is density, 'g' is acceleration due to gravity, and 'v' is velocity, respectively, to determine the final velocity in the pipe. Bernoulli's equation can be validly applied because the flow is steady, incompressible and inviscid.",
        "reference": "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bernoullis_principle"
      },
      {
        "question": "Calculate the momentum flux of a fluid with density 400 kg/m^3 flowing through a pipe with velocity profile v(r) = V0 * (1 - (2 * (r/R)^3))  where the pipe radius R = 2 m, and the center line velocity V0 = 1 m/s.",
        "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n\n      rho = 400 # density (kg/m^2)\n      R = 2 # pipe radius (m)\n      V0 = 1 # center line velocity (m/s)\n\n      # Apply momentum flux equation\n      mdot_v = (2/5) * np.pi * rho * (V0 ** 2) * (R ** 2)\n\n      print('The momentum flux is:', mdot_v, 'N')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code evaluates the integral of rho * v(r)^2 * 2pi * r dr from 0 to R in order to determine the momentum flux, where 'rho' is density, 'v(r)' is the velocity profile specified in the question, and 'R' is the pipe radius.",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "Plot a graph of area over throat area vs. Mach number for Mach numbers 0.1 to 3 where heat capacity ratio gamma is 1.4.",
        "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n      import matplotlib.pyplot as plt\n\n      gamma = 1.4 # Heat capacity ratio\n      M = np.linspace(0.1,3,100) # Mach number\n      AoverAstar = (((gamma + 1)/2) ** (- (gamma + 1)/(2 * (gamma - 1)))) * (((1 + (((gamma - 1)/2) * (M ** 2))) ** ((gamma + 1)/(2 * (gamma - 1))))/M)\n\n      plt.plot(AoverAstar,M)\n      plt.xlabel('A/A*')\n      plt.ylabel('M')\n      plt.show()\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code uses the relationship between area over throat area and Mach number to generate the desired graph.",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "Plot a graph of dimensionless impulse function (F / mdot*sqrt(cp*T0)) for Mach numbers 0.5 to 10 where heat capacity ratio gamma is 1.4.",
        "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n      import matplotlib.pyplot as plt\n\n      gamma = 1.4 # Heat capacity ratio\n      M = np.linspace(0.5,10,100) # Mach number\n\n      dimensionless_impulse_function=(((1 + (((gamma - 1)/2) * (M**2)))**(gamma/(gamma - 1))) ** (-1)) * (((gamma / np.sqrt(gamma - 1)) * M * ((1 + (((gamma - 1)/2) * (M**2)))**(-0.5 * (gamma + 1)/(gamma - 1))))**(-1)) * (1 + (gamma * (M ** 2)))\n\n      plt.plot(M, dimensionless_impulse_function)\n      plt.show()\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code uses the relationship between dimensionless impulse function and Mach number to generate the desired graph.",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "Given a constant initial temperature T1 = 290 K, graph the resulting stagnation temperature for Mach numbers 0.5 through 5. It may be assumed that the heat capacity ratio gamma is 1.4.",
        "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n      import matplotlib.pyplot as plt\n\n      gamma = 1.4 # Heat capacity ratio\n      M = np.linspace(0.5,10,100) # Mach number\n      T1 = 290 # Initial temperature (K)\n\n      T01 = T1 * (1 + (((gamma - 1)/2) * (M ** 2)))\n\n      plt.plot(M, T01)\n      plt.show()\n      ",
        "explanation":  "This code uses the relationship between the ratio of stagnation temp (T01) over temperature (T1) and Mach number (M) to produce the desired graph.",
        "reference":""
      },
      {
        "question": "In what type of flows can Bernoulli’s principle be applied?",
        "answer": "Bernoulli’s can be applied at low speed, inviscid (without flow friction or viscous effects), and incompressible steady flow. It is applied to flow along a streamline, where the flow can be rotational or irrational. However, if the flow is rotational, Bernoulli holds between any 2 points in the flow, not necessarily just on the same streamline. If the flow is irrotational, Bernoulli’s can apply across streamlines.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the difference between Couette Flow and Poiseuille Flow, and when can each be applied?",
        "answer": "Both Couette and Poiseuille flows are both examples of viscous flows. Couette flow is considered to flow between a moving and stationary plate. The pressure gradient between the two plates is 0, and the flow is driven solely by the shearing motion of the plates rather than pressure differences. Poiseuille flow is a flow between 2 stationary plates, driven by a constant pressure gradient induced by a constant pressure difference or pressure drop in a pipe or between 2 parallel plates. Poiseuille flow is axisymmetric and swirl-free. Poiseuille flow can be observed in blood flow or through pipes, while Couette Flow can be observed in engineering applications involving lubrication between 2 surfaces, like a bearing. ",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Why is there a pressure gradient across curved streamlines?",
        "answer": "Neglecting gravitational forces, consider a fluid blob traveling along a curved streamline. The acceleration is in the normal direction towards the center of curvature. This acceleration wouldn’t exist if it were traveling in a straight path. When the streamline is curved, a normal pressure force must balance the normal acceleration, and that normal pressure force keeps the fluid moving in its curved path. Due to curvature, fluid moves at higher velocities towards the inside of the curvature, and following Bernoulli’s equation, low pressure is related to high velocity, causing a pressure gradient with low pressure towards the inside of the curve and high pressure on the outside.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "What is the significance of the Clausius Inequality in irreversible and reversible processes? ",
        "answer": "For an irreversible process, the Clausius Inequality strictly says that heat transfer occurs WITH irrecoverable energy loss. This holds because an irreversible process means the system cannot be brought to its original state without external help. For reversible processes, equality (in the Clausius Inequality itself) applies when all processes within the cycle are reversible. Heat transfer occurs WITHOUT any irrecoverable energy losses, and the system changes in a quasi-equilibrium matter. ",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "How does entropy relate to the directionality and irreversibility of processes in nature?",
        "answer": "Entropy represents the inability of a system’s thermal energy to yield useful work. Processes favor the direction that leads to an increase in entropy, like heat flowing from a hot object to a cold one. In irreversible processes, entropy increases, leading to a loss of the ability to perform useful work. Reversible processes allow quasi-equilibrium changes, allowing a system to be brought back to its original state without any entropy change. ",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "What are adiabatic, isobaric, isochoric, isentropic, and isothermal processes, and how can I relate them? ",
        "answer": "The adiabatic process occurs when no heat is exchanged between the system and its surroundings. Isobaric processes occur at constant pressure, isochoric processes occur at constant volume, and isothermal processes occur at constant temperature. An isentropic process occurs with no change in entropy. Relating these processes depends on the conditions and behaviors of the system and can overlap. In isentropic processes, the system remains adiabatic. An adiabatic process can be isentropic if it is reversible. Isothermal processes can be isochoric or isobaric if they occur at constant volume or pressure.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Why do we consider flow across an expansion fan isentropic?",
        "answer": "Isentropic flow assumes energy conservation and moment without losses due to friction, heat transfer, and shock waves when we consider it isentropic. It is also associated with ideal gas behavior, and the fact that entropy stays in contrast through the expansion process simplifies the analysis of energy changes and heat transfer within a system. Assuming the flox is isentropic allows us to use our isentropic relations to solve flow problems as well. ",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Why does decreasing exit static pressure move a shock in the throat to the exit plane in a supersonic converging-diverging nozzle? ",
        "answer": "Flow reaches its maximum velocity at the throat of the nozzle. Before the throat, flow is supersonic, while after the throat, flow is subsonic. The shock wave depends on the pressures and velocities before and after the throat. The diverging section of the nozzle allows the flow to increase its velocity and decrease its static pressure. If exit static pressure is less than the pressure at the throat, the shockwave will form at the throat, and decreasing the pressure will cause the shock to move toward the exit plane. The pressure ratio/gradient is important to determining shock position.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Why doesn’t the mass flow rate through a converging nozzle increase when reducing exit static pressure in choked flow?",
        "answer": "The mass flow rate doesn’t increase when reducing exit static pressure at the exit because the choked flow is reached at the throat of the nozzle. Choked flow occurs flow at the nozzle reaches Mach 1, and flow is limited by the speed of sound and can’t accelerate further. The communication between the initial conditions at the start of the nozzle and the conditions at the end travel at the speed of sound, so once Mach 1 is hit at the throat, the inlet doesn’t know what’s happening at the exit.",
        "explanation": "",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "A wind tunnel produces inviscid incompressible flow along a streamline. There is a factor of .05 decrease in the pressure from point 1 to point 2, and a factor of 20 increase in the velocity from point 1 to point 2. At point 1 the pressure is 106kPa and the velocity is 5 m/s. Calculate the density of air in the wind tunnel, ignore any effects due to gravity.",
        "answer": "\n      \nP1 = 106000 # Pressure (Pa)\nV1 = 5 # Velocity (m/s)\n\n# Calculate P2 and V2 with given ratios\nP2 = (106000)*(1-.05)\nV2 = 20*5\n\n#Apply Bernoulli's (P1+(1/2)(rho)(V1)^2= P2+(1/2)(rho)(V2)^2)\n\nrho = (2*(P2-P1))/((V1)**2-(V2)**2)\nprint(str(rho)+'kg/(m**3)')\n\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the density of air at a point in a streamline using bernoulli's equation (P1+(1/2)(rho)(V1)^2= P2+(1/2)(rho)(V2)^2) where p1 is the pressure at point 1, rho is the desnity of the fluid, v1 is the velocity of the fluid at point 1, p2 is the pressure of the fluid at point 2, and v2 is the velocity of the fluid at point 2.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "An H shaped tank is filled with water, with the top exposed to open air. From the bottom of the H to the top is 1 m. From the bottom of the H to the bar on the H is 0.5m. If the density of water is 1000 kg/m^3 and the pressure at the bar in the H is 101234 Pa, calculate the air pressure.",
        "answer": "\nrho_water = 1000 #Density of water (kg/m**3)\nheight = 1-0.50 # Height difference (m)\nP_bar = 101234 # Atmospheric pressure (Pa)\ng = 9.81 # Gravity (m/s**2)\n\n#Use hydrostatic equation (P_bar = P_air + rho*g*height)\nP_air = -((rho_water*g*height)-P_bar)\n\nprint(str(P_air) + 'Pa')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code uses the hydrostatic equation to find the pressure at a point of the tank (p = p_air + rho*g*height), where p_air is the atmospheric pressure the liquid is exposed to, rho is the density of the liquid, g is the gravitation acceleration, and h is the height differnce from the 2 points. ",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "A converging-diverging nozzle has air flow entering at 15 kPa and a stagnation temperation of 290 K. The flow is steady and isentropic with y = 1.4. The throat of the nozzle has a mach number of 1. If the mass flow rate is 3.56 kg/s, what is the area of the throat? Assume R = 0.287 kJ/ kg * K.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nm_dot = 3.56 # Mass flow rate (kg/s)\nR = 0.287 #Constant for air (kJ/kg*K)\np_stagnation = 15 #Stagnation pressure (kPa)\nT_stagnation = 290 #Stagnation Temperature \n\nrho_stagnation = (p_stagnation)/(R* T_stagnation) #Calculate stagnation density\n\n#from flow tables throat density/stagnation density = 0.6339 and throat temperature/ stagnation temperature = 0.8333\n\nthroat_density = 0.6339 * rho_stagnation\nthroat_temperature = 0.8333 * T_stagnation\n\n#Use equation of throat velocity (sqrt(yRT))\n\nthroat_velocity = np.sqrt(1.4*.287*throat_temperature*10**3)\n\n#Use equationof mass flow rate ( mdot = rho * A * throat velocity)\nArea = (m_dot)/(throat_velocity*throat_density)\n\nprint(str(Area) + 'm**2')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the throat area of converging-diverging nozzle using the equation for stagnation density ( stagnation pressure/ (universal gas constant * stagnation temperature), isentropic flow tables with a y value of 1.4, the throat velocity equation ( throat velocity = sqrt(yRT), and the mass flow rate equation ( mdot = rho*Area*throat velocity).",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Air is hit by a shockwave in a tunnel. The air has a static pressure of 95 kPa. What is the mach wave downstream of the shock if the static pressure behind the shock is 7.24 kPa and the mach number upstream is M = 0.594.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\np2 = 7.24 # pressure after shock (kPa)\np1 = 95 # pressure before shock (kPa)\ny = 1.4 #gamma value\nM1 = 0.594 # Mach number upstream\n\n#Using normal shock equation ( p2/p1 = (1+yM1^2)/(1+yM2^2) due to equation formatting equation isn't it 1 line\n\np_ratio = 7.24/95\nnumerator = 1+y*M1**2\nM2 = np.sqrt(((numerator/p_ratio)-1)/y)\nprint(str(M2))\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the Mach wave downstream of the shock wave using the isentropic flow tables, and the isentropic relation that p2/p1 = (1+yM1^2)/(1+yM2^2) where y = 1.4, M1 is the mach number upstream, M2 is the mach number downstream, p2 is the pressure after the shock, and p1 is the pressure before the shock.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "An ideal gas has density of 2.3 kg/m^3, a molar mass of 23 kg/mol and a temperature of 32 degrees Celcius. What is the pressure of the gas if it is in a sealed container under these conditions? The universal gas constant is 8.314 J/mol * K.",
        "answer": "\n      \n\nrho = 2.3 #density of gas (kg/m^3)\nMmass = 23 # Molar mass of gas (kg/mol)\nTemp = 32 # Temperature of gas (C degrees)\nRbar = 8.314 # Universal gas constant (J/mol K)\n\nTemp = 23 + 273.15 #converting the temp to Kelvin\nR = Rbar/Mmass #Specific gas constant of the gas\np = rho * R * Temp # Ideal gas law equation for mass (p = rho*R*T)\nprint(str(p) + 'Pa')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the pressure of an ideal gas using the ideal gas law, converting for mass values. It uses the fact that the specific gas constant is the universal gas constant/ the material's molar mass in kg/mol, and a form of the ideal gas law equation (p= rho*R*T), where p is the pressure of the gas, rho is the density of the gas, R is the specific gas constant, and T is the temperature.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "A heat engine does 212 J of work and has an efficiency of 14%. How much energy is absorbed by the heat?",
        "answer": "\nwork = 212 # work by the heat engine (Joules)\nn = .23 # efficiency of heat engine\n\nQ1 = work/n # using equation for efficiency (n = W/Q1)\nprint(str(Q1) + 'J')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates how much energy was absorbed by heat in a heat engine by using the efficiency formula (n = W/Q1) where n is the efficiency of the heat engine, W is the work done by the heat engine, and Q1 is how much heat is absorbed.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "A fluid moving at a velocity of 13 m/s has a specific pressure of 8 Pa and a temperature of 141 K. What is the stagnation temperature of the fluid?",
        "answer": "\nTemp = 141 #Temperature of fluid (K)\nv = 13 #velocity of fluid (m/s)\ncp = 8 # specific pressure of fluid\n\nTstag = Temp + (v)**2/(2*cp)\n\nprint(str(Tstag) + 'K')\n      ",
        "explanation": "This code calculates the stagnation temperature of a fluid using the equation for stagnation temperature (T = T1+v1^2/2cp), where T = the stagnation pressure, T1 is the temperature of the fluid, V1 is the velocity of the fluid, and cp is the fluid's specific pressure.",
        "reference": ""
      },
      {
        "question": "Discuss one method to accurately measure the pressure used in deriving the Bernoulli equation.",
        "answer": "The pressure used in deriving the Bernoulli equation is the thermodynamic pressure, more commonly referred to as static pressure. This is the pressure experienced by the fluid blobs as they are in motion. Since there is no static pressure variation normal to straight streamlines, a tube with a measuring section aligned with local flow extending out from any near surface with small holes oriented perpendicular to flow direction at a location where streamlines have become parallel to the measuring section can be used when connected to a pressure sensor to accurately determine static pressure at the pressure sensor located at a no flow location inside the tube.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "Fox, Robert W., and Alan T. McDonald (2011), Introduction to Fluid Mechanics, 8th ed. John Wiley & Sons."
    },
    {
        "question": "What is used in the place of the free body diagrams used in basic mechanics for fluids problems?",
        "answer": "Instead of using free-body diagrams that rely on identifiable rigid bodies, a set of control surfaces that enclose a control volume is observed. It is a volume in space in which fluid flows that can either be stationary or moving with no net change in the quantity of mass contained. This solves the issue of system boundaries that do not allow any mass crossing system boundaries.",
        "reference": "Fox, Robert W., and Alan T. McDonald (2011), Introduction to Fluid Mechanics, 8th ed. John Wiley & Sons."
    },
    {
        "question": "Why must the hydrostatic force act normal to any surface the fluid is in contact with?",
        "answer": "The hydrostatic force must act normal to any surface because a static fluid cannot hold any shear stresses.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "Fox, Robert W., and Alan T. McDonald (2011), Introduction to Fluid Mechanics, 8th ed. John Wiley & Sons."
    },
    {
        "question": "How does torque output relate to conservation of energy in stationary systems?",
        "answer": "Torque is equal to a force applied multiplied by a distance. The distance this force is applied through is equal to the path traveled s=2*pi*r*n, where n is the revolutions of the shaft being applied a torque. We can then arrive at shaft work which equals torque times 2*pi*n. When converted into an equation of energy per unit time this becomes 2*pi*torque*n_dot, where n_dot is revolutions per unit time. In a stationary system, the total change in energy must equal the change in internal energy. Therefore, the rate of change in internal thermal energy must be equivalent to the shaft work thereby associating torque with conservation of energy.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel (2007), Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
    },
    {
        "question": "Describe why a compressed air canister gets cold while in use.",
        "answer": "When the can is sealed, over time, the temperature of the can reaches the room temperature. When the can is used, the liquid becomes exposed to atmospheric pressure. Since the boiling temperature of the gas is significantly lower than room temperature at this atmospheric pressure, the liquid in the can begins boiling. To be boiling the temperature of the liquid must drop, pulling heat from the can in the amount of the latent heat of vaporization causing it to feel cold.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel (2007), Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
    },
    {
        "question": "Why do aircraft engines not have a low temperature sink to satisfy the Kelvin Planck Statement?",
        "answer": "Aircraft engines are internal combustion engines that bring in air from an external source, and combust with fuel turning some of the increased internal energy into shaft work and other energy into high-velocity air that is output. The high-temperature reservoir comes from the combusting fuel. The acting low-temperature reservoir is how the engine brings in fresh cold air from the environment for every cycle while outputting a relatively small amount of heat to the environment.",
        "explanation":"", 
        "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel (2007), Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
    },
    {
        "question": "Describe why a converging diverging nozzle is used to accelerate airflow.",
        "answer": "By analyzing the momentum equation of a differential control volume dp/rho + d(V^2/2) = 0 we can arrive at dV/V = (-dA/A)*(1/(1-M^2)). This equation shows that for subsonic flow M<1, and we reduce the area, the change in velocity is positive. Now if we use supersonic flow M>1, and the area is increased, the change in velocity is positive. This shows that a converging nozzle increases velocity at subsonic velocity and a diverging nozzle increases velocity at supersonic speed. If a converging-diverging nozzle is put together and designed for the velocity to be M=1 at the center, then air can be accelerated from subsonic to supersonic speed.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "Fox, Robert W., and Alan T. McDonald (2011), Introduction to Fluid Mechanics, 8th ed. John Wiley & Sons."
    },
    {
        "question": "Under what conditions does a normal shock form and what occurs  to the fluid through the shock?",
        "answer": "When flow is moving at supersonic speed such that a pressure field cannot propagate upstream, then the fluid creates a violent adjustment to the downstream conditions. The pressure suddenly increases over a distance of <2 micrometers, velocity decreases, and temperature increases. These things cause a rise in density and because the shock is adiabatic but irreversible, the entropy increases. These things also cause an increase in the speed of sound causing the Mach number of the flow to decrease.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "Fox, Robert W., and Alan T. McDonald (2011), Introduction to Fluid Mechanics, 8th ed. John Wiley & Sons."
    },
    {
        "question": "Discuss the effects of heating and cooling on the temperature of the flow using a Ts diagram for frictionless flow in a constant-area duct.",
        "answer": "The effects of heating and cooling on the temperature can be observed from the shape of the Rayleigh line on the Ts diagram. For every region outside 1/sqrt(k)<M<1, heating causes the temperature to increase, and cooling causes the temperature to decrease. This is because as flow is initially subsonic, heating increases the Mach number until the maximum heat addition without choking is reached at M=1. If the flow is initially supersonic, heating reduces the Mach number to M=1.",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "Fox, Robert W., and Alan T. McDonald (2011), Introduction to Fluid Mechanics, 8th ed. John Wiley & Sons."
    },
    {
      "question": "Consider steady flow in a water pipe joint with input fluid through A1 at velocity v1, output thorugh A3 at v3, leak through a hole at rate of O. Find the velocity v2 and direction of fluid flowing through the third open part of the joint with area A2.",
      "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nrho = 999  # Density (kg/m^3)\nA1 = 0.2  # Area 1 (m^2)\nv1 = 5  # Velocity 1 (m/s)\nA2 = 0.2  # Area 2 (m^2)\nv2 = 5  # Velocity 2 (m/s)\nA3 = 0.2  # Area 3 (m^2)\nv3 = 12  # Velocity 3 (m/s)\nO = 0.1 # Volumetric flow rate leakage (m^3/s)\n\n# Make assumption that flow at 2 is outward to solve\n# Assume steady flow, incompressible flow, Uniform Properties at each section\n\n# Apply the principle of continuity (-A1*v1 + A2*v2 + Q = 0)\nv2 = (v1*A1 - v3*A3 - O) / A2  \n\nprint('Velocity at location 2:', v2, 'm/s')\n      ",
      "explanation": "This code uses the general control volume equation for continuity of incompressible flow. The flow into the joint is negative area * velocity with flow out of the joint being positive. Any known volumetric leaking can be added or subtracted as appropriate with the whole equation equaling to 0. Because the output of v2 is a negative number, we know that our assumption of flow outward was incorrect and it is actually flowing inward.",
      "reference": "Fox, Robert W., and Alan T. McDonald (2011), Introduction to Fluid Mechanics, 8th ed. John Wiley & Sons."
    },
    {
      "question": "Water flows steadily through a horizontal nozzle, discharging to the atmosphere. At the nozzle inlet the diameter is D1; at the nozzle outlet the diameter id D2. Evaluate the inlet gage pressure with given D1 and D2 and a desired flow rate Q.",
      "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nD1 = 3  # Nozzle inlet diameter (in)\nD2 = 1 # Nozzle outlet diameter (in)\nQ = 0.7 # Desired output flow rate (ft^3/s)\nrho = 1.94 # Fluid density (slug/ft^3)\npi = 3.1416\n\n# Apply the Bernoulli equation along a streamline to find minimum gage pressure (p1=(rho/2)*(v2^2-v1^2))\n# Apply continuity equation (v1*A1=v2*A2=Q)\n# Combine equations with A=pi*D^2/4\np1 = (8*rho*Q^2 / ((pi^2)*D1^4))*((D1/D2)^4 - 1)\n\nprint('Inlet gage pressure:', p1, 'lbf/in^2')\n      ",
      "explanation": "This code calculates the minimum inlet gage pressure at the nozzle inlet to produce the desired flow rate. It applies the Bernoulli equation along a streamline to find minimum gage pressure (p1=(rho/2)*(v2^2-v1^2)) then substitutes the continuity equation to get the desired volumetric flow rate into the equation.",
      "reference": "Fox, Robert W., and Alan T. McDonald (2011), Introduction to Fluid Mechanics, 8th ed. John Wiley & Sons." 
    },
    {
      "question": "Air flows steadily through a converging-diverging duct from P1, T1, v1 to M2 at the outlet, where local isentropic stagnation conditions are known to be P02 and T02. Compute the local isentropic stagnation pressure P01.",
      "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nP1 = 350 # Pressure inlet (kPa)\nk = 1.4 # Ideal Gas\nR = 287 # Specific Gas Constant (J/kg*K)\nT1 = 60 # Temperature inlet (degrees C)\nv1 = 183 # Velocity inlet (m/s)\n\n\n#Find speed of sound using c=sqrt(kRT)\nc=(k*R*(T1+273))^(1/2)\n\n#Find the Mach number using M=v/c\nM=v1/c\n\n# Use local isentropic stagnation properties\nP01=P1*(1+((k-1)/2)*M^2)^(k*(k-1))\n\nprint('Stagnation pressure at inlet:', P01, 'kPa')\n      ",
      "explanation": "This code calculates the inlet stagnation pressure after determining the local speed of light and mach number to use the local isentropic stagnation property equation: P01=P1*(1+((k-1)/2)*M^2)^(k*(k-1)).",
      "reference": "Fox, Robert W., and Alan T. McDonald (2011), Introduction to Fluid Mechanics, 8th ed. John Wiley & Sons."
    },
    {
      "question": "Air flows isentropically through a converging nozzle. At a section where the nozzle area is A1, there is local P1, T1, and M1. The back pressure is P2. Find the mass flow rate at the throat Mdot.",
      "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nM1 = 0.52 # Mach number at section\nT1 = 40 # Temperature at section (degrees F)\nP1 = 60 # Pressure at section (psia)\nA1 = 0.013 # Area at section (ft^2)\nk = 1.4 # Ideal gas\nP2 = 30 # Back pressure (psia)\nR = 53.3 # Specific Gas Constant (ftlbf/(lbm degree Rankin))\nrho = 0.324 #Density of air (lbm/ft^3)\n\n# Use local isentropic stagnation properties\nP01=P1*(1+((k-1)/2)*M1^2)^(k*(k-1))\n\n#Calculate back pressure ratio\nRatio=P2/P01\n\n#Ratio is less than 0.528 so flow is choked\nM=1\n\n#Calculate velocity using speed of sound and mach number converting degrees F to degrees R\nV1=M*(k*R*(T1+460)*32.2)^(1/2)\n\n#Calculate mass flow rate using rho*V*A\nMdot=rho*V1*A1\n\nprint('Mass flow rate:', Mdot, 'lbm/s')\n      ",
      "explanation": "This code calculates the mass flow rate of air flow through a converging nozzle with choked flow. Initial conditions are used to determine the back pressure ratio using stagnation equation: P01=P1*(1+((k-1)/2)*M^2)^(k*(k-1)) and check for choking. Once choking was identified, the velocity was found using Msqrt(kRT) and plugged into mdot=rho*V*A.",
      "reference": "Fox, Robert W., and Alan T. McDonald (2011), Introduction to Fluid Mechanics, 8th ed. John Wiley & Sons."
    },
    {
      "question": "The gage pressure of an automobile tire is measured to be P1 before a trip and P2 after the trip at a location where the atmospheric pressure is ATM. Assuming the volume of the tire remains constant and the air temperature before the trip is T1, determine air temperature in the tire after the trip.",
      "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nP1g = 210 # Initial gage tire pressure (kPa)\nP2g = 220 # Final gage tire pressure (kPa)\nATM = 95 # Atmospheric pressure (kPa)\nT1 = 25 # Initial air temperature (degrees C)\n\n# Assume volume of tire remains constant, air is an ideal gas\n# Find initial and final pressures using Pgage +Patm = P\nP1= P1g + ATM\nP2= P2g + ATM\n\n# Calculate final temperature using P1*V1/T1 = P2*V2/T2\nT2=P2*(T1+273)/P1\n\nprint('Final tire temperature:', T2, 'Degrees Kelvin')\n      ",
      "explanation": "This code determines the final temperature of the tire given initial temperature and pressure and final pressure. The gage pressures are first converted to total pressure then plugged into an application of the ideal gas law to determine final temperature.",
      "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel (2007), Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
    },
    {
      "question": "A car engine with a power output of PWR has thermal efficiency of E. Determine the fuel consumption rate of this car if the fuel has a heating value of HV.",
      "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nPWR = 65 # Power output (hp)\nE = 0.24 # Thermal Efficiency (%)\nHV = 19000 # Heating value of fuel (Btu/lbm)\n\n# Use definition of thermal efficiency Qdot=Wnet/efficiency and convert to Btu/h\nQdot=(PWR/E)*2545\n\n# Find fuel burn rate mdot=Qdot/HV (energy required/energy supplied per weight of fuel)\nmdot=Qdot/HV\n\nprint('Rate of fuel consumption:', mdot, 'lbm/h')\n      ",
      "explanation": "This code outputs the rate of fuel consumption of an engine given its efficiency, power output, and the energy density of the fuel itself. Values are first plugged into Qdot=workout/efficiency and convereted to proper units to plug into fuelconsumption=energyrequried/(energy/massoffuel).",
      "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel (2007), Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
    },
    {
      "question": "A Carnot heat engine receives energy E of heat per cycle from high temperature source T1 and rejects heat to a low-temperature sink T2. Determine the thermal efficiency and the amount of heat rejected to the sink per cycle.",
      "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nE=500 # Energy received (kJ)\nT1 = 652 # Temperature of heat source (degrees C)\nT2 = 30 # Temperature of sink (degrees C)\n\n# Carnot heat engine is reversible so efficiency(N) = 1-lowtemp/hightemp with temperature converted to kelvin\nN= 1-(T2+273)/(T1+273)\n\n# Amount of heat rejected by reversible process given by heatrejected=(lowtemp/hightemp)*heatreceived\nQl=((T2+273)/(T1+273))*E\n\nprint('Thermal efficiency:', N, ' Heat rejected to the sink:', Ql, 'kJ')\n      ",
      "explanation": "This code outputs both the thermal efficiency and the heat rejected to a sink of a reversible heat engine. The efficiency is calculated by  efficiency(N) = 1-lowtemp/hightemp with temperature converted to kelvin. The heat rejected is calculated by heatrejected=(lowtemp/hightemp)*heatreceived.",
      "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel (2007), Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
    },
    {
        "question": "Air flows smoothly past your face as you ride your bike, but bugs and particles or dust pelt your face and get into your eyes. Explain why this is so.",
        "answer": "\nThe airflow containing bugs and particles undergoes a swift direction change around the biker's face, but the particles heavier than air require greater force to change their state of motion (Newton's Second Law of motion). The air is not viscous enough to force the particles to follow it around the biker's head so the heavy particles collide with the head.\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "Q3.11, Page 150,Munson, B. R., Young, D. F., & Okiishi, T. H. Fundamentals of Fluid Mechanics."
        },
        {
        "question": "Air steadily expands adiabatically and without friction from stagnation conditions. Determine the velocity of the expanded air if Pressure at point 1 (P1),Pressure at point 2 (P2) and Temperature (T) is given assuming: (a) Incompressible Flow (b) Compressible Flow.",
        "answer": "\n\n# (a) When the flow is considered incompressible, the Bernoulli Equation, can be applied.\n# Bernoulli Equation: P2 + 1/2*ρ*((V_2)**2) = P1 + 1/2*ρ*((V_1)**2)\n# V_1 = 0, because it is coming from a stagnation condition\n# Density is constant as it is incompressible\n# To find density(ρ) we use idea gas fromula : ρ = P1/RT ;\n# After Algebra manipulation the formula will be\n\nprint('V_2 = sqrt((2(P2-P1))/ρ)')\n\n# (b) When the flow is considered compressible, and assuming it is a frictionless, ideal gas and steady pathline flow, we use the formula Bernouli's Principle: ((γ/γ-1)*(P2/ρ2) + ((V_2)^2/2) + (g*z_2) = ((γ/γ-1)*(P1/ρ1) + ((V_1)^2/2) + (g*z_1)\n# V_1 = 0, because it is coming from a stagnation condition\n# gz is negligible in the flow\n\n# To find density use the relationship: (P2/(ρ2)**γ) = (P1/(ρ1)**γ)\n#ρ2 = ρ1((P2/P1)**(1/γ))\n# After Algebric manipulation the SFEE formula will be:\n\nprint('V2 = sqrt(((2*γ)/(γ-1)) * ((P1/ρ1) - (P2/ρ2)))')\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
        },
        {
        "question": "For any ideal gas, prove that the slope of constant pressure lines on a temperature-entropy diagram is positive and that higher pressure lines are above lower pressure lines. Why is this important?",
        "answer": "\n# Using the Tds equation which is obtained by substituting for specific enthalpy\n# T * ds = dh - v * dp\n# Assuming that the pressure is constant the simplification leads to \n# T = dh/ds \n# Where temperature is equal to the change in enthalpy with respect to entropy, which is useful in analyzing ideal gas behavior under constant pressure conditions. \n# The change in enthalpy (dh) is expressed as  \n# dh=cp * dT, \n# Where cp is the specific heat at constant pressure.\n#  By dividing both sides by dT, we get  \n# dh/dT=cp \n# This equation shows that the rate of change of enthalpy with respect to temperature is equal to the specific heat at constant pressure (cp). Understanding this relationship is crucial for analyzing the energy changes in ideal gas systems, especially under constant pressure conditions.\n# Divide the equation to get: \n# (dh/ds)/(dh/dT) = T/cp \n# Showing the relationship between temperature change and entropy change. By analyzing this relationship, we can determine whether the change in temperature with respect to entropy is positive or negative in an ideal gas system under constant pressure conditions.\n\n# The ratio of temperature to specific heat ratio \n# T/cp > 0 #is always positive. \n\n# Since this ratio is positive, it implies that the ratio of temperature change to entropy change \n# dT/ds > 0  # is also positive.  \n\n# A positive dT/ds indicates that the slope for constant pressure lines on a temperature-entropy diagram is positive for any ideal gas.\n\n# The equation represents the relationship between pressures at two different states in an isentropic process.\n# P2/P1 = (T2/T1)**(γ/γ-1) \n# The equation helps demonstrate that higher temperatures lead to higher pressures in an isentropic process.\n\n# If we consider a process from point 1 with temperature  T1 ​ and point 2 with temperature T2, and: \n# T1 < T2.\n# According to the isentropic process equation, this temperature increase results in higher pressure at point 2 compared to point 1. Therefore, the assertion that higher pressure lines are above lower pressure lines is proven through the relationship between temperature and pressure changes in an isentropic process.\n# This relationship is essential because it highlights the direct connection between temperature and pressure variations during an isentropic process. It means that when the temperature from one state to the other increases, the pressure also increases. Understanding this relationship helps in analyzing and predicting the behavior of ideal gasses under conditions where entropy remains constant.\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
        },
        {
        "question": "How do various devices like heat engines, refrigerators, and heat pumps operate differently in utilizing heat for specific tasks, and what parameters are used to measure their effectiveness in their respective functions?",
        "answer": "\n Heat engines and heat pumps operate on the principle of utilizing heat to perform work. They absorb heat from a hot reservoir, typically at a higher temperature, and utilize a portion of it to generate work, while the remaining heat energy is expelled to a cold reservoir at a lower temperature. The efficiency of these devices, known as Thermal Efficiency(η = W/Q), quantifies how effectively they convert heat into useful work. This efficiency parameter is crucial in assessing the performance of a specific heat engine or heat pump. Refrigerators are essential household appliances designed to maintain a low temperature. They operate based on the principle of transferring heat. In essence, refrigerators absorb electrical energy as work and convert it into heat. Specifically, they extract heat from a cold reservoir, typically the interior of the fridge, and release this excess heat energy to a warmer reservoir, such as the surroundings. Therefore, evaluating the effectiveness of a refrigerator requires assessing a key parameter known as the Coefficient of Performance (β = Q/W).\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "Page 66,Moran, M. J., & Shapiro, H. N. (2010). Fundamentals of Engineering Thermodynamics."
        },
        {
        "question": "Explain how you could vary the Mach number but not the Reynolds number in airflow past a sphere.",
        "answer": "Given the formula of the Mach number M = V/(sqrt(γ*R*T) and Reynolds number formula is R = (ρ*V*D)/μ. We can seeBy decreasing the density of the flowing fluid in an inversely increase in flow velocity, we can elevate the Mach number while maintaining a constant Reynolds number.\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "Q11.19,pg773,Munson, B. R., Young, D. F., & Okiishi, T. H. Fundamentals of Fluid Mechanics."
        },
        {
        "question": "Assuming a fluid travels from left (station 1) to right (station 2), for each of the following features, please write down whether there is an increase in the Mach number (e.g., M1 < M2 or M1 > M2), stagnation temperature, static pressure, stagnation pressure and static temperature for heating and cooling subsonic Rayleigh Flow. If any further assumptions about the flow are required, please do make note of them.",
        "answer": " \n#For Heating:\n# M2 > M1\n# T0,2 > T0,1\n# P2 < P1\n# P0,2 < P0,1\n# T2 > T1 (for 0 <= M <= sqrt(1/γ) and T2 < T1 (for sqrt(1/γ) <= M <=1)\n\n#For Cooling:\n# M2 < M1\n# T0,2 < T0,1\n# P2 > P1\n# P0,2 > P0,1\n# T2 < T1 (for 0 <= M <= sqrt(1/γ) and T2 > T1 (for sqrt(1/γ) <= M <=1)\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "pg757,Munson, B. R., Young, D. F., & Okiishi, T. H. Fundamentals of Fluid Mechanics."
        },
        {
        "question": "Sketch a P-V diagram of an ideal gas executing a power cycle consisting of four internally reversible processes: isobaric,isochoric,isothermal,isentropic",
        "answer": " \nimport numpy as np\nimport matplotlib.pyplot as plt \n\n# isentropic\nP1 = np.array([10,15,20,25,30,35,40,45,50], dtype = 'int32')\nV1 = np.array([30,20,15,12,10,8,7.5,6.6,6.1], dtype = 'int32')\n\n# isochoric\nP2 = np.array([10,15,20,25,30,35,40,45,50], dtype = 'int32')\nV2 = np.array([6,6,6,6,6,6,6,6,6], dtype ='int32')\n\n# isobaric\nP3 = np.array([30,30,30,30,30,30,30,30,30], dtype = 'int32')\nV3 = np.array([30,20,15,12,10,8,7.5,6.6,6.1], dtype = 'int32')\n\n# isothermal\nP4 = np.array([30,32.5,35,37.5,40,42.5,45,49,50], dtype = 'int32')\nV4 = np.array([30,20,15,12,10,8,7.5,6.6,6.1], dtype = 'int32')\n\n\nplt.plot(V1, P1, label = 'isentropic', linestyle='-') \nplt.plot(V2, P2, label = 'isochoric', linestyle='--' ) \nplt.plot(V3, P3, label = 'isobaric') \nplt.plot(V4, P4, label = 'isothermal',linestyle='-.')\nplt.xlabel('Volume')\nplt.ylabel('Pressure')\nplt.title('Pressure-Volume Graph')\nplt.tick_params(left = False, right = False , labelleft = False, labelbottom = False, bottom = False)\nplt.legend()\nplt.show()\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
        },
        {
        "question": "Converging-Diverging Nozzle: Let the reservoir pressure be denoted by P0. The pressure drops to a quarter of the reservoir pressure at the throat. It is known that the cross-sectional area A2 is three times the cross-sectional area of the throat. Express the pressure at (2) in terms of the reservoir pressure. Assume incompressible, inviscid flow, and no body forces.",
        "answer": " \n# For the reservoir: P0\n# For the throat: P1 = (1/4)P0 and A1\n# For the Exit: A2 = (3)A1 and we are finding P2\n\n\n# Incompressible continutiy equation A2 * V2 = A1 * V1. Which gives us V2 = (1/3)V1\n# Applying the Bernoulli Equation when the flow is steady, inviscid, and incompressible: P + (1/2)ρV**2.\n\n# From the reservoir to the throat. The velocity at the reservoir is zero.\n# Formulating P0 = P1 + (1/2)ρ(V_1)**2. Which can be written as P0 = (1/4)P0 + (1/2)ρ(V_1)**2.\n# Solve for (V_1)**2 = (3/2)(P0/ρ)\n\n# From the throat to the Exit: P1 + (1/2)ρ(V_1)**2 = P2 + (1/2)ρ(V_2)**2\n# After substituting: (1/4)P0 + (1/2)*ρ*(3/2)*(P0/ρ) = P2 + (1/2)*ρ*((1/3)*sqrt((3/2)(P0/ρ)))**2\n# Simplifying: (1/4)P0 + (3/4)P0 = P2 + (1/12)P0\n# Rearranging: P2 = P0 - (1/12)P0\n# Answer: P2 = 11/12P0\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
        },
        {
        "question": "An inventor claims to have developed a device that undergoes a thermodynamic cycle while communicating thermally with two reservoirs. The system receives energy QC from the cold reservoir and discharges energy QH to the hot reservoir while delivering a net amount of work to its surroundings. There are no other energy transfers between the device and its surroundings. Evaluate the inventor's claim using (a) the Clausius statement of the second law, and (b) the Kelvin-Planck statement of the second law.",
        "answer": "\n# According to Clausius statement: It is impossible to construct a cyclic device whose sole effect is the transfer of heat from a cooler to a hotter body.\n# With the claims that the inventor has made, it supports Clausius Statement, because the device is transfering heat from a cold reservoir to a heat resrvoir while losing a net amount of work to the surroundings. \n\n# According to Kelvin-Planck Statement: It is impossible to construct a cyclic device whose sole effect is to produce positive work whilst receiving heat from a single thermal reservoir.\n# With the claims that the inventor has made, it does violate Kelvin-Planck statement because the device is taking in heat from the reservoir but is not converting to all postive work, instead it loses a net amount of work to its surrounding.\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "Q5.2, pg245,Moran, M. J., & Shapiro, H. N. (2010). Fundamentals of Engineering Thermodynamics."
        },
        {
        "question": "Inside, a crackling fire warms the room as the occupant prepares for the day ahead. Outside, the air is crisp as it flows steadily between two sections of the valley. At the inlet, where the sunlight peeks through the canopy, the air is warmed to 30°C and pressurized at 650 kPa. However, as it travels further down the valley, the temperature drops to a brisk 15°C, and the pressure diminishes to a mere 30 kPa at the outlet. Calculate the change in specific internal energy between the inlet and outlet, the change in the specific enthalpy between the inlet and outlet, the change in density between the inlet and outlet, and the change in specific entropy between the inlet and outlet. Would you expect compressibility effects to be important for this flow? State any major assumptions you make.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nT1 = 303.15 # Inlet Temperature (K)\nT2 = 288.15 # Outlet Temperature (K)\nP1 = 650 # Inlet Pressure (kPa)\nP2 = 30 # Outlet Pressure (kPa)\ncV = 717 # Heat Capacity (J/Kg*K)\ncP = 1004 # Heat Capacity(J/Kg*K)\nR = 287 # \n\n#a the change in specific internal energy between the inlet and outlet\nΔu = cV*(T2-T1) \n\nprint('Specific Internal Energy', Δu, 'J/Kg')\n\n#b the change in the specific enthalpy between the inlet and outlet\nΔh = cP * (T2-T1)\n\nprint('Specific Enthalpy', Δh, 'J/Kg')\n\n#c the change in density between the inlet and outlet\nΔρ = (P2 / (R*T2)) - (P1/(R*T1))\nprint('Change in Density',Δρ,'g/m**3')\n\n#d the change in specific entropy between the inlet and outlet.\nΔs = cP*np.log(T2/T1) - R*np.log(P2/P1)\nprint('Specific Entropy', Δs,'J/Kg')\n\n#e Would you expect compressibility effects to be important for this flow? State any major assumptions you make.\nρ = P1/(R*T1)\nCOMP = (Δρ/ρ) * 100 \nprint('Compressibility Effects lies as there is a great change in density', COMP,'%')\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
        },
        {
        "question": "A mass of 10 kg of ice at -10°C is added to 250 kg of hot coffee at 95°C. Both the ice and coffee are at the ambient pressure of 1 atm. What is the eventual temperature of the mixture? Assume that the container is well insulated and that the thermodynamic properties of the hot coffee are approximately the same as those for pure water.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nm_i = 10 # mass of ice (kg)\nT_i = -10 # temperature of ice (°C)\nh_i = -354 # specfic enthalpy of ice (KJ/Kg)\nm_c = 250 # mass of coffee (Kg)\nT_c = 95 # temperature of coffee(°C)\nh_c = 398 # specfic enthalpy of coffee (KJ/Kg)\nc_P = 4.2 # specfic heat at constant pressure (KJ/Kg*K) \n\n# Assuming that the system is well insulated and reading the description we see it is a hetergenous since it has discrete parts that are intially in different states of equilibrium.\n# Using the Steady Flow Energy Equation: Q - W = ΣU*PE*KE. There is no flow in the experiment, we can form the equation by cancelling KE and PE: Q - W = ΣU\n# We can subsititue W = pΔV. Q = (U2 + PV2) - (U1 + PV1). or Q = H2 - H1\n# The container is well insulated so Q = 0\n# Hence forming the equation H2 = H1, presenting that the final state the system becomes homogenous\n\n# Enthalpy at intial state \nH1 = (m_i * h_i) + (m_c * h_c)\n                 \n# total mass of the system\nm_s = m_i + m_c\n                 \n# Specfic enthalpy at final state\nh2 = H1 / m_s\n\n# Answer: final temperature of the mixture\nT2 = round(h2/c_P,1)\n\nprint('Temperature of the mixture',T2,'°C')\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
        },
        {
        "question": "Suppose an engineer devices a theoretical device that utilizes a flow of 15 kg/s of high-pressure steam at 200°C and 1 atm pressure to produce a mechanical shaft power output of 600 kW. After processing, the steam exits the device at 1 atm pressure and 50°C. The device continuously dissipates heat to the surrounding ambient air, which is at 30°C. Based on this information, assess the proposed device's practical implementation. (h_i = 632 KJ/Kg, h_e = 209 KJ/Kg, s_i = 1.842 KJ/Kg*K, s_e = 0.703 KJ/Kg*K)",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nP_i =1 #atm\nP_e = 1 #atm\nT_i = 423 # K\nT_e = 323 #K\nT_surr = 303 # K\nm_dot = 15 #Kg/s\nW = 600 #KW\nh_i = 632 #KJ/Kg\nh_e = 209 #KJ/Kg\ns_i = 1.842 #KJ/Kg*K\ns_e = 0.703 #KJ/Kg*K\n\n# Using the SFEE equation, where the KE and PE be negliable. -Q - W = m_dot(h_e - h_i). Do remeber the heat is transfer from the system, hence negative.\n\nQ = (m_dot*(h_i - h_e)) - W\n\n      # As we have the heat transfer using the dS = dQ/T + dS_irr\n\ndS_irr = round(m_dot*(s_e - s_i) + (Q/T_surr),3)\n\nprint('dS_irr',dS_irr,'KJ/K*s')\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "PG288,Russell, L. D., & Adebiyi, G. A. (1993). Classical thermodynamics. Suanders College Publishing."
        },
        {
        "question": "A supersonic airplane is flying at Mach 2 at an altitude of 16 km. Assume the shock wave pattern from the airplane quickly coalesces into a Mach wave that intersects the ground behind the airplane, causing a “sonic boom” to be heard by a bystander on the ground. At the instant the sonic boom is heard, how far ahead of the bystander is the airplane?",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\n# Note: It is easier visualize by making a free body diagram for this question.\n# Since the airplane is in supersonic state a Mach can be generated at the tip of the airplane.\n\ny = 16,000 # (m)\nM = 2 \n# x - horizontal distance\n\n# Using trig, we reach this formula: μ = tan(y/x).\n\n# Mach Angle : μ = (sin**(-1))(1/M) = tan(y/x)\n# The mu are same (note using Alternating angles we will see it matches)\n# With Algebric manipulation the formula will be\n\nx = y/(np.tan(np.arcsin(1/M)))\n\nprint('Bystander's Position', x[0],'Km')\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference":""
        },
        {
        "question": "Steam enters a convergin-diverging nozzle operating at steady state with P1 = 4 MPa. T1 = 500°C, and a velocity of 10 m/s. The steam flows through the nozzle with negligible heat transfer and no significant change in potential energy. At the exit, P2 = 15 bar, and the velocity is 665 m/s. The mass flow rate is 2 kg/s. Determine the exit area of the nozzle.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\n\nP1 = 4 # MPa\nT1 = 500 # °C\nh1 = 3445.3 # KJ/Kg\nV1 = 10 # m/s\nP2 = 1.5 # MPa\nm_dot = 2 # Kg/s\nν2 = 0.1627 # m^3/Kg\nV2 = 665 # m/s\n\n# Using the SFEE equation: Q - W = m_dot((h1-h2) + ((((V1)**2)-(V2)**2)/2) + g(z1-z2)\n# Neglected potiential energy and heat transfer and work is negliable.\n\nh2 = h1 + ((((V1)**2)-(V2)**2)/2)\n\n# The exit area can be determined from the mass flow rate.\n\nA2 = ((m_dot)*(ν2))/V2\n\nprint('Exit Area', A2, 'm^2')\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "Russell, L. D., & Adebiyi, G. A. (1993). Classical thermodynamics. Suanders College Publishing."
        },
        {
        "question": "Air flows steadily between two cross sections in a long, straight section of 0.25 m inside-diameter pipe. The static temperature at section 1 is 300K and static pressure at section 1 690 KPa(abs) and the static temperature at section 2 is 252K and static pressure at section 2 127 KPa(abs) If the average air velocity at section is 320 m/s, determine the average air velocity at section(1).",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np  \n\nP1 = 690 # KPa(abs)\nP2 = 127 # KPa(abs)\nT1 = 300 # K\nT2 = 252 # K\nV2 = 320 # m/s\nD = 0.25 # m\n\n# Using mass flow rates m_dot1 = m_dot2 can equal ρ1*A1*V1 = ρ2*A2*V2\n# As the diameter in the control volume A2 = A1\n# To find V1 = (ρ2/ρ1)*V2\n\n# Using  Ideal gas Law: P =ρRT, we get ρ = P/(RT)\n# Finalizing the equation to:\n\nV1 = (P2*T1*V2)/(P1*T2)\n\nprint('Average air velocity',V1,'m/s')\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "Q5.4,pg288,Munson, B. R., Young, D. F., & Okiishi, T. H. Fundamentals of Fluid Mechanics."
        },
        {
        "question":"The Pitot tube on a supersonic aircraft cruising at an altitude of 30,000 ft senses a stagnation pressure of 12 psia. If the atmosphere is considered standard, determine the airspeed and Mach number of the aircraft. A shock wave is present just upstream of the probe impact hole. [Static Pressure = 4.633 psia, Gas constant = 1.716*10**3, γ = 1.4, static temperature = 412.17 R]  ]",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np \n\nP = 4.633 #psia\nP0 = 12 # psia\nH = 30000 # ft\nR = 1.716*10**3 # ftlb/lb*R\nγ = 1.4 \nT = 412.17 # R\n# Having the static pressure and stagnation pressure, we use that to find the Mach number.\nratio = P/P0\n\n# Using the Normal Shock table, the ratio of P/P0 is when Mach number is 1.25\nM = 1.25\nprint('M =',1.25)\n\n# To find the speed of the aircraft, find the speed of sound\na = np.sqrt(γ*R*T)\n\n# Use the formula Mach number M = V/a\n\nV = round(M*a, -1)\n\nprint('speed of the aircraft',V,'ft/s')\n",
        "explanation":"",
        "reference": "Q11.70,pg776,Munson, B. R., Young, D. F., & Okiishi, T. H. Fundamentals of Fluid Mechanics."
        },
        {
            "question": "Why is the pressure the same at all depths of a connected (barrierless) fluid, regardless of shape?",
            "answer": "To answer this question, we can look at the general equation for pressure in a fluid: p = rgh + pa, where r represents density, g represents gravity, and h represents the depth we are measuring. pa is atmospheric pressure, which will be the same across all points, so it can be ignored. As for rgh, we can see that this value only ever changes depending on the height and density of the fluid. In a connected fluid, the density will be the same at all points, therefore if we establish h to be the same at all points, they will return the same total pressure, regardless of the shape of the fluid.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "What does it mean for a process to be 'quasi - equilibrium', and why is this statement so important to applying thermodynamic relations to fluids?",
            "answer": "A process can be called 'quasi - equilibrium' if the rate of change of the process is extremely large compared to the time it takes for a system to reach thermodynamic equilibrium. This statement holds value when applying thermodynamic relations, as it allows us to be sure that only one 'state' of a system exists at a single point in time. Many thermodynamic relations directly affect the state of a system, so being sure that there is only one option is integral to applying these relations confidently.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "Can a fluid going through an isochoric process have work done on it or do work?",
            "answer": "An isochoric process is one where the volume of the fluid being studied is kept constant. We can assume shaft work is zero and use the definition of pressure to define the relation between work (W) and volume (V). Pressure (p) is equal to Force (F) over Area (A). Therefore, F = pA. Since W is equal to F along an infinitesimal distance (dx), and pressure always acts normal to a surface, we can get W = pAdx. Adx is equal to dV, or the change in volume. Therefore W = pdV. Since an isochoric process means that dV is 0, that means W must be 0, and work cannot be created from an isochoric process.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "What does it mean for a process to be 'path-dependent'? Which terms of the first Law of Thermodynamics are path-dependent? ",
            "answer": "Path dependency means that the method (path) by which a system is taken from one state to another affects the end state of the system. The first law of thermodynamics can be defined as follows: Q = W + dU. Work is path dependent because it can be thought of as the area under a Pressure - Volume graph. Multiple lines can be taken between any two points (states), and the area under their curves can be drastically different. The internal energy of a system depends on state variables, i.e. the change in energy is only defined by the values of the initial and final state, not the path between the two. Since Q is in part defined by a path-dependent variable (W) , it is also logical to conclude that Q is a path-dependent variable, which it is.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "If a system is taken to a Pressure-Volume (pV) curve by stirring at a constant volume and reversibly compressing or expanding, can it be adiabatically taken off that curve?",
            "answer": "An adiabatic process is one where no heat is extracted or added to the system from the surroundings. When a fluid system is stirred, this is the same as adding work to a system. Using the first Law of Thermodynamics we know that since Q = W + dU, therefore in this scenario, Q must increase. In order to leave this new state then, heat must taken out, as the work cannot be removed by 'unstirring', however this isn't possible in an adiabatic process, where heat cannot be added or removed. Therefore a system cannot be adiabatically shifted off a pV curve.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "Explain why an Adiabatic and Reversible process must be Isentropic?",
            "answer": "For this, lets take a look at the fundamental differential equation for entropy: ds = dQ/T + ds(irreversible). For an irreversible process, ds(irreversible) goes to zero, as no irreversible entropy is generated. In an adiabatic process, no heat is transfered, so dQ is also zero. Plugging these values into the differential equation, we can see that ds will be 0, or there will be no change in entropy, which is what characterizes an isentropic equation. Therefore, a reversible and adiabatic process must be isentropic.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "At the exit of a nozzle, the static pressure is 5.28 kPa, while at the entrace, the stagnation pressure is 10.00 kPa. Would decreasing the pressure at the exit increase the mass flow rate?",
            "answer": "No. This is because the ratio of static pressure to stagnation pressure is 0.528. At this ratio, the flow is choked, meaning that further decreasing the exit static pressure would not increase the mass flow rate through the nozzle.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "What happens to static temperature, static pressure, and density across a shock and why?",
            "answer": "Static temperature, static pressure, and density all increase almost instantaneously across a shock. This is because shocks are created by objects moving faster than the speed of sound, i.e. the speed at which fluid blobs can communicate and react to changes in the environment. Because of this, the variations cause a high pressure shock wave to build up and release in a very short amount of time.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "What is the difference between supersonic and subsonic Fanno flow in a piper with friction? Why does this occure?",
            "answer": "In a pipe with friction, supersonic flow starts decreasing in speed, while subsonic flow increases in speed. This occurs because Fanno flow always increases in entropy. For a supersonic flow, this is shown by the Mach number decreasing until the flow is choked. Conversely subsonic flow increases in Mach number until the flow is choked.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "A rectangular window of height 4m and unknown width is used to seal up a tank of water. The top of the window is 3m deep in the tank. What is the ratio of the the total force due to pressure on the bottom half of the window over the top half?",
            "answer": "\n            h = 4  # height of window\n            i = 3  # depth of top of window\n            h1 = h/2  # height of each of the two pieces of window after being split in half\n            i1 = i + h1  # depth of top of lower half of window\n            F1 = h1 * h1 * (i + (h1/2))  # top half force, equation found by solving out integral in the explanation\n            F2 = h1 * h1 * (i1 + (h1/2))  # bottom half force\n            ratio = F2/F1  # ratio of bottom half force to top half force\n            print('The ratio of force on the bottom half of window over the top half of window is:', ratio)\n            ",
            "explanation": "In order to figure out the ratio, we can split the window into two separate windows and calculate the force on them equally. The force of pressure on a window can be found by the summation of force on all small sections of the window. For a single window, this can be shown by rgh times the integral of z dz along the path from i to i + h, where r is the density, g is gravity, i is the depth of the top of the window, and h is the height of the window. r and g can be ignored because they are constants and will divide out in the ratio regardless.",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "An aircraft moving at Mach 3 with an atmospheric temperature of 217K. What is the stagnation temperature of the flow of air at the inlet of the engine?",
            "answer": "\n            M = 3  # Mach Number\n            y = 1.4  # Gamma value for air\n            T = 217  # Atmospheric Temperature\n            ratio = 1 + (y-1)/2 * (M**2)\n            print('The stagnation temperature at the inlet of engine flow is:', round(T * ratio,3))\n            ",
            "explanation": "This can be solved using the equation T0/T = 1 + (y-1)M^2/2, where T0 is the stagnation temperature, M is the mach number, and y is the ratio of cp/cv for the fluid, where in this case it can be assumed as 1.4 for air.",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "Water is flowing into a tank with an area of 3 m^2 and an inlet velocity of 10 m/s, and an outlet area of 2 m^2 and an outlet velocity of 5 m/s. What is the rate of mass accumulation in the tank?",
            "answer": "\n            Ain = 3  # Area of inlet pipe\n            Vin = 10  # Velocity of inlet flow\n            Aout = 2  # Area of outlet pipe\n            Vout = 5  # Velocity of outlet flow\n            p = 1000  # Density of water\n            mIN = p * Ain * Vin  # Massflow rate in\n            mOUT = p * Aout * Vout  # Massflow rate out\n            mA = mIN - mOUT  # Mass accumulation\n            print('The mass accumulation rate is:', mA,'kg/s')\n            ",
            "explanation": "We can use the equation mf = pAv for both the inflow and the outflow, and then we can subtract the outflow from the inflow to find the mass accumulation in the tank. We can assume p is 1000 kg/m^3",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "1000 kJ of energy is added to 2m^3 of air at a pressure of 10 bar. The temperature of the system is 100K, and the specific heat at constant volume is 0.74 kJ/(kgK). What is the change in temperature of the system?",
            "answer": "\n            import numpy as np\n            cv = 0.74  # specific heat at constant volume\n            Q = 1000  # Added heat\n            V = 2  # Volume of air\n            T = 100  # Temperature in Kelvin\n            p = 10  # Pressure\n            R = 287  # Constant\n            m = (p * (10**5) * V/(R * T))  # mass from ideal gas law\n            dT = Q/(m * cv) # change in temperature\n            print('The change in temperature is: ', round(dT,3),'K')\n            ",
            "explanation": "First, we use pV = mRT to find the mass of the air in the system. Then we use the Q - W = dU, and set du equal to mcvdT and solve for dT",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "At mach 1.050, a skin friction coefficient of 0.05, and a diameter of 2m, what length of pipe is needed to choke a viscous flow?",
            "answer": "\n            cf = 0.05  # skin frction coefficient\n            D = 2  # Diameter of pipe\n            Val = 0.0027  # value of 4cfL/D for mach 1.050\n            L = Val * D/(4 * cf)  # length to chock pipe\n            print('The length of pipe needed to choke the flow would be:', L,'m')\n            ",
            "explanation": "We can use the supersonice mach relation tables to find the value of 4cfL/D. This is 0.0027, we can use this to solve for L.",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "A system extracts heat from a heat source at 1000K and the atmosphere at 200K in order to deliver 13kW of energy to a building at 500K. What rate is the heat being extracted from the heat source?",
            "answer": "\n            T1 = 1000  # Temperature of source 1\n            T2 = 200  # Temperature of source 2\n            T3 = 500  # Temperature of source 3\n            Q3 = 13  # Rate of heat transfer\n            ratio = (1/T2 - 1/T1)/(1/T2 - 1/T3)  # ratio of Q3/Q1\n            print('The rate of heat extraction from the heat source is:', round(Q3/ratio,3),'kW')\n            ",
            "explanation": "We can use the Clausius inequality to solve for Q1 in Q1 + Q2 = Q3, and Q1/T1 + Q2/T2 - Q3/T3 <= 0. By doing some algebra on these equations, we can set Q2 = Q3 - Q1 and solve for the ratio of Q3/Q1 and then divide the value of Q3 to get Q1.",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "Water is flowing through a tube with an area of π/4m^2 at a rate of 2m^3/s and a pressure of 80 kPa. What is the pressure after the area becomes π/16 m^2?",
            "answer": "\n            import numpy as np\n            vF = 2 # Volumetric flow rate\n            p = np.pi # pi\n            Ain = p/4 # Area of inlet\n            Aout = p/16 # Area of second point\n            pIn = 80 # Pressure of inlet\n            v1 = vF/Ain # Velocity at point one\n            v2 = vF/Aout # Velocity at point two\n            p2 = (80 * 1000) + (0.5 * 1000 * ((v1**2) - (v2**2))) # Pressure at point two\n            print('The pressure at the second point is:', round(p2/1000,3),'kPa')\n            ",
            "explanation": "Use bernoulli's equation, assuming a steady, incompressible, and inviscid flow as it is not mentioned. the rgz component can also be neglected as no change in height is mentioned. First, use the volumetric flow rate to find the velocity at both points by dividing by area. Then, simply solve for the constant at the initial point and use the value to find the pressure at the second point. ",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "How is it that incompressible flow can have a non-uniform velocity profile and why do we evaluate mass flow rate differently compared to a constant profile?",
            "answer": "Fluid flow near walls wants to 'grip' the wall due to the friction of the pipe and the viscosity of the fluid, this is the internal resistance of a fluid to flow. The velocity of the flow near the walls will be less than the flow further away from the walls, this is known as Poiseuille flow. To evaluate flow with gradients you must integrate with area. If we induce a tangential force at the top of the flow, the molecules need to accommodate this displacement through momentum exchange. This is Couette flow and is evaluated the same.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference": "https://www.lehman.edu/faculty/anchordoqui/chapter28.pdf , page: 28-5"
           },
           {
            "question": "Is Bernoulli's equation a statement on the conservation of momentum and does that mean it is related to Newton's second law?",
            "answer": "Bernoulli's equation implies that when focusing on the forces on the streamline we can apply Newton's 2nd law. The conservation of Momentum is also derived from Newton's 2nd law. It is important to understand that Bernoulli's equation is only valid along streamlines and can be used for problems related to momentum if they are connected by streamlines following the conditions stated earlier. Understanding its assumptions will differentiate its applicability. However, Bernoulli's equation is more closely a statement on energy conservation: energy of a fluid remains constant along a streamline.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference": "https://www.grc.nasa.gov/www/k-12/VirtualAero/BottleRocket/airplane/bernnew.html"
           },
           {
            "question": "How does one go about calculating stagnation pressure within a flow that has a specific inlet velocity?",
            "answer": "Stagnation pressure is the reading when the flow is impeded and has a stagnation point. This is most commonly recorded with a pitot-static tube and In incompressible flow, the stagnation pressure can be read as the static pressure plus the dynamic pressure. Impeding sonic flow will develop shocks, which will cause a drop in stagnation pressure that is read vs what that value is. Utilizing isentropic relations can yield results pre and post-shock, but this utilizes the Rayleigh pitot tube formula and is only valid when Mach is greater than 1."
           },
           {
            "question": "If a heat engine is at maximum efficiency when it is cyclic, does that mean it is also in quasi-equilibrium?",
            "answer": "A heat engine is only at maximum efficiency when it is reversible and cyclic. This is an idealized process meaning that in practice this cannot be achieved. Quasi-Equilibirum refers to a process that occurs slowly and remains infinitesimally close to an equilibrium state at all times. If a heat engine is utilizing maximum efficiency, which means it is reversible, does not mean quasi-equilibrium because a reversible process must be carried out in a way to avoid creating entropy.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference": "https://bingweb.binghamton.edu/~suzuki/ThermoStatFIles/1.5%20Review%203%20%20Phys.131%20Entropy%20Carnot%20cycle.pdf, page 7"
           },
           {
            "question": "How can one consider a steady flow process, what are the analytical steps and equations used to determine this?",
            "answer": "Whether steady conditions are valid depends on how the flow crosses that control volume. It is important to draw a control volume that makes calculating the flow easiest to determine kinetic and potential components. After taking these steps it is important to recognize that steady flow processes are understood as there is no accumulation of energy or depletion of mass, meaning that conservation is at play: steady flow mass continuity, steady flow momentum equations, and steady flow energy equations constitute the steady flow conservation equations.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
           },
           {
            "question": "How is it that choked flow has a peak mass flow rate value regardless of how much you raise the pressure differential, will anything else happen to the flow otherwise?",
            "answer": "Choked flow occurs when the Mach number at the throat reaches 1, and once the flow is choked any changes to the pressure differential will not increase the mass flow rate through the throat. This is because the flow velocity at the throat won't exceed the speed of sound. However, decreasing the exit pressure downstream of the throat will shift the position of the shock further downstream of your nozzle or pipe. This will alter your stagnation and static values at specific points within your flow.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
           },
           {
            "question": "If flow through a variable nozzle has an inlet velocity that is subsonic, how can the flow post throat be supersonic or subsonic and what conditions would need to be applicable?",
            "answer": "We assume that flow is choked at the throat and friction can be ignored, we can utilize isentropic relations to find the mach number downstream of the throat. The concept being discussed is when the area ratios can result in the possibility of super-sonic and sub-sonic solutions. This would need to be calculated given a specific problem. If flow entering the diverging section is subsonic, the static pressure will begin to rise to match the exit static pressure. The opposite holds for flow entering the diverging duct that is supersonic. If a shock forms the static pressure post-shock will rise to match the exit static pressure, this is done isentropically.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
           },
           {
            "question": "Explain how expansion fans are isentropic processes while shocks are entropic processes and the consequences given that both are results of compressible flow?",
            "answer": "Entropy is a thermodynamic property defined as: 'the inability of a 'system's thermal energy to yield useful mechanical work'. For shocks, there can be normal shocks, oblique shocks, or bow shocks which is what happens when the impeding angle is greater than the maximum turning angle. In all three of these situations, they are entropic processes and have similar consequences. However, expansion fans, are adiabatic and reversible due to the isentropic property of the flow, meaning they are isentropic: constant entropy throughout the expansion fan. This creates different relations across the fan that are seemingly opposite of those compared to a shock.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference": "https://www.grc.nasa.gov/www/k-12/airplane/expans.html"
           },
           {
            "question": "If I had a variable nozzle with significant friction, an inlet subsonic velocity, and made the throat of the nozzle long enough such that Fanno-Flow took effect, what would happen to the mach number downstream of this long throat?",
            "answer": " What would happen is if you had a case where the flow entering this pipe was subsonic, friction would reduce the area and velocity would begin to rise in the pipe eventually hitting what is called the choking condition, flow reaching the choking condition would experience drops in static temperature and pressure. If the flow entering the pipe is sonic, friction reduces the area and velocity will drop down to the choking condition. The flow will begin to experience increases in static temperature and pressure. It is important to note that in the case of Fanno flow, flow cannot surpass the choking condition.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
           },
           {
               "question" : " A jet engine with an inlet diameter of 8m is operating at sea level. The Ambient air pressure is 101.325kPa, and the Ambient air temperature is 15 C. The jet engine is able to pull in air with a velocity of 100 m/s and reads a temperature of 400k at the exit. The exit diameter is a quarter of the inlet diameter. Assuming the flow is adiabatic and reversible, calculate the velocity at the exit of the jet engine, and the specific work this engine produces. Assuming changes in potential energy are negligible. Assume a cp value of 1.006 kj/(kg . K). ",
               "answer" : "\nimport numpy as np\n\npi = 3.141592653589793\nv1 = 100  # Velocity (m/s)\nP1 = 101.325  # Pressure (kPa)\nT1 = (15 + 273.15)  # Temperature (K)\nD1 = 8  # Diameter (m)\nD2 = (D1) / 4  # Diameter2 (m)\nT2 = 400  # Temperature2 (K)\nCp = 1.006  # Specific Heat Capacity (kJ/(kg . K))\nGamma = 1.4  # Gamma for air\n\n# We have the required values to find density at the inlet and recognizing the flow is isentropic we can find density at the exit.\nrho1 = P1 / ((Cp - (Cp / Gamma)) * T1)\nP2 = ((T2 / T1) ** (Gamma / (Gamma - 1))) * P1\nrho2 = P2 / ((Cp - (Cp / Gamma)) * T2)\n\n# Apply continuity utilizing area calculations\nA1 = pi * (D1 ** 2) * .25\nA2 = pi * (D2 ** 2) * .25\nV2 = (rho1 * A1 * v1) / (A2 * rho2)\n\n# Utilize steady flow energy equation disregarding potential\nsWork = -((Cp * (T2 - T1)) + ((V2 ** 2 - v1 ** 2) / 2))\n\nprint('The specific work done is', sWork, 'kW, note the negative implying work is done onto the system, and the exit velocity is ', V2, 'm/s.')\n     ",
               "explanation": "This code utilizes ideal gas law and continuity to calculate the SFEE in order to find the work that is done at the system and to calculate the velocity at the exit.",
               "reference":""
           },
           {
               "question" : "Air flows through a pipe at M = 1.25. The diameter of the pipe is 6m and at some length in the pipe, a shock forms and the exit static reads 75k with a skin coefficient of .002. The stagnation temperature is 100k and the Stagnation pressure is 125kPa at the inlet. What is the exit stagnation pressure to inlet stagnation pressure, the exit static temp to inlet static temp? At what length in the pipe are these values read, What is the impulse relative to the stagnation pressure at exit?",
               "answer" : "\nimport numpy as np\n\npi = 3.141592653589793\nM1 = 1.25\nT0 = 100 # Stagnation Temperature (k)\nP0 = 125 # Stagnation Pressure (kPa)\nD = 6  # Diameter (m)\ncf = .002 # skin friction coefficient\nPe = 75 # Exit static pressure (kPa)\nnonDimFlow1 = 1.2238 # value in gas table\n\n#Utilizing gas table, find non-dim flow rate at inlet related to stagnation pressure and calculate it such to get non-dim related to exit pressure, this will give us our downstream mach value)\nnonDimFlow2 = (nonDimFlow1 * (P0/Pe))\nfriction1 = 0.0486\n\n#Looking at gas tables we find that this flow rate is at mach 0.860, now we can calculate stagnation values\nP0e = (Pe/0.6170)\nTe = (T0 * .8711)\nfriction2 = 0.0310\n\n#next utilizing the friction expressions at the different values and solving for Lmax will allow us to yield the length\nfrictionM = friction1 - friction2\nLmax = (frictionM * 6)/(4 * cf)\n\n#For impulse look back at gas property table at exit and utilize manipulation to get F/P0e)\nA = pi * (D ** 2) * .25\nimpulseP = .9979 * nonDimFlow2 * ((Pe * A) / P0e)\n\nprint('The Impulse ratio is,', impulseP, 'and the length of the pipe is,', Lmax,'m.')\n        ",
               "explanation": "This code utilizes the gas property tables and expects you to be able to pull the correct values, from there it calculates length of the pipe utilizing Lmax which is L1 ratio - L2 and through manipulation get Impulse over pressure",
               "reference": "Brian J. Cantwell Fundamentals of Compressible Flow , pages: 283-284"
           },
           {
               "question": "A rocket with a solid motor is flying through the air at 165 m/s, it has a static pressure of 380kPa at the exit and ejects the propellant out at 200m/s.  The solid rocket motor burns right at the exit of the motor casing and the temperature at the exit is 550K. The volumetric flow rate is 115 m^3/s and the ambient pressure at this level is 75kPa. Find the thrust this rocket produces and the specific impulse. Assume a gamma of 1.4 and a Cv of 1.3 kJ/(kg.K) for the gas expelled from the motor and assume this gas acts like a perfect gas.",
               "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nvFlow = 115 # Volumetric flow rate (m^3/s)\nPe = 380 # Exit Pressure (kPa)\nTe = 550 # Exit Temperature (K)\nPa = 75 # Ambient Pressure (kPa)\nvPropellant = 200 # Velocity of propellant (m/s)\ngammaGas = 1.4\ncvGas = 1.3 # heat capacity at constant volume kJ/(kg.K)\n\n#utilizing steady flow momentum, we can calculate for thrust, but we need density of the propellant at the exit.\ncpGas = cvGas * gammaGas\nRgas = cpGas - cvGas\nrhoe = (Pe/(Rgas * Te)) #density of propellant exiting\nAe = vFlow/vPropellant #area of motor casing\nmachGas = vPropellant/((gammaGas * Rgas* Te)**.5)\n\n#utilizing gas table we can find impulse expressions and flow rate expressions to manipulate ratios)\nThrust = 1.1903 * 1.1341 * Ae * Pe - (Ae*Pa)\nT0e = Te / .9524\nImpulse = 1.1903 * vFlow * rhoe * ((cpGas * T0e)**.5)\n\nprint('The thrust of the motor is,', Thrust, 'kN and the specific impulse is', Impulse,'kN.s/kg .')       \n        ",
               "explanation": "This code utilizes the fact there are no inlet components to the solid rocket motor and only considers the exit. It uses Steady Flow energy with thrust and impulse in order to calculate thrust. From there it gets exit mach to find impulse at exit.",
               "reference": "Moran, M. J., et. al., 2014, Fundamentals of Engineering Thermodynamics, 8th ed., Wiley, Hoboken, NJ , question 13.37 , page 673" 
           },
           {
               "question": "Flow is fully released for only .1 seconds and enters a pipe at 300 m/s with a temperature of 300K and the flow is strictly driven by a pressure gradient where downstream pressure is 1 bar and upstream pressure is 8 bar. The area at the inlet is half of the area at the exit. Note that the cp value is 2.5, The gamma of this gas is 1.67. and this gas acts like a perfect gas assuming the flow is incompressible. Does the system have backflow, if so calculate the specifc work required to go against the gradient. Ignore changes in potential",
               "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nVin = 300 # Velocity inlet (m/s)\nTin = 300 # Temperature inlet (K)\nPin = 8*(10**2) # Pressure inlet (kPa)\nPout = 1*(10**2) # Pressure outlet (kPa)\ncp = 2.5 # Heat capacity at constant pressure (kJ/(kg.K))\ngamma = 1.67\nAin = 0.5 # Area (m^2)\nAexit = 1 # Area (m^2)\n\n#understanding we have flow that is compressible we must calculate density utilizing continuity\ncv = cp/gamma # Heat capacity at constant volume\nR = cp - cv #gas constant (kJ/(kg.K))\nrho = (Pin/(R*Tin))\nmDot = rho * Ain * Vin\nVout = (Ain/Aexit) * Vin\n\n#To calculate for back flow we must utilize the change in entropy equation and calculate if change is entropy due to irreversibilities is negative\nTexit = (Pout * Tin)/Pin\ndSirrev = (cp * np.log(Texit/Tin)) - (R * np.log(Pout/Pin))\n\n#Since the flow is going backwards that must mean work is being done onto the system to go against the pressure differential\nspecificWork = (cp * (Texit-Tin)) + (0.5 * (Vout**2 - Vin**2))\n\nprint ('the change in irreversibilities is:', dSirrev, 'kj/kg.k meaning that flow is going agaisnt the gradient, the specific work to perform this is:', specificWork, 'kw.s/kg')\n        ",
               "explanation": "This code is utilizing the relations of change in entropy in order to determine the work required to find how there is flow opposite to the pressure gradient, a lot of algebraic manipulation is involved.",
               "reference":""
           },
           {
               "question": "A new system that utilizes compression that is adiabatic and reversible is to decrease the density of gas. The gas has a cv value of .73 and an R-value of .450, the inlet static temperatures are 300k and static pressures are 105kPa, however, it takes in gas rapidly at 225 m/s and reads 350k at the exit. The device relies on changes in height from the inlet to the exit of 0.25 with an inlet height of 1m and the density at the inlet is 1.75 kg/m^3. Calculate the work done, as well as static, pressure, and density ratios of exit to inlet.",
               "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nrho1 = 1.75 # Density (kg/m^3)\nT1 = 300 # Temperature inlet (K)\nT2 = 350 # Temperature exit (K)\nP1 = 105 # Pressure inlet (kPa)\nV1 = 225 # Velocity inlet (m/s)\ncv = .73 # Heat capacity at constant volume (kJ/(kg.K))\nR = 0.450 # gas constant (kJ/(kg.K))\n\n#using continuity we must find the mass flow rate, then using isentropic relations find rho 2 and from continuity find v2\ncp = cv + R # heat capacity at constant pressure (kJ/(kg.K))\ngamma = cp/cv\nA1 = 1 # height in meters\nA2 = 4 * A1 # height in meters\nmdot = rho1 * A1 * V1\nP2 = ((T2/T1)**(gamma/(gamma-1))) * P1\nrho2 = P2/(R * T2)\nV2 = mdot /(A2 * rho2)\n\n#calculate static ratios\nrhoRatio = rho2/rho1\npressureRatio = P2/P1\n\n#calculate work using SFEE accounting for kinetic and potential\nwork = mdot * ((cp * (T2-T1)) + (0.5 * (V2**2 + V1**2)) + 9.81 * (A2 - A1))\nmWork = work/1000\nprint('The work done by the system is,',mWork,'Megawatts (MW). The density ratio is:', rhoRatio, 'and pressure ratio is:', pressureRatio)\n        ",
               "explanation": "This code calculates the work done on the system utilizing the potential and kinetic components, it also uses isentropic relations in order to find the static ratios of exit and inlet.",
               "reference": "Moran, M. J., et. al., 2014, Fundamentals of Engineering Thermodynamics, 8th ed., Wiley, Hoboken, NJ , question 4.24 , page 166"
           },
           {
               "question": "Air enters pipe 1 uniformly at 25m/s and at 45 degrees relative to the control surface of the pipe. Pipe 1 has a diameter of 0.5 meters and is connected to pipe 2 which has a diameter of 0.3m. As the flow goes through pipe 1 it holds a static pressure value of 100kPa and temperature of 175k throughout the whole flow, but as it enters pipe 2 it now has a parabolic profile expressed as V2(1+(r)^2) where r is the radius. These pipes are not orthogonal to each other and are at an additional angle of 20 degrees. What is the velocity exiting pipe 2 and the momentum flux components only through pipe 2?",
               "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\npi = 3.141592653589793\nV1 = 25 # Velocity inlet (m/s)\nD1 = 0.5 # diameter of pipe 1 (m)\nD2 = 0.3 # diameter of pipe 2 (m)\nP1 = 100 # pressure inlet (kPa)\nT1 = 175 # temperature inlet (K)\nR = .287 # gas constant for air (kJ/(kg.K))\n\n#Calculate mass flow rate in the x direction\nvtheta1 = V1 * .707106      # velocity normal to surface of pipe 1\nrho = P1/(R * T1)\nA1 =  pi * (D1 ** 2) * .25\nmdot = rho * A1 * vtheta1\n\n#calculate v2 and find momentum flux components\nintegrand = ((0.3**2)/2) + ((0.3**4)/4)\nV2 = mdot / (rho * 2 * pi * integrand)\nvtheta2 = V2 * .9396926208 # velocity component in x of pipe 2\nvtheta3 = V2 * .342021433 # velocity component in y of pipe 2\nmxFlux = mdot * vtheta2\nmyFlux = mdot * vtheta3\n\nprint ('The velocity exiting pipe 2 is:', V2, 'm/s. The momentum flux component in the x is,', mxFlux,'kg/s and in the y is,', myFlux,'kg/s.')\n        ",
               "explanation": "The code involves the user to do some hand integration, however it computes the integration to find the mass flux components and finds the mass flow rate in order to find those components.",
               "reference":""
           },
           {
               "question": " A company wants to try to use boats in the ocean as pads for the boosters to land on which are 25m by 30m. The pressure and temperature at which the gas is being expelled are 700k and 450 kPa.The booster's jet radius is 10m the exit velocity of the jet is 300 m/s and the booster is at an attack angle of 30 degrees normal to the boat before contacting the boat. What is the total force the boat experiences? Assume a gamma value of 1.9 and a cv value of 3.3 kj/(kg. k) for the gas from the booster.",
               "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\npi = 3.141592653589793\nT1 = 700 # temperature exit (K)\nP1 = 450  # pressure exit (kPa)\nV1 = 300  # velocity exit (m/s)\nRad = 10  # radius (m)\ngamma = 1.9\nPa = 101.325  # pressure atmosphere (kPa)\ncv = 3.3  # heat capacity at constant volume (kJ/(kg.K))\n\n# first calculate the density of the gas being expelled\ncp = cv * gamma\nR = cp - cv\nrho = P1 / (R * T1)\nA = 25 * 30  # area (m^2)\n\n# calculate mass flow rate entering control volume\nvtheta1 = V1 * .5  # .5 arises from sin of 30\naJet = pi * Rad ** 2\nmdot = rho * (aJet / 0.5) * vtheta1\n\n# calculate force on the boat including atmosphere and pressure gradient from jet\nforce = (rho * aJet * V1 ** 2 * 0.5) + (Pa * 1000 * A) + (P1 * 1000 * aJet)\nforceK = force / 1000\n\nprint('The force experienced by the boat is', forceK, 'kN.')\n    ",
               "explanation": "This code utilizes the ideal gas relations to find density and from there expects a correct control volume analysis. It utilizes pressure from atmosphere and jet, along with momentum flux from the jet to calculate the force on the boat.",
               "reference":""
           },
           {
            "question": "How can we define incompressible flow, is it real in nature? If not, why can we apply incompressible flow to aerospace?",
            "answer": "Incompressible flow is defined as having constant density and negligible viscosity (inviscid). In reality there will always be some amount of friction meaning that there is no such thing as true inviscid flow. In addition to this every flow has some level of compressibility, therefore there is no true incompressible fluid. We are allowed to apply incompressible ideas to certain aerospace applications because they are so close to being inviscid and incompressible that we can obtain accurate results with these assumptions.  ",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "What must stand true for the use of Bernoulli’s principle to be valid, how do we obtain it, and why is this equation so important for understanding incompressible flow?",
            "answer": "For Bernoulli’s equation to be valid, flow must be steady, incompressible and inviscid (usually true along streamlines). It is derived from the momentum equation and Newton's second law. It is one of the most important expressions in fluid mechanics as it relates pressure variation along streamlines as a function of the change in velocity. In simpler terms, it tells us that velocity and pressure have an inverse relationship, when velocity increases from point A to point B, pressure decreases and vice versa.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "Describe the difference between Lagrangian and Eurlerian descriptions. When is it helpful to use one over the other?",
            "answer": "The Langrangian and Eulerian descriptions are both used to describe fluid motion, but they differ in approach and application. The Lagrangian description describes the entire flow by focusing on individual fluid particles (described using position of the particle and time) while the Eularian description is more concerned with a fixed field and how the substance moves through it (the field is described using a function of position and time). With that being said, the Lagrangian method is most useful when tracking the properties of a specific fluid as it moves and the Eulerian method is the most useful when studying velocity variation at specific points over time.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "What causes choked flow and what is its significance in compressible fluid mechanics?",
            "answer": "Choked flow occurs when velocity reaches the speed of sound causing the flow to become sonic (mach number = 1). It is significant because an increase in pressure would not increase flow rate as one would presume, but rather it would increase the density of the fluid.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "Explain the difference between normal shocks, oblique shocks and expansion fans. Include how they form, any changes in flow properties, and instances where they can be applied to aerospace.",
            "answer":  "Normal shocks form when a supersonic flow (mach number > 1) experiences an unexpected decrease in area causing a sudden increase in pressure, temperature and density, and a decrease in velocity. The flow also experiences a change in direction causing it to be subsonic (mach number < 1) downstream from the shock. These shocks can be observed when working with high speed propulsion systems. Oblique shocks are formed when a supersonic flow flows into an object at an angle (such as a concave corner) causing a deflection in the flow. They are similar to normal shocks as they also have an increase in pressure, density, and temperature. However, they vary with normal shocks because flow remains supersonic downstream. An aerospace application for oblique shocks is high speed flow over airfoils and wings. Expansion fans happen when supersonic flow encounters a convex corner (opposite to oblique in this sense). Expansion fans are unique in regard to changes in flow propertiesas they experience a decrease in pressure, density, and temperature rather than an increase. Similar to oblique shocks the flow remains supersonic downstream of the shock. Expansion fans can be encountered when working with supersonic aircrafts.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "What exactly is mach number, what is it used for and how is it derived?",
            "answer": "Mach number is the ratio of the speed of an object and the speed of sound it is encountering. (M = v/a where v is velocity and a is the speed of sound). It helps to define the movement of a flow and helps to explain flow properties. A flow is incompressible when M < 0.3, subsonic when M < 1, transonic when 0.8 < M < 1.2, sonic when M = 1, supersonic when M > 1, and hypersonic when M > 5. It is used to predict wave propagation, shock formation, and other compressibility effects. For an ideal gas, the a in the mach number question is derived from the ideal gas equation (p = ρRT) and adiabatic assumptions (p𝒗^𝛾 = constant and 𝛾 = cp /cv = 1.4), therefore a = sqrt(𝛾RT).",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
           },
           {
            "question": "Explain the difference between an adiabatic and an isothermal process.",
            "answer": "In an adiabatic process there is no heat transfer between the system and its surroundings so Q = 0. This process likely leads to changes in temperature. An example of this would be compression or expansion at constant pressure in a perfectly insulated system. However in an isothermal process, the temperature remains constant in the system. This means that there must be heat transfer between the system and its surroundings. An example of this would be the expansion or compression of a gas in contact with a heat or cooling reservoir at a constant temperature. ",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
           },
           {
            "question": "Why is a steady, adiabatic and reversible flow automatically considered an isentropic process?",
            "answer": "To understand this concept we must break down each case. A steady flow is one where the conditions remain constant throughout time. An adiabatic process is a process that has no heat transfer between the system and its surroundings meaning Q = 0. A reversible process is a process that can be reversed with its system and surroundings being returned to their initial states. This means it must be in quasi equilibrium with only small departures from equilibrium. We also know that an isentropic process is one in which entropy remains constant meaning delta(S) = 0. For this to occur there needs to be no heat transfer to change the entropy of the system therefore it must be adiabatic. In addition to this there needs to be no irreversibilities that would cause entropy to change, therefore it must also be a reversible process. And lastly, other properties must remain constant hence the need for it to be a steady flow. ",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "Explain the clausius statement in greater detail than the statement 'it is impossible to constuct a cyclic device whose sole effect is the transfer of hear from a cooler to a hotter body'",
            "answer": "This statement means that heat cannot magically pass from a cooler body to a hotter body without work input. Heat transfer occurs when there is a temperature difference between two bodies. The heat flows from the hotter body to the cooler one until equalibrium is reached. This type of transfer cannot just happen spontaneously and that is what the clausius statement is trying to address.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""   
        },
        {
            "question": "Consider an airfoil at standard sea level conditions with a freestream velocity of 33 m/s. At a certain point on the airfoil, the pressure is 0.3*10^5 N/m^2. First derive Bernoulli's equation from the momentum principle then find the velocity at this point.",
            "answer": "\n          import numpy as np\n\n          pInf = 101000 # standard sea level in N/m^2\n          rho = 1.23 # standard sea level in kg/m^3\n          vInf = 33 # m/s \n          p = 30000 # N/m^3\n          # use bernoulli's equation (pInf + .5*rho*vInf^2 = p + .5*rho*v^2) and simplify to isolate v\n          v = np.sqrt((2 * (pInf-p) / rho)+ 33*33)\n\n          print('velocity at this point is:', str(v), 'm/s')\n               ",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
           "question": "Consider the inviscid, incompressible flow of air along a streamline. The air density along the streamline is 0.002456 slug/ft^3. At the point 1 on the streamline, the pressure and velocity are 2010 lb/ft^2 and 10 ft/s, respectively. Further downstream, at point 2 on the streamline, the velocity is 180 ft/s. Find the pressure at point 2. What can be said about the change in pressure from point 1 to point 2 compared to the corresponding change in velocity. ",
           "answer": "\n         import numpy as np\n\n         # we can use bernoulli's equation since the flow is steady, incompressible, and inviscid\n         p_1 = 2010 # lb/ft^2\n         rho = 0.002345 # slug/ft^3\n         v_1 = 10 # m/s\n         v_2 = 180 # m/s\n         # bernoulli's (p_1 + .5*rho*v_1^2 = p_2 + .5*rho*v_2^2)\n         p_2 = p_1 + .5*rho*(v_1 * v_1 - v_2 * v_2) # isolate p_2\n         print('the pressure at point 2 is:', str(p_2), 'lb/ft^2')\n              ",
            "explanation": "Velocity increases from point 1 to point 2 while pressure decreases which aligns with bernoulli's equation",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
           "question": "Find the mass and density of 3 liters of air at 1.033 bar and 33 degrees celcius given that the gas constant is 287 J/kg*K",
           "answer": "\n         import numpy as np\n\n                       # assume ideal gas \n         R = 287 # 287 J/kg*K\n         p = 1.033 # bar\n         T = 33 + 273.15 # convert celcius to Kelvin\n         v = 3 * (0.001 / 1) # convert liters to m^3\n         m = (p * v) / (R * T) # manipulated form of ideal gas law equation in kg\n         rho = m / v # calcuates density in kg/m^3\n         print('The mass of the air is:', m, 'kg. The density of the air is:', rho, 'kg/m^3.')\n              ",
           "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
           "question": "calculate the mach number downstream of a shock with the following upstream properites: mach 1 = 1.3, pressure 1 = 93 kPa, and temperature 1 = 333K",
           "answer": "\n         import numpy as np\n\n         m_1 = 1.3 # mach 1\n         p_1 = 93 # kPa\n         T_1 = 333 # K\n         gamma = 1.4 # assumption \n                       # we can use the equation m_2^2 = (1+((gamma-1)/2)*m_1^2)/(gamma*(m_1^2)-(gamma-1)/2)\n         m_2 = np.sqrt((1+((gamma-1)/2)*m_1*m_1)/((gamma*m_1*m_1)-(gamma-1)/2))\n         print('mach downstream is:', m_2)\n                                     ",
           "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
           "question": "Calculate the static temperature and pressure of a flow downstream of a shock with the mach number 1.5, pressure of 200 kPa and temperature of 200 K.",
           "answer": "\n         import numpy as np\n\n         m_1 = 1.5 \n         gamma = 1.4 # assume isentropic\n         T_1 = 200 #K\n         p_1 = 200 #kPa\n         p_2 = ((2*gamma/(gamma+1))*m_1*m_1 - (gamma-1)*(gamma+1))*p_1 # manipulation of continuity, momentum and energy equation for isentropic flow\n         T_2 = ((1+ ((gamma-1)/2)*m_1*m_1) * (((2*gamma)/(gamma-1))*m_1*m_1) - 1)/ (((gamma-1)*(gamma-1))/(2*(gamma-1)*m_1*m_1))*T_1\n         print('The static pressure is:', p_2, 'kPa. The static temperatre is:', T_2,'K.')\n                                      ",
           "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
           "question": "At a point in an airflow the temperature is 333 K and the velocity is 3333 m/s. Find the total temperature at this point.",
           "answer": "\n         import numpy as np\n\n         T = 333 # K\n         v = 3333 # m/s\n         gamma = 1.4 # assume isentropic\n         R = 287 # J/kg*K\n                       # we can use the equation h+ v^2/2 = h_0\n                       # we know h = c_p * T so c_p = gamma * R /(gamma - 1)\n                       # putting these equations together we get c_p * T + v^2 / 2 = c_pT_0 \n                       # manipulate to get T_0 = T + (v*v)/(2*c_p) and sub c_p\n         T_0 = T + v*v*(gamma-1)/(2*gamma*R)\n         print('the total temperature is:', T_0, 'K.')\n",
           "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "Find the mach number of an ideal gas travelling at 20 m/s at a temperature of 100 K and define its flow.",
            "answer": "\n         import numpy as np\n         gamma = 1.4 # assume isentropic flow\n         v = 20 # m/s\n         T = 100 # K\n         R = 2.87 # gas constant in J/kg*K\n         a = np.sqrt(gamma*R*T) # because this is an ideal gas\n         m = v/a # known mach number equation \n         print('the mach number is', m, 'since m < 1 the flow is subsonic.'')\n",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "Can we apply Bernoulli's principle for shocks?",
            "answer": "Shocks occur as the object reaches transsonic or supersonic flow (M>1) while Bernoulli's principle works effectively at M<0.3. One can apply afore mentioned principle but a several assumptions have to be applied: incompressiblility, steady inviscid flow along the streamlines, and no external forces acting on the flow. Under all assumptions, we can use Bernoulli's principle, but results would be far off from a reality, making it highly inefficient.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
            
          {
            "question": "How is the internal energy of an ideal gas affected during an adiabatic process, where no heat is exchanged with the surroundings?",
            "answer": "During an adiabatic process, the internal energy decreases. This decrease occurs because work done by the gas against external forces results in reduction of its internal energy which is explained by the First Thermodynamics Law.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          
          {
            "question": "Under what circumstances can the assumption of negligible shaft work be made?",
            "answer": "Such assumption can be made for steady state processses with little to none mechanical effects, processes where only interaction is through the heat transfer or during ideal gas expansions/compressions.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          
          {
            "question": "Why do pressure lines exhibit curvature on an enthalpy-entropy (h-s) graph?",
            "answer": "The curvature of pressure lines on an enthalpy-entropy (h-s) graph occurs because specific enthalpy is a function of both pressure and temperature. When pressure is held constant, changes in temperature lead to variations in specific enthalpy, resulting in curved lines on the h-s graph.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference": "Çengel, Y. A., & Boles, M. A. (2018). Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach (9th ed., Chapter 7). McGraw-Hill Education."
          },
          
          {
          "question": "Can entropy be subject to conservation principles?",
          "answer": "Entropy is a nonconserved property, and there is no such thing as the conservation of entropy principle. Entropy remains constant during idealized reversible processes and increases during all actual processes.",
          "reference": "Çengel, Y. A., & Boles, M. A. (2018). Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach (9th ed., Chapter 7). McGraw-Hill Education., https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entropy"
          },
          
          {
          "question": "Why exactly pressure drops along the pipe?",
          "answer": "The pressure loss occurs when frictional forces, caused by the resistance to flow, act on a fluid as it flows through a conduit.",
          "explanation":"",
          "reference": "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pressure_drop"
              },
          
              {
          "question": "Why expansion fans are insetropic?",
          "answer": "Expansion fan is formed of Mach waves. Since the flow turning gradually with each succesive wave (unlike shocks), and each Mach wave is isentropic, then the flow across the expansion fan is also isentropic.",
          "explanation":"",
          "reference": "Çengel, Y. A., & Boles, M. A. (2018). Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach (9th ed., Chapter 17 p.856). McGraw-Hill Education."
              },
          
              { 
          "question": "Can heat be transferred to a liquid without inducing a change in its temperature?",
          "answer": "Yes, it is possible during the phase transformations (vaporization, melting) or if the liquid does work on a system. For this to be possible we have to assume steady state, adiabatic conditions and no external work for the system. ",
          "explanation":"",
          "reference":""
          },
          
              {
          "question": "Why pitot tube has to be turned towards the direction of the flow?",
          "answer": "Assuming the tube is not aligned properly, the dynamic pressure component would not be captured properly due to the turbulence. This results in total pressure distortion meaning wrong pressure reading.",
          "explanation":"",
          "reference":""
          },
               
          {
          "question": "An ideal monoatomic gas, initially comprising 3 moles, undergoes an adiabatic expansion. As a consequence of this expansion, the gas experiences a decrease in temperature from 323 K to 308 K. Please determine work performed by the gas during the process. Assume R = 8.314 J/(K*mol)",
          "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nn = 3  # Moles of gas (mol)\nR = 8.314  # Gas constant (J/mol*K)\nT1 = 323  # Initial Temperature (K)\nT2 = 308  # Final Temperature (K)\n\n# Work done in an adiabatic expansion process for an ideal gas\ninternal_energy = (3/2) * n * R * (T2-T1)\nwork_done = round(-internal_energy,2)\n\nprint('Work done by the gas:', work_done, 'Joules')\n  ",
          "explanation": "This code calculates work done in an adiabatic process. For this problem we can use the First Law of Thermodynamics. Recognizing that for adiabatic process Q = 0, we have ΔU = -W. Solving for internal energy, internal energy = (3/2) * n * R * (T2-T1) where 'n' is the number of moles, 'R' is the gas constant, 'T1' and 'T2' are initial and final temperatures, respectively. The work done is simply the same value with opposite sign.",
          "reference":""
          },
          
          {
          "question": " The aircraft flies at the height where static temperature is 250K. Please find the Mach number if the velocity of the aircraft is 650m/s? Assume isentropic steady flow where, γ = 1.4, R = 287 J/kg*K.",
          "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nT = 250  # Static Temperature (K)\nv = 650 # Velocity of the aircraft (m/s)\nR = 287 # Gas Constant (J/(kg*K)))\nγ = 1.4 # Specific heat ratio\n\n# Let's find the speed of sound at the altitude, and then find the Mach number\nc = pow(R*γ*T,1/2) # speed of sound\nM = round(v/c,2) # Mach number\n\nprint('The Mach number is equal to', M)\n  ",
          "explanation": "This code calculates the mach number given the atmospheric temperature and the velocity. First, we have to find the speed of sound at the height where temperature is 250K. Then, we have to recognize the formula for Mach number M=v/c.",
          "reference":""
          },    
          
          {
          "question": "A pipe has an inlet radius of 0.1 m and fluid velocity of 2.5 m/s. Assuming steady incompressible flow, please, find the mass flow rate out of the pipe. ",
          "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nr1 = 0.1  # Initial radius (m)\nv1 = 2.5 # Initial velocity (m/s)\nρ = 1000 # Density (kg/m^3)\n# Under the assumption of the steady flow we can claim that mass flow rate in is the same as mass flow rate out ṁ1=ṁ2.\n# ρ - const, density of the fluid\n\nA1 = np.pi * r1**2\nṁ1 = round(ρ*A1*v1,2)\nṁ2 =  ṁ1\nprint('The mass flow rate out is equal to', ṁ2, 'kg/s.')\n  ",
          "explanation": "This code calculates the mass flow rate out of the pipe. For this problem, it is important to recognize that mass flow rates in and out of the pipe are the same. ",
          "reference":"" 
          
          },        
          
          {
          "question": "A certain amount of gas undergoes the process wthout heat exchange adiabatically and very slowly from initial state, where temperature is 325 K and density is 1.2 kg/m^3, to a final state where the temperature is 500 K and density is one-half of the initial value. The specific heat capacity at the constant pressure is 1005 J/(kg*K), and specific gas constant is 287 J/kg*K. Calculate the entropy change of the air duing the process.",
          "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nT1 = 325  # Initial temperature (K)\nT2 = 500 # Final temperature (K)\np1 = 103000 # Initial pressure (Pa)\np2 = p1/2 # Final pressure (Pa)\nCp = 1005 # Specific heat capacity under the constant pressure (J/(kg*K))\nR = 287 # Specific gas constant (J/(kg*K))\n\n# It is important to recognize that air is an ideal gas.\n# Use an enthropy change for ideal gas formula \n\nΔs = round(Cp * np.log(T2/T1) - R * np.log(p2/p1),2)\n\nprint('The entropy change is ', Δs, 'J/K.')\n  ",
          "explanation": "This code calculates the change in entropy of the system. From the condition of the problem it is important to recognize that the process is adiabatic, was reached by quasi-equilibrium, and the air is ideal gas. Under this assumptions we can use the entropy changes for perfect gas formula. Positive change in entropy value indicates the increase in disorder of the system.",
          "reference":""
          }, 
              
          
          {
          "question": "A Pitot tube, mounted on the aircraft's fuselage is used to measure the velocity of an aircraft in flight. If the pressure difference between the stagnation pressure and static pressure is 4000 Pa, the air density is 1.2 kg/m^3 and the atmospheric pressure is 101325 Pa, find the velocity of the aircraft. Additionally, if the aircraft would climb to an altitude where air density is 0.8 kg/m^3, what would be a new pressure difference? Assume velocity did not change with elevation. ",
          "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nΔp = 4000 # Pressure difference (Pa)\nρ = 1.2 # density of air (kg/m^3)\n\nρ_new = 0.8  # density of air at the final altitude (kg/m^3)\n\n# We can apply Bernoulli's equation\n\n# Δp == p0-p = 1/2 * ρ * v**2\n\n# Where we can solve for v: \n\nv = round(np.sqrt(2*Δp/ρ),2)\n\n# Since we know the velocity of the aircraft, we can apply Bernoulli's principle once again to obtain the pressure difference.\n\nΔp_new = 1/2 * ρ_new * v**2\n\n\n\nprint('The aircraft's velocity is ', v, 'm/s. At the new altitude, the pressure difference is', round(Δp_new,1),' Pa. ')\n  ",
          "explanation": " This code calculates the velocity of the aircraft and the pressure difference at the altitude where density is given utilizing Bernoulli's principle. Student should recognize that and apply afore mentioned principle to find both unknowns.",
          "reference":""
          },
          
          {
          "question": "A reversible heat engine operates between two reservoirs at temperatures T1 = 900 K and T2 = 500 K. During each cycle, the engine absorbs Q_h = 7500 J amount of heat from the high-temperature reservoir and rejects Qc amount of heat to the low-temperature reservoir. Find the efficiency of the engine and the amount of heat rejected to the lower-temperature reservoir.?",
          "answer": "\n\nimport numpy as np\n\nQ_h = 7500 # Amount of heat from high-temperature reservoir (J)\nT_h = 900 # temperature of the high-temperature reservoir (K)\nT_c = 270 # temperature of the high-temperature reservoir (K)\n\n# To find the efficiency of the engine we can use the following formula:\n\nη = (1 - T_c/T_h)\n# Note, we are solving for the fraction, not percentage! \n \n# Since the process is reversible:  η = 1 - Q_c/Q_h\n# Derive Q_c: \n\nQ_c = round(Q_h*(1-η))\n\nprint('The efficiency of the engine is', η*100, '%. The amount of heat rejected to the low-temperature reservoir is Qc ≈',Q_c,'.')\n",
          "explanation": "This code calculates calculates the efficiency of the reversible engine as well as the heat rejected to the low-temperature reservoir. It is important to recognize that we can find efficiency using η = 1 - Tc/Th and then find Qc knowing that the process is reversible using η = 1 - Q_c/Q_h.",
          "reference": "Çengel, Y. A., & Boles, M. A. (2018). Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach (9th ed., Chapter 10, p.555-557). McGraw-Hill Education."
          },
              
          
          {
          "question": "An insulated container at a temperature of 27 °C and pressure 1.8 atm contains some amount of gas. If the number of molecules tripled while temperature and volume are unchanged, what would be the new pressure inside the container? Then, how pressure would change if the volume halved. Assume the gas is ideal.",
          "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\np = 1.8 # pressure (atm) \nt = 27 # temperature (°C)\n# Since the temperature and volume are the same, we can use ideal gas law to find a new pressure:\n\n#p = n*R*T/V \n\n#p_new = 3*n*R*T/V\n\n# We can substitute p into p_new to get: \np_new = 3*p\n\n#When the volume is halved: \n#p_final = 3*n*R*T/(V/2) = 6*n*R*T/V \np_final = 6*p\n\nprint('After tripling the number of molecules, the new pressure is p =', p_new, 'atm. When we halve the volume, the pressure is p =', p_final, 'atm.')\n\n  ",
          "explanation": " This code utilizes the ideal gas law to find the change in pressure gives changes in the number of molecules or volume of the system. It is essential to recognize that we can use previously mentioned law and Boyle's law given that the gas is ideal.",
          "reference":""
          },
          
          {
          "question": "A p-V diagram depicts 4 different reversible cyclic processes performed isobarically. During which cycle did gas do the most work? Explain your answer. Assume no external work, steady state and clockwise movement on the p-V diagram.",
          "answer": "\nimport matplotlib.pyplot as plt\nimport numpy as np\n\n\n# Create plot and axis\nfig, ax = plt.subplots()\n\n# Set axis values\nax.set_xlim(0, 10)\nax.set_ylim(0, 10)\n\n# Draw circles\ncircle1 = plt.Circle((8, 4), 1, color='b', fill=False)\ncircle2 = plt.Circle((4, 3), 1.75, color='g', fill=False)\ncircle3 = plt.Circle((4, 8), 2, color='r', fill=False)\ncircle4 = plt.Circle((8, 8), 1.5, color='m', fill=False)\n\n# Add circles to plot\nax.add_artist(circle1)\nax.add_artist(circle2)\nax.add_artist(circle3)\nax.add_artist(circle4)\n\n# Make a square plot\nax.set_aspect('equal')\n\n#Labels and title\nplt.xlabel('Volume (V)')\nplt.ylabel('Pressure (P)')\nplt.title('p-V Diagram')\n\n# Show plot\nplt.grid(True)\nplt.show()\n\nx = round(np.log(5/2),2)\nprint(x)\n\n# Given the fact that the process is isobaric (p-const), we can compute the work done by each process by finding the area enclosed in each circle. \n\nA1 = np.pi * 1**2\nA2 = np.pi * 1.75**2\nA3 = np.pi * 2 **2\nA4 = np.pi * 1.5 **2\n\n\nprint('The area's of the circles calculated by A = πR² are the following: blue circle area =', round(A1,2), 'green circle area =',round(A2,2),'red circle area =',round(A3,2),'and magenta circle area =',round(A4,2), 'So, the biggest amount of work was done by the red cyclic process.')\n  ",
          "explanation": " This code plots the p-V diagram on which four isobaric processes are depicted. The cycle with the largest area represents the most work done by the gas.",
          "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "Can you explain what exactly the Magnus effect is?",
            "answer": "A phenomenon associated with a spinning object moving through a fluid. Life forces act on the spinning object. The easiest example of the Magnus effect in real life is a soccer ball being kicked, and the lift generated on it."
        },
        {
            "question": "Assuming incompressible fluid, what can you interpret Bernoulli's equation to be an approximation of?",
            "answer": "The conservation of momentum"
        },
        {
            "question": "When Observing curved streamlines, how would you expect the pressure and velocities to act inside the curve? How about outside the curve?",
            "answer": "Low pressure and high velocity on the inside, high pressure and low velocity on the outside"
        },
        {
            "question": "How do you describe a reversible process in thermodynamics? Can you give three examples?",
            "answer": "A reversible process is a process in which any action done by the system can be undone. Three examples are: Compressing a gas, rotating magnetic fields, and a Carnot Engine Cycle."
        },
        {
            "question": " What are the three primary systems in thermodynamics, and what do they each mean?",
            "answer": "Isolated systems, closed systems, and open systems. Isolated system: mass nor energy can pass, and no external factors can ever affect it. Closed system: a closed system can exchange only energy with its surroundings, not matter. Open system: an open system can exchange both energy and matter with its surroundings"
        },
        {
            "question": "What are examples of things that affect the value of Sdot_irrev?",
            "answer": "Changes in entropy production due to irreversibilities. This includes viscous dissipation and internal heat transfer across finite temperature differences for example. Does not occur in reversible processes"
        },
        {
            "question": "What three equations are used to derive the relationship between M2 and M1 for normal shocks? How do you combine these three equations to arrive at this derivation?",
            "answer": "The conservation of mass: rho_1*V_1 = rho_2*V_2; Conservation of momentum: P1 + rho_1*V_1^2 = P2 + rho_2*V_2^2; Conservation of energy h1 + .5V_1^2 = h2 + .5V_2^2. Get them in isentropic form and then multiply continuity of mass and energy, and divide by momentum."
        },
        {
            "question": "What does flow across a concave corner create? What about a convex corner?",
            "answer": "An oblique shock across the corner. A convex corner creates an expansion fan across the corner."
        },
        {
            "question": "What is the deflection angle of an oblique shock? At what value is this angle at a maximum?",
            "answer ": "The deflection angle is what describes how the shock is oriented. This angle is at a maximum at 0 degrees, as it increases the more it approaches 90 degrees, or a normal shock."
        },
        {
            "question": "The following plot depicts water crashing into a dam. The density of the water is given as 1 Mg/m^3, the density of the materials in the dam is given by 2.5 Mg/m^3, the height of the dam is 6 meters, and the distance between point D and 6 is one. Find the minimum length from 4 to point D.",
             "code": "\n\nimport matplotlib.pyplot as plt\nimport numpy as np\n                \nx_wave = np.linspace(0, 5.61, 100)\ny_wave = 6 + 0.18 * np.sin(20 * np.pi * x_wave / 5.61)\n                \nx_water = [0, 5.61, 4, 0, 0]\ny_water = [6, 6, 0, 0, 6]\n                \nx_dam = [4, 5.61, 6.61, 6.61, 4]\ny_dam = [0, 6, 6, 0, 0]\n                \nplt.fill(x_water, y_water, color='lightblue')\nplt.fill(x_wave, y_wave, color='lightblue')\nplt.fill(x_dam, y_dam, color='gray')\n                \nplt.ylim(-.1, 8)\nplt.xlim(0, 6.61)\n                \nplt.gca().spines['top'].set_visible(False)\nplt.gca().spines['right'].set_visible(False)\nplt.gca().spines['bottom'].set_visible(False)\nplt.gca().spines['left'].set_visible(False)\n                \nplt.gca().set_xticks([4, 6])\nplt.gca().set_yticks([0, 6])\n                \nplt.plot([5.61], [0], marker='o', markersize=5, color='black', label='D')\nplt.text(5.61, .1, 'D', horizontalalignment='center')\n                \nplt.show()\n                ",
           "answer": {
           "code": "\nimport matplotlib.pyplot as plt\nimport numpy as np\n            \nx_wave = np.linspace(0, 5.61, 100)\ny_wave = 6 + 0.18 * np.sin(20 * np.pi * x_wave / 5.61)\nx_water = [0, 5.61, 4, 0, 0]\ny_water = [6, 6, 0, 0, 5]\nx_dam = [4, 5.61, 6.61, 6.61, 4]\ny_dam = [0, 6, 6, 0, 0]\ndam_rho = 2.5\nwater_rho = 1\n            \n            \nplt.vlines(x = 5.61, ymin = 0, ymax = 6, colors = 'black')\nplt.hlines(y = 0, xmin = 4, xmax = 5.61, colors = 'red')\nplt.fill(x_wave, y_wave, color='lightblue')\nplt.plot([4, 5.61], [0, 6], color='black')\nplt.vlines(x = 6.61, ymin = 0, ymax = 6, colors = 'black')\nplt.hlines(y = 0, xmin = 5.61, xmax = 6.61, colors = 'black')\nplt.hlines(y = 6, xmin = 5.61, xmax = 6.61, colors = 'black')\nplt.hlines(y = 6, xmin = 4, xmax = 5.61, colors = 'green')\nplt.vlines(x = 4, ymin = 0, ymax = 6, colors = 'green')\nplt.hlines(y = 0, xmin = 0, xmax = 4, colors = 'blue')\nplt.vlines(x = 0, ymin = 0, ymax = 6, colors = 'blue')\n            \nplt.ylim(-.1, 8)\nplt.xlim(-0.1, 6.63)\n            \nplt.gca().spines['top'].set_visible(False)\nplt.gca().spines['right'].set_visible(False)\nplt.gca().spines['bottom'].set_visible(False)\nplt.gca().spines['left'].set_visible(False)\n            \nplt.gca().set_xticks([4, 6.61])\nplt.gca().set_yticks([0, 5])\n            \nplt.plot([5.61], [0], marker='o', markersize=5, color='Red', label='D')\nplt.text(5.61, -.35, 'D', horizontalalignment='center', color ='Red')\nplt.plot([6.11], [3], marker='X', markersize=5, color='Red', label='D')\nplt.arrow (6.12, 3, 0, -1, head_width=0.1, head_length=0.1, fc='red', ec='red')\nplt.plot([5.0733], [2], marker='X', markersize=5, color='orange', label='D')\nplt.arrow (5.0773, 2, 0, -1, head_width=0.1, head_length=0.1, fc='orange', ec='orange')\nplt.plot([4.5367], [4], marker='X', markersize=5, color='green', label='D')\nplt.arrow (4.542, 4, 0, -1, head_width=0.1, head_length=0.1, fc='green', ec='green')\nplt.plot([3], [2], marker='X', markersize=5, color='blue', label='D')\nplt.arrow (3, 2, 1, 0, head_width=0.1, head_length=0.1, fc='blue', ec='blue')\n            \nplt.show()\n\n#calculate force at each center of mass of four broken up bodies, as shown in the diagram\n#W_red = (dam_rho*(6*1)*9.81)\n#W_orange = (dam_rho*(.5*(d-1)*6)*9.81)\n#W_green = (water_rho*(.5*(d-1)*6)*9.81)\n#F_blue = (.5*(water_rho*9.81*6)*6)\n#use the sum of moments = to to find d, distance\n#sum of moments = (W_red*(.5)+(W_orange*(1+(d-1)/3)+(W_green*(d-(d-1)/3)(F_blue*3) = 0\n#sum of moments = 44.15d^2 + 14.72d -338.445 = 0\nd = 2.61m\nprint('The distance between the point D and x=4 is ', d,'m')\n            ",
         "explanation": "This code calculates the Mach number using isentropic flow tables and an understanding of pitot tubes to find a stagnation pressure value."
                }
        },
        {
            "question": "Air is flowing at a constant rate, and has an initial temperature and pressure of 245.85 C and 56.355 Kpa, respectively. A pitot tube is inserted with its entrance facing the flow direction in the positive x direction, and measures a pressure of 1604 lb/ft^2. Determine the mach number of this flow.",
            "answer": {
               "code": "\nimport numpy as np\np = 56.355 # initial pressure, Kpa\nT = 245.85 # initial temperature, C\np_0_lbft = 1604 #stagnation temperature pulled from pitot tube, lb/ft\n                \np_0 = (p_0_lbft*47.880208) = 76.799 #unit conversion\nP_ratio = (P/(P_0))\n# from isentropic flow tables\nM = .68\nprint('The P to P0 ratio is thus .7338, and so the mach number is .68 in this case.')\n         ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the Mach number using isentropic flow tables and an understanding of pitot tubes to find a stagnation pressure value."
            }
        },
        {
            "question": "On mars, water flows out of the bottom of a rectangular tank through a hole in the center of the bottom side at 12 m/s. Given that the density of water is 1000kg/m^3, determine the height from the top of the water to the source of the leak (the hole)",
            "answer": {
               "code": "\nimport numpy as np\nrho = 1000 #constant density, kg/m^3\nV2 = 12 #velocity at exit, m/s\ngMars = 3.71 #gravity on mars\n# use berenoulli's principle, (v1^2/2) + (g*h1) + (P1/ρ) = (v2^2/2) + (gh2) + (P2/ρ) (energy state at 1 and 2 is the same, so equal)\nv1 = 0 # velocity at surface\nh2 = 0 # height with respect to top of the tank\n# h1 = ??\n# P1-P2 = 0\n#(gMars*h1)=(v2^2/2)\nh1 = (v2^2)/(2*gMars)\nprint('The height of the tank is thus', h1, 'm')\n         ",
             "explanation": "This problem uses the idea of berenoulli's principle, and how since it is a constant can be set equal to itself for a second state to solve for any unknown variables."
            }
        },
        {
            "question": "3 kg of a gas with a molecular weight of .28kg is heated from 34 degrees C to 394 degrees K. If the Cv is a constant value of 1 J/mol*K, what is the minimum required heat for an isochoric process?",
            "answer": {
               "code": "\nimport numpy as np\nm = 3 # mass of the gas kg\nM = .28 # molar mass of the gas kg\nT1 = 34 # Initial temperature C\nT2 = 394-273.15 # Final temperature C\nCv = 1 # Cv value, J/mol*K\n# using ideal gas, derive to Q = nCv(dt)\nn = m/M #n, moles\nQ = n*Cv*(T2-T1)\nprint('The required heat is ', Q, 'KJ')\n         ",
                 "explanation": "This code describes a problem where the volume is constant, in other words an isochoric process. Using the equation Q=nCvdT one can find the Q required for this equation to be true"
            }
        },
        {
        "question": "An ideal gas starts at a volume of 1.6 m^3 and a pressure of 2 bar. Later, the volume is isothermally expanded to 2.5 m^3. How much thermal energy is transferred to the gas during this process?",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n#knowing for an isothermal process, W=nRTln(Vf/V0) as well as the ideal gas law Pv=nRT\n#moles and T aren’t given, so we rewrite work as W=PiViln(Vf/V0)\nP = 200000  # constant pressure, Pa\nVi = 1.6    # initial volume, m^3\nVf = 2.5    # final volume, m^3\nW = P * Vi * np.log(Vf/Vi)\nprint('The work done is thus', W, 'J')\n",
        "explanation": "This problem uses the definitive knowledge of isothermal processes and the ideal gas law to create the equation for work",
        "reference":""
        },
        {
        "question": "How much mass is needed to fill a 500 liter tank of xenon kept at 200 bar? Assuming standard temperature, and given that the molecular weight of 131.293g/mol.",
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n# Use ideal gas law, Pv=nRT\nP = 2000000 #initial pressure, pa\nV = .5 #volume, m^3\nT = 273.15 #Temperature, K\nR = 8.314 # universal gas constant, J/mol\nM = .131293 # molar mass of xenon\nn = (P*V)/(R*T)\nm = n*M #mass calculation\nprint('The required mass is ', m , 'kg')\n",
        "explanation": "This problem uses the ideal gas law as xenon is an ideal gas, along with the knowledge of standard temperature and molar mass of xenon to find the required mass.",
        "reference":""
        },
        {
        "question": "Air is flowing at a mach number of 1.6 and experiences a concave corner with a theta of 22 degrees. Using the Prandtl-Meyer function, calculate the mach number after the oblique shocks. Assume gamma = 1.4.",  
        "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\nimport math\nM1 = 1.6 # initial mach number\ntheta = 22 #degree of shock\nvM1= (math.sqrt(6)) * (math.atan(math.sqrt(1.67 * (M1**2 - 1)))) - (math.atan(math.sqrt(M1**2 - 1))) #prandtl meyer function\n#theta = vM2-vM1\nvM2 = vM1+theta\n#Table for this part\nM2 = 1.9\nprint('The value of M2, the mach after the shock, is ', M2)\n",
        "explanation": "This problem uses the prandtl meyer function for expansion fans in order to find a second mach number after a fan given the first one and the angle theta of which the fan is created at.",
        "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "Why is the efficiency of a heat engine given as 1 - (Q2/Q1), but the efficiency of a reversible heat engine is 1 - (T2/T1)?",
            "answer": "The relationship between the efficiency of a standard heat engine and a reversible one comes from the Clausius inequality. The Clasius inequality states that Q1/T1 - Q2/T2 <= 0. When a process is reversible, Q1/T1 = Q2/T2, and the relation can be substituted into the efficiency equation to give efficiency = 1 - (T2/T1).",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "What is the difference between static temperature and stagnation temperature?",
            "answer": "Static temperature is the temperature you would record if you moved a thermometer along the fluid, and it does not include the kinetic energy of the flow. Stagnation temperature is what the temperature would be if the flow was isentropically brought to a stop.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "Why do oblique shocks and an expansion fans cause the flow properties to change in opposite directions?",
            "answer": "In an oblique shock, the compressible flow is forced onto itself by a rigid corner, causing a shock to occur. Changes in flow properties occur in the same direction as a normal shock. In an expansion fan, the compressed flow is given more room to flow, effectively acting as an area increase, so the mach number increases. Expansion fans are also isentropic because there is not a shock.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "Why does the velocity of an incompressible fluid increase as the area it is flowing through decreases?",
            "answer": "The law of conservation of mass states that the steady mass flow into and out of a control volume must be equal. By the mass flow equation mdot = rho*A*v, if rho is constant (true for an incompressible fluid), then if area decreases velocity must increase.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "What does it mean for a process to be both adiabatic and reversible?",
            "answer": "For a process to be adiabatic, there must be no heat transfer in and out of the system. Note that this does not mean that temperature must be constant. Generally, for a process to be adiabatic, the system must be insulated from the environment, or be quick enough that heat does not have time to transfer. Reversible processes are those where the system and surroundings can be return to an initial state. For a process to be reversible, it must be done in small enough increments that it can be considered a quasi-equilibrium process. Processes that are both adiabatic and reversible are isentropic.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "Explain the role of entropy in determining the direction of natural processes.",
            "answer": "Entropy can be thought of the extent to which a system's energy is unable to yield useful mechanical work. Because of this, a process cannot have a negative entropy associated with it without a greater entropy increase elsewhere.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "Explain why a pitot tube needs to take two measurements to determine the velocity of a flow.",
            "answer": "A simple pitot tube generally takes two measurements, one of the stagnation pressure and one of static pressure. By taking a measurement after forcing the flow to stagnate, the stagnation pressure can be recorded. The static pressure is recorded by measuring the pressure of the flow without stopping it. The static pressure and stagnation pressure together can be used to determine the velocity of the flow by equation p_stagnation = p_static + 1/2 * v^2. This is only valid without any shocks.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "Explain why the stagnation temperature of a flow does not change across a shock.",
            "answer": "Shocks always cause an increase in entropy, however, the stagnation temperature is essentially a statement on the conservation of energy. Because shocks are an adiabatic process, the stagnation temperature of a flow does not change.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "What is the difference between enthalpy and internal energy?",
            "answer": "A change in enthalpy describes the heat transfer in a constant pressure process, while internal energy describes the various forms of energy within a thermodynamic system. The heat transfer in a constant volume process with no external work is equal to the change in internal energy, excluding any graviational or kinetic energy changes.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "An airfoil is placed in a flow of 100% dinitrogen monoxide gas with a freestream velocity of 50m/s at sea level conditions. The pressure in the flow is 1.35 bar and the density is 1.9781 kg/m^3. At a given point, the pressure is 1.2 bar. Calculate the velocity at this point.",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nrho = 1.9781  # Density at sea level (kg/m^3)\nv1 = 50  # Freestream velocity (m/s)\np1 = 135000  # Pressure of the flow (N/m^2)\np2 = 120000 # Pressure at point on airfoil (N/m^2)\n\n# Apply Bernoulli's equations to the airfoil\nv2 = np.sqrt((2*(p1-p2)/rho + v1**2))\n\nprint('Velocity at the point on the airfoil where pressure = 1.2 bar:', v2, 'm/s')\n        ",
            "explanation": "This code utilizes Bernoulli's equation along a streamline. It states that p1 + 1/2 * rho * v1^2 = p2 + 1/2 * rho * v2^2. The equation can be rearranged to solve for v2.",
            "reference": "John Anderson, (2023) Fundamentals of Aerodyanmics, Seventh Edition, McGraw-Hill."
          },
          {
            "question": "A large hall has a with a rectangular floor that is 22m by 75m, and a 100m high ceiling. The air pressure is 1.03 bar and the temperature is 17 degrees C. Calculate the internal energy and the enthalpy of the air in the room.",
            "answer": "\nV = 22 * 75 * 100  # Volume of the room (m^3)\np = 101300  # Pressure in the room (N/m^2)\nT = 17 + 273.15 # Temperature in the room (N/m^2)\nR = 287 # J/kg/K of air\ncv = 717.5 # J/kg/K\ncp = 1004.5 # J/kg/K\n\n# density of the air\nrho = p/R/T\n\n# Mass of the air\nm = rho * V\n\nU = m * cv * T\nH = m * cp * T\n\nprint('Internal energy of the air:', U, 'J')\nprint('Enthalpy of the air:', H, 'J')\n        ",
            "explanation": "Density of the air is first calculated by using the ideal gas law. Mass is found using density and volume. Afterwards, the mass can be multiplied by cp and cv and temperature in Kelvin to find the total internal energy and enthalpy.",
            "reference": "John Anderson, (2023) Fundamentals of Aerodyanmics, Seventh Edition, McGraw-Hill."
          },
          {
            "question": "An aircraft flies at an altitude of 20,000 m. The pressure at a point on the wing is 5,000 Pa. Assuming isentropic flow over the wing, calculate the temperature at this point. The stagnation pressure and temperature at 20,000 m are 5,475 Pa and 217 K respectively.",
            "answer": "\np1 = 5000 # Pressure at a local point on the wing, Pa\np01 = 5475 # Stagnation pressure at h = 20,000 m, Pa\nT01 = 217 # Stagnation temperature at h = 20,000 m, K\ngamma = 1.4 # Specific heat ratio of air\n\nT1 = T01 * (p1/p01)**((gamma-1)/gamma)\n\nprint('Local temperature at the point:', T1, 'K')\n        ",
            "explanation": "The problem states that the flow is isentropic. The isentropic relation T/T01 = (p/p01)^((gamma-1)/gamma) can be applied to the flow to find the local temperature.",
            "reference": "John Anderson, (2023) Fundamentals of Aerodyanmics, Seventh Edition, McGraw-Hill."
          },
          {
            "question": "A steady flow has a static temperature of 400 K, and a velocity of 1,200 m/s. Calculate the Mach number at this point, and find what the mach number would be after a normal shock. Afterwards find the new temperature.",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nT = 400 # Static temperature, K\nv = 1200 # Velocity of the flow, m/s\nR = 287 # Gas constant of air, J/kg/K\ngamma = 1.4 # Specific heat ratio of air\n\n# Calculate the speed of sound\na = np.sqrt(gamma * R * T)\n\n# Calculate the Mach number\nM1 = v/a\n\n# Use the equation for mach number after a shock\nM2 = np.sqrt((1 + ((gamma - 1)/2) * M1**2) / (gamma*(M1**2) - (gamma - 1)/2))\n\n# New temperature after a shock\nT2 = T1 * (1 + ((gamma - 1)/2) * M1**2) * ((2*gamma)/(gamma - 1)*M1**2 - 1) / ((gamma + 1)**2 / (2*(gamma - 1)) * M1**2)\n\nprint('Mach number of the flow:', M1)\nprint('Mach number of the flow after the shock:', M2)\nprint('The temperature after the shock:', T2, 'K')\n        ",
            "explanation": "The speed of sound is found by applying a = sqrt(gamma*R*T) using temperature and gas properties. The Mach number is found by dividing the velocity by the speed of sound. The Mach number post shock is found by using the normal shock equation for velocity after a shock. The temperature after the shock is found by using the change in temperature equation. It is important to remember that this temperature is the static temperature, and that stagnation temperature across a shock is constant.",
            "reference": "John Anderson, (2023) Fundamentals of Aerodyanmics, Seventh Edition, McGraw-Hill."
          },
          {
            "question": "An aircraft flies at an altitude of 6000 m at Mach 1.7. If a shock occurs, assuming the shock wave pattern is a Mach wave, the moment a person on the ground hears the shock, how far ahead is the aircraft?",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nM = 1.7 # Mach number\nh = 6000 # altitude of the plane, m\n\n# calculate the Mach angle\nmu = np.arcsin(1/M)\n\n# calculate distance using tan(mu) = h/d\nd = h / np.tan(mu)\n\nprint('The distance between the person and the aircraft is:', d, 'm')\n        ",
            "explanation": "The shockwave from the aircraft follows a straight line at an angle relative to the ground. This angle is found as the inverse sin of 1/M. Some trigonometry can then be applied to determine that the horizontal distance d between the aircraft and the first people to hear the shock is h / atan(mu).",
            "reference": "John Anderson, (2023) Fundamentals of Aerodyanmics, Seventh Edition, McGraw-Hill."
          },
          {
            "question": "A heat source at 1000 K loses 1600 kJ of heat to a sink at (1) 750 K and (2) 900 K. Determine which process is more irreversible.",
            "answer": "\nT = 1000 # Temperature of heat source, K\nQ = 1600000 # Heat loss to a sink\n\n# Entropy to a sink at 500 K\nS_source = -Q/T\nS_sink1 = Q/750\nS_1 = S_source + S_sink1\n\n# Entropy to a sink at 750 K\nS_sink2 = Q/900\nS_2 = S_source + S_sink2\n\nprint('Change in entropy in process 1:', S_1, 'J/K')\nprint('Change in entropy in process 2:', S_2, 'J/K')\nprint('Process 1 is more irreversible.')\n        ",
            "explanation": "The irreversibility of a process can be measured in the change in entropy that comes from the process. The change is entropy can be found as the sum of entropy of different parts of a system. The entropy of heat loss from a source can be found with S = -Q/T1. The entropy of heat going into the sink is S = Q/T2. Summing these gives the net entropy of the process. Whichever net entropy is greater is more irreversible. Process 1 is also intuitively more irreversible because the temperature different between the source and sink is greater.",
            "reference": "Michael Boles and Yunus Çengel, (2010) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
          },
          {
            "question": "A hose with a nozzle is used to fill a 350-L reservoir. The inner diameter of the hose is 10 cm, and it reduces to 1 cm at the nozzle. It takes 15 s to fill the reservoir with water, determine the average velocity of water at the nozzle exit and the mass flow rate.",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nV = 350 # Volume of bucket, L\nD_1 = 0.1 # Initial diameter of hose, m\nD_2 = 0.01 # Final diameter of hose, m\nt = 15 # Time to fill the reservoir, s\nrho = 1 # density of water, kg/L\n\n# calculate volumetric flow rate\nVdot = V / t\n\n# calculate mass flow rate\nmdot = rho * Vdot\n\n# calculate the exit area of the nozzle\nAe = np.pi * (D_2 / 2)**2\n\n# calculate the mean exit velocity of the flow\nVe = Vdot / Ae * (1/1000) # multiple by 1/1000 to convert from liters to cubic meters\n\nprint('The mean exit velocity from the nozzle is:', Ve, 'm/s')\nprint('The mass flow rate is:', mdot, 'kg/s')\n        ",
            "explanation": "First begin by calculating the volumetric flow rate. This can be found by dividing the volume of liquid moved by time. Volumetric flow rate can be multiplied by density to get mass flow rate. The exit area of the nozzle can then be calculated by finding the area of a circle. Dividing the volumetric flow rate by the exit area gives the average velocity of the fluid.",
            "reference": "Michael Boles and Yunus Çengel, (2010) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
          },
          {
            "question": "An isolated electrochemical cell indefinitely generates an electrical current. How does this process violate the first law of thermodynamics, “the conservation of energy?",
            "answer": "The first law of thermodynamics states that energy and matter cannot be created or destroyed, but only converted from one form to another. An electrochemical cell that generates electricity is an example in which energy is being created in a closed system without external energy input. Since energy is increasing without outside interference, the first law of thermodynamics is being violated.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference": "https://www.khanacademy.org/test-prep/mcat/chemical-processes/thermodynamics-mcat/e/thermodynamics-questions"
        },
        {
            "question": "What does Archimedes principle state and can this principle be applied to all fluids? What about objects of any shape or size?", 
            "answer": "Archimedes principle states that if a body is partially or wholly submerged, then it receives an upward thrust equivalent to the displaced fluid. All fluids, not just liquids and gases, can be covered by the Archimedes principle. However, as gases are less dense and have a weaker buoyancy factor, it is most often used in liquids. Also, objects of any shape or size shall be subject to this principle, as long as they are completely immersed in the liquid."
        },
        {
            "question": "What is the main function of a pressure regulator in a supersonic wind tunnel?",
            "answer": " In a wind tunnel, air flowing out of the tank results in a pressure drop. The pressure regulator ensures that the mass flow rate remains constant.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference": "https://scholarworks.uark.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1020&context=meeguht"
        
        },
        {
          "question": "What are the distinct character differences between laminar and turbulent flow.",
          "answer": "Laminar flow is where the fluid flows in layers without heavy integration between the layers. Within each layer, the velocity, pressure, and other hydrodynamic properties remain unchanged. Contrarily, turbulent flow displays erratic movements that mix particles between the layers of fluids flowing.  ",
          "explanation":"",
          "reference":""
        },
        {
          "question": "How does the second law of thermodynamics describe why heat is transferred from a hot object to a cold object?",
          "answer": "The second law states that there exists a useful state variable called entropy. The change in entropy is equal to the heat transfer divided by the temperature. Thus, in a closed system, entropy tends to increase over time. When heat flows from a hot object to a cold object, it increases the overall entropy of the system, as the hot object loses heat and the cold object gains heat. This process tends to move the system towards a state of maximum entropy, which is the state of thermodynamic equilibrium.", 
          "explanation":"",
          "reference": "https://www1.grc.nasa.gov/beginners-guide-to-aeronautics/second-law-entropy/"
        },
        {
          "question": "What is an example of a reversible process? What is an example of an irreversible process? ",
          "answer": "An example of a reversible process would be forcing a flow, with zero viscosity, through a constricted pipe. As the flow moves through the pipe, the pressure, temperature, and velocity would change, but these variables would return to their original values downstream. An example of an irreversible process is putting a hot object in contact with a cold object. Eventually, they both achieve the same equilibrium temperature. If we separate the objects they will not return to their original temperatures.",
          "explanation":"",
          "reference": "https://www1.grc.nasa.gov/beginners-guide-to-aeronautics/second-law-entropy/"
        },
        {
          "question": "Why does viscosity decrease with increasing temperature in a liquid?",
          "answer": "Viscosity, denoted by mu, varies strongly with temperature as it is closely linked to molecular motion. In a liquid molecules form bonds which enhances the transfer of momentum. As temperature rises, the kinetic energy of the molecules of the liquid increases. Thus, the particles move farther apart until bond forces no longer bind them together. Bond forces decrease and thus the transfer of momentum is reduced.",
          "explanation":"",
          "reference":""
        },
        {
          "question": "What are the main assumptions associated with Fanno flow?",
          "answer": "Fanno flow is the adiabatic flow through a constant area duct where the effect of friction is considered. From this definition, we can identify that the main assumptions associated with Fanno flow are: the flow is steady, one-dimensional, and adiabatic through a constant-area duct, and the fluid is an ideal gas with constant specific heats.", 
          "explanation":"",
          "reference": "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fanno_flow"
        },
        {
          "question": "Does the Mach number increase across an expansion fan? Why?",
          "answer": " Through an expansion fan, the Mach number increases, the static pressure decreases and the total pressure remains constant. This is because expansion fans are isentropic as a result of the area increase. Across an expansion fan, the velocity increases. Since Mach number can be determined by calculating velocity/area, this results in an increasing Mach number.",
          "explanation":"",
          "reference":"https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prandtl%E2%80%93Meyer_expansion_fan,https://www1.grc.nasa.gov/beginners-guide-to-aeronautics/centered-expansion-fan/, https://www.grc.nasa.gov/www/k-12/airplane/isentrop.html"
        },  
        {
            "question": "A pressure indicator column has a height of 2.25 meters and a density of 11300 kg/m^3. Determine the local atmospheric pressure. Assume acceleration due to gravity.",
            "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n        \n        rho = 11300\n        h = 2.25\n        g = 9.8\n        \n        # Apply the formula used to describe the pressure exerted by the weight of a gas or liquid in a column\n        atm_p = rho * h * g\n        print('The local atmospheric pressure is str(atm_p/101325)+' atm')\n        ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the pressure exerted by the weight of a gas or liquid in a column. Where h is the height above the observation point, rho is the density of the fluid, and g is the acceleration due to gravity on Earth.",
            "reference": "https://www.khanacademy.org/science/physics/fluids/density-and-pressure/v/fluids-part-3"
        },
        {
            "question": "Consider water moving through a leveled pipe of varying diameter. Fluid enters the pipe with a velocity of 1.2m/s and exits the pipe with a velocity of 2m/s. The pressure into the pipe is 1650N/m^2. Assume laminar flow. Using Bernoulli's equation, calculate the pressure of water leaving the pipe.",
            "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n        \n        v1 = 1.2\n        v2 = 2\n        p1 = 1650\n        rho = 1000 # density of water\n        \n        # Recall Bernoullis Equation: \n        p1 + rho * h1 * g + 0.5 * rho * v1**2 = p2 + rho * h2 * g + 0.5 * rho * v2**2\n        \n        # Since the pipe is level, the height at either end of the pipe is the same, thus h1 = h2. Therefore, we can cancel out the terms involving h:\n        p1 + 0.5 * rho * v1**2 = p2 + 0.5 * rho * v2**2\n        \n        # Now substituting in our values we can solve for p2: \n        p2 = 0.5 * ((v1)**2 - (v2)**2) + p1\n        \n        print('The pressure of water that is exiting the system is str(p2)+' N/m^2')\n        ",
            "explanation": "This code uses Bernoulli's equation to determine the pressure leaving out of a pipe of varying diameter.",
            "reference": "https://www.khanacademy.org/science/physics/fluids/fluid-dynamics/v/fluids-part-12"
        },
        {
            "question": "An oil of viscosity 0.97 poise and relative density 0.9 is flowing through a horizontal circular pipe of diameter 100 mm and of length 10 m. Calculate the difference of pressure at the two ends of the pipe, if 100 kg of the oil is collected in a tank in 30 seconds. Assume the flow is laminar.",
            "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n        \n        t= 30 # time\n        mu = 0.97/10 # Converting poise to N-s/m^2. 10 poise = 1 N-s/m^2\n        l = 10 # length \n        mdot = 100/t # mass flow rate\n        rho = 0.9 * 1000 # relative density is equal to 0.9(of 0:1)  \n        Q = mdot/rho # volume flow rate \n        d = 100/1000 # we must convert mm to m. 1mm is equal to 0.001m \n        r = d/2 # radius\n        A = (pi/4) * d**2 # area \n        v = Q/A # velocity\n        \n        # Since the flow is laminar we can apply the Hagen-Poiseuille equation to determine the pressure loss across a pipe:\n        Delta_p = (8 * mu * v * l)/(r**2)\n        \n        print('The loss in pressure is '+str(np.around(Delta_p,3))+'N/m^2')\n        ",
            "explanation": "This code determines the loss in pressure across a pipe such that t represents time, mu is viscosity, l is length, mdot is mass flow rate rho = is relative density, Q is volume flow rate, d is diameter, r is radius, A is area, and v is velocity.",
            "reference": "K., B. R., & Bansal, R. K. (2000). Textbook of fluid mechanics and hydraulic machines. Laxmi Pub."
        },
        {
            "question": "An aircraft is flying at a cruising speed of 300m/s at an altitude of 4500m where the atmospheric pressure is 60.25kPa and the ambient air temperature is 235.7K. The ambient air is first decelerated in a diffuser before it enters the compressor. Assuming both the diffuser and the compressor to be isentropic, what is the stagnation pressure at the compressor inlet? The constant-pressure specific heat cp is 1.005kJ/(kg*k) and the specific heat ratio, k, of air at room temperature is 1.4.",
            "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n        \n        v1 = 300 #velocity\n        p1 = 60.25\n        t1 = 235.7\n        cp = 1.005 * 1000 # conversion factor \n        k = 1.4\n        \n        # First we must determine the stagnation temperature, t0, at the compressor inlet:\n        t0 = t1 + ((v1 ** 2)/(2 * cp))\n        \n        # Then using the equation for stagnation pressure for ideal gases with constant specific heats:\n        p0 = p1 * ((t0/t1) ** (k/(k-1))\n        \n        print('The stagnation pressure at the compressor inlet is str(p2)+' kPa')\n        ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the stagnation pressure at the compressor inlet such that v is the velocity, k is the specific heat ratio of air at room temperature, cp is the constant-pressure specific heat, t is the ambient air temperature, and p is the atmospheric pressure.",
            "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill. page number 826. Chapter 17, example number 17-1"
        },
        {
          "question": "Air enters a diffuser with a velocity of 500m/s. Determine (a) the speed of sound and (b) the Mach number at the diffuser inlet when the air temperature is 30°C. Assume air at specified conditions behave as ideal gasses.",
            "answer": "\n        import numpy as np\n        \n        R = 0.287 *1000 # gas constant of air converted from kJ/kg*K to m^2/s^2\n        k = 1.4 # specific heat ratio at 30 degrees Celsius\n        T = 30 + 273.15 # converting temperature in Celsius to temperature in kelvin\n        V = 500\n        \n        # (a) The speed of sound in the air can be expressed and determined using Hook's Law:\n        c = sqrt(k * R * T)\n        \n        # (b) The Mach Number is then easily determined using M = V/c\n        M = V/c\n        \n        print('The speed of sound is str(c)+' m/s')\n        print('The Mach number is str(M))\n        ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the speed of sound in air such that R is the gas constant of air, k is the specific heat ratio at 30 degrees Celsius, T is the given temperature, and v is our given velocity.",
            "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill. page number 829. Chapter 17, example number 17-2"
        },
        {
            "question": "A coffee thermos is initially closed and filled with 0.1m^3 of hot liquid at 366.15K and contains air at 0.2MPa. The thermos is then opened and left exposed to a space with a volume of  0.2m^3 at a temperature of 343.15K and 0.1MPa. Equilibrium is achieved adiabatically. What is the total mass of air? ",
            "answer": "\n        \n        import numpy as np\n        \n        p1 = 0.2 * 10**6 # converting MPa to Pa\n        v1 = 0.1\n        T1 = 366.15 \n        R = 287 \n        p2 = 0.1 * 10**6 # converting MPa to Pa\n        v2 = 0.2\n        T2 = 343.15\n        \n        # We can apply the Ideal Gas equation to find the mass inside the thermos and the mass of the room:\n        m1 =  (p1*v1)/(R * T1) \n        m2 =  (p2*v2)/(R * T2)\n        \n        # Then summing m1 and m2 to determine the total mass:\n        m_tot = m1 + m2\n        \n        print('The total mass of air is str(m_tot)+' kg')\n        ",
            "explanation": "This code solves for the total mass amongst two systems that have been interfaced and have reached equilibrium. Using the ideal gas equation such that P is the pressure, v is the volume, m is the mass, and T is the temperature. The total mass is determined by summing the individual masses of each system together.",
            "reference":"" 
        },
        {
          "question": "A heat engine receives heat from a source at 1200 K at a rate of 500 kJ/s and rejects the waste heat to a medium at 300 K. The power output of the heat engine is 180 kW. Determine the reversible power and the irreversibility rate for this process.",
            "answer": "\n        \n        import numpy as np\n        \n        waste = 300\n        source = 1200\n        q = 500 # volume flow rate\n        w_out = 180 # power output of heat engine\n        \n        # The reversible power for this process is the amount of power that a reversible heat engine would produce when operating between the same temperature limits, and is determined to be:\n        w_rev = (1- (waste /source)) * q \n        \n        # The irreversibility rate is the difference between the reversible power and the power output:\n        w_irrev = w_rev - w_out\n        \n        print('The reversible power for this process is str(w_rev)+' kW')\n        print('The irreversibility rate is str(w_irrev)+' kW')\n        ",
            "explanation": "This code solves for the reversible power and the irreversibility rate for work done on a heat engine. The waste is the heat rejected by the heat engine. The source is the heat received by the heat engine. The volume flow rate, q, is the rate in which the heat is received by the heat engine and the power output is the amount of work being output by the heat engine.",
            "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill. page number 429. chapter 8, example number 8-3"
        },
        {
            "question": "How do you determine the forces acting on a submerged wedge?",
            "answer": "First define your coordinate system. Then consider the two type of forces acting on the wedge: the pressure forces acting on each surface and the weight of the wedge. For a fully submerged wedge the pressure forces acting in all directions will be equal.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "What are the different types of pressure?",
            "answer": "The gauge pressure is the relative pressure with respect to the atmosphere. Stagnation pressure is the pressure of a fluid when the velocity is 0. Static pressure is a general term used to describe the relative pressure at any point in a fluid. Dynamic pressure is the pressure dependent on flow velocity represented as q=(1/2)(rho)(v^2)",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "What assumptions must we make to apply Bernoulli's equation?",
            "answer": "Flow must be inviscid. We neglect the effect of gravity. And there is no fluid motion (acceleration).",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "What is the correct definition of temperature?",
            "answer": "Bodies that are in thermal equilibrium with one another must share a common property which we call temperature.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "What does it mean if a process is isentropic?",
            "answer": "It means that the total change in entropy of a system is equal to 0 and that the process is both reversible and adiabatic (heat exchange is equal to 0).",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "What are the Tds equations and how are they used?",
            "answer": "The integration of the Tds equations can be used to calculate the change in entropy. Tds = dU + pdV. Tds = dH - Vdp",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "What are some of the relationships between c_p, c_v, and gamma?",
            "answer": "c_p/c_v = gamma. c_p - c_v = R (gas constant). gamma = 1.4 under standard conditions.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "What are the different types of variable nozzle flows?",
            "answer": "When the area is increasing in a nozzle and the mach number is less than 1, the velocity decreases in a subsonic diffuser. When the mach number is greater than one with an increasing area, the velocity increases in a supersonic nozzle. When the area decreases with the flow and the mach number is less than 1, the velocity increases in a subsonic nozzle. When the area decreases at a mach number greater than 1, the change in velocity decreases at a supersonic diffuser.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "What is choked flow and why does it happen?",
            "answer": "Choked flow means that the mass flow rate through a converging nozzle will not increase no matter how much the exit static pressure is reduced. This happens at the speed of sound (Mach 1) because the lines of communication between the entry and exit static pressures are lost.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "Upstream of an airfoil, flow has a velocity of 20 m/s and a temperature of 200 K. There is no external work and no heat transfer in the flow. What is the stagnation temperature at the airfoil. Assume c_p = 100.",
            "answer": "\n            import numpy as np\n            \n            v1 = 20 # velocity (m/s)\n            t1 = 200 # temperature (K)\n            c_p = 100 #molar heat capacity at constant pressure\n            \n            # start with the steady flow energy equation\n            # q - w = (h_2 + (1/2)((v_2)^2+)+(gz_2))-(h_1 + (1/2)((v_1)^2+)+(gz_1))\n            # we know q, w, effects of gravity, and v_2 are all equal to 0.\n            # we are left with h_2 = h_1 + (1/2)(v_1)^2\n            # we know that enthalpy (h) is equal to T(c_p)\n            # substituting in, we have T_2 = T_1 + ((v_1)^2)/(2*(c_p))\n            t2 = t1 + ((v_1**2) / (2 * c_p))\n            \n            print('Stagnation temperature at the airfoil:' t2, 'Kelvin')\n            ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the stagnation temperature at an airfoil in steady flow using the steady flow energy equation and known temperature, velocity, and specific heat capacity of the flow under constant pressure at some distance upstream of the airfoil.",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "Consider a control volume with an inlet area double that of it's exit area. If the velocity of the flow going into the control volume is 25 m/s, what is the velocity of the flow exiting the tube. Assume the flow is inviscid",
            "answer": "\n            import numpy as np\n            \n            v1 = 25 #inlet velocity (m/s)\n            \n            # mass flow in is equal to mass flow out\n            # rho * v1 * A1 = rho * v2 * A2 (conservation of mass)\n            # rho * v1 * (2A) = rho * v2 * A\n            v2 = 2 * v1 #canceling rho and A on both sides\n            \n            print('The velocity of the flow exiting the tube:', v2, 'm/s')\n            ",
            "explanation": "This code utilizes the conservation of mass equation stating that the mass flow in is equal to the mass flow out. Then recognizing that mass flow is equal to (density) * (area) * (velocity)",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "Consider a pitot-static tube in incompressible flow. The static pressure is 1 bar, the fluid velocity is 20 m/s and the density is 1.2 kg/m^3. Calculate the velocity and pressure measured by the pitot-static tube whe the flow is moving perpendicular to the tube's opening and when the flow is moving parallel to the tube's opening.",
            "answer": "\n            import numpy as np\n            \n            v0 = 20 #velocity m/s\n            p = 1 #pressure is 1 bar\n            rho = 1.2\n            \n            pressure = p + ((1/2) * (v0**2) * rho) # pressure read by the tube when the flow is parallel calculated due to Bernoulli's principle\n            \n            print('Velocity when flow is perpendicular:', v0, 'm/s. Pressure when flow is perpendicular:', p, 'bar') \n            print('Velocity when flow is parallel: 0 m/s. Pressure when flow is parallel:', pressure, 'bar.')\n            ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the pressure and velocity measured by a pitot-static tube in two different flow conditions. When the flow is moving perpendicular to the tube, the velocity measured is the velocity of the flow and the pressure measured is the static pressure. However, when the flow is moving parallel to the tube's opening the velocity stagnates and is 0 while the pressure can be worked out using Bernoulli's principle.",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "Consider a process in which 100J of heat is added to a system and 250J of work is done on a system. Calculate the change in energy of the system.",
            "answer": "\n            import numpy as np\n            \n            Q = 100 # positive because heat is being added to the system (Joules)\n            W = -250 # negative because work is being done on the system (Joules)\n            \n            # First law of thermodynamics\n            dE = Q - W\n            \n            print('The total change in energy of the system:', dE, 'Joules')\n            ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the change in energy of a system using the first law of thermodynamics: dE = Q - W where Q is heat exchange and W is work done.",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "A cyclic heat engine receives 600J of heat from a hot body while discharging 200J of heat to a cold body. Assume there is no change in internal energy of the system. What is the efficiency of this heat engine?",
            "answer": "\n            import numpy as np\n            \n            Q1 = 600 # energy entering the heat engine (Joules)\n            Q2 = 200 # energy leaving the heat engine (Joules)\n            \n            # Because there is no change in internal energy, we can write work = dQ from the first law of thermodynamics\n            W = Q1 - Q2\n            # efficiency of a system is given as:\n            efficiency = W/Q1\n            \n            print('The efficiency of the cyclic heat engine:', efficiency)\n            ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the efficiency of a cyclic heat engine using the fact that: efficiency = work / Q1. We were able to find the work done by using the first law of the thermodynamics: dE = Q - W. Noting that dE equals 0, we are left with dQ = W.",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
          "question": "A system starts at 300K and increasing in temperature to 600K. The change in entropy of the system is found to be 50 J/K and changes linearly with temperature. What is the change in heat energy of the system?",
          "answer": "\n          import numpy as np\n          \n          T1 = 300 # initial temperature of the system (Kelvin)\n          T2 = 600 # final temperature of the system (kelvin)\n          dS = 50 # change in entropy of the system (Joules/Kelvin)\n          \n          dT = T2 - T1 # change in temperature of the system\n          # the change in heat energy is found by taking the area under the curve of a T-S diagram\n          top_part = (1/2) * dT * dS # triangular part of the graph\n          bottom_part = T1 * dS\n          total_heat = top_part + bottom_part\n          \n          print('Change in heat energy of the system:', total_heat, 'Joules')\n          ",
          "explanation": "This code calculates the change in heat energy of a system utilizing the fact the change in heat energy can be calculated by finding the area under a T-S curve. We found the area under the triangular part of the curve and then the area under the rectangular part of th curve and added them together to find the total.",
          "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "Consider flow with a mach number of 1.2 traveling at 400 m/s. What is the temperature of the flow? Assume gamma is 1.4.",
            "answer": "\n            import numpy as np\n            \n            M = 1.2 # mach number\n            v = 400 # velocity of the flow (m/s)\n            gamma = 1.4\n            R = 8.3145 # specific gas constant\n            \n            # velocity is equal to mach number times the speed of sound (a)\n            # a = sqrt(gamma * R * T)\n            a = v / M # a is the speed of sound\n            T = (a**2)/(gamma * R)\n            \n            print('The temperature of the flow:', T, 'Kelvin')\n            ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the temperature of flow recognizing that: mach number = velocity/speed of sound, and that: speed of sound = sqrt(gamma * R * temperature).",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "Calculate the change in entropy per kilogram as air is heated from 300 to 600 K while pressure drops from 400 to 300 kPa.",
            "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n\n      T1 = 300 # Initial Temperature (K)\n     T2 = 600 # Final Temperature (K)\n     P1 = 400 # Initial Pressure (kPa)\n     P2 = 300 # Final Pressure (kPa)\n     Cp = 1.005 # Specific heat capacity at constant pressure (kJ/kg-K)\n     R = 0.287 # Specific Gas constant (kJ/kg-K)\n\n      # Using equation for Entropy changes for perfect gases, ds = s2 - s1\n     ds = Cp*np.log(T2/T1) - R*np.log(P2/P1)\n\n     print('The change in specific entropy of air is: ', ds, 'kJ/kg-K')\n      ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the change in specific entropy as the temperature and pressure of air are varied. It employs the perfect gas relations with the equation for entropy change",
              "reference": "Fundamentals of Thermodynamics, 8th Edition, by Borgnakke and Sonntag, page 275."
          },
          {
            "question": "A cylinder fitted with a piston has an initial volume of 0.1 m3 and contains nitrogen at 150 kPa, 25 C. The piston is moved, compressing the nitrogen until the pressure is 1 MPa and the temperature is 150 C. During this compression process heat is transferred from the nitrogen, and the work done on the nitrogen is 20 kJ. Determine the amount of this heat transfer",
            "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n\n      V = 0.1 # Initial volume (m^3)\n     P1 = 150 # Inital pressure (kPa)\n     P2 = 1 # Final pressure (MPa)\n     T1 = 25 # Initial temperature (C)\n     T2 = 150 # Final temperature (C)\n     W = -20 # Work done (kJ)\n     R = 0.2968 # Specfic gas constant for Nitrogen (kJ/kg-K)\n     Cv = 0.745 # Specific heat constant at constant volume for Nitrogen (kJ/kg-K)\n\n     # Using ideal gas relations, pV = mRT, can find mass of nitrogen\n     m = (P1*V)/(R*(T1+273.15))\n\n     # From the equations for first law and internal energy, dQ -dW = dU, du = Cv * dT\n     Q = m *Cv*(T2-T1) + W\n\n     print('The heat transfer due to compression from the nitrogen is: ', Q, 'kJ')\n      ",
            "explanation": "Here, the code calculates the amount of heat transfer done during the compression process of a piston. It uses the ideal gas relation, pV = mRT, and the first law of thermodynamics Q - W = U, where U is the internal energy.",
              "reference": "Fundamentals of Thermodynamics, 8th Edition, by Borgnakke and Sonntag, page 119."
          },
          {
            "question": "A flow of air has velocity of 850 m/s, pressure of 130 kPa, and temperature at 180 C. Compute the pressure and temperature of the air if brought isentropically to rest.",
            "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n\n     Cp = 1005 # Specific heat capacity of air at constant pressure (J/kg-K)\n     gamma = 1.4 # Specific heat ratio of air\n     V1 = 850 # Inital velocity of air (m/s)\n     P1 = 130 # Initial pressure of air (kPa)\n     T1 = 180 # Initial temperature of air (C)\n\n     # Stagnation temperature due to steady isentropic process\n     T2 = (T1 + 273.15) + (V1**2)/(2*Cp)\n\n     # Stagnation pressure using isentropic relations\n     P2 = P1*(T2/(T1 + 273.15))**((gamma)/(gamma - 1))\n\n     print ('The stagnation temperature and pressure of air due to isentropic process is ', T2, 'K, ',P2, 'kPa, respectively' )\n      ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the stagnation temperature and pressure which is if it were brought to zero velocity by steady isentropic process with no external work. With these assumptions, we use the equation for stagnation temperature, T01 = T1 + v1^2/2Cp. And to find stagnation pressure, we use the isentropic relations between pressure and temperature, p0/p1 = (T0/T1)^(k/k-1), where k is the specific heat ratio, gamma.",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "A chemical is flowing through a pipe with 90° bend, with a mass flow of 200 kg/s. Its incoming velocity (uniform) is 2 m/s, and its outgoing velocity is 3 m/s. What is the net force exerting on the fluid and its magnitude?",
            "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n\n     mdot = 200 # Mass flow rate (kg/s)\n     V1 = 2 # Incoming velocity (m/s)\n     V2 = 3 # Outgoing velocity (m/s)\n\n     # Momentum flux and conservation of mass, find force compenents\n     Fx = mdot * (0 - V1)\n     Fy = mdot * (V2 - 0)\n     Fz = 0\n     Fnet = [Fx, Fy, Fz]\n\n     # Magnitude of net force\n     Fmag = np.sqrt(Fx**2 + Fy**2 + Fz**2)\n\n     Force = ['Fx', 'Fy', 'Fz']\n\n      print ('The net force exerting on the fluid is:', Force, '= ', Fnet, 'N and the magnitude is:',Fmag ,'N' )\n      ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the net force exerting on the fluid around a bend. Assuming incoming velocity is in the positive x direction and outgoing velocity is in the positive y direction, we can find individual components of force using the momentum flux equation (Fx = mDotOut * vOut - mDotIn * vIn) and idea of concervation of mass (mDotOut = mDotIn). We can assume flow is inviscid.",
              "reference": "Jack B. Evett, Cheng Liu, 2500 Solved Problems in Fluid mechanics and Hydraulics, Revised First Edition."
          },
          {
            "question": "A needle nose projectile traveling at a speed of M = 3 passes 200m above an observer. Find the projectiles velocity and determine how far beyond the observer the projectile will first be heard.",
            "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n\n     M = 3 # Mach number of projectile\n     h = 200 # Height of projectile (m)\n     k = 1.4 # Specific heat ratio (gamma)\n     R = 287 # Specific gas constant of air (J/kg-K)\n\n     # Assuming the temperature of air is room temperature\n     T = 300 # (K)\n\n     # Speed of sound (m/s)\n     a = np.sqrt(k*R*T)\n\n     # Velocity of projectile (m/s)\n     V = M*a\n\n     # Wave angle calculation (rad)\n     u = np.arcsin(1/M)\n\n     # Distance of sound heard beyond observer\n     x = (h)/(np.tan(u))\n\n     print('The velocity of the projectile is: ',V, 'm/s')\n     print('The distance beyond the observer which projectile is first heard is: ', x, 'm')\n      ",
            "explanation": "This code involves a projectile moving at supersonic speed which creates a mach wave. Knowing the air conditions, the speed of sound can be calculated using a = sqrt(kRT). Thus, the velocity of the projectile can be found. Given the observer is stationary, the wave angle can be calculated using u = sin-1(1/M) and with trigonometry, the distance of the heard projectile is found using tan(u) = h/x.",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "Water enters a stationary lawn sprinkler through its base at the steady rate of 1000 ml/s. The exit area of each of the two nozzles is 30 mm^2. Determine the average speed of water leaving the nozzle.",
            "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n\n     Q = 0.001 # Volumetric flow rate (m^3/s) = 1000/10^6\n     A = 30/(10**6) # Area of nozzles (m^2)\n\n     # Conservation of mass (Continuity), A2*v2 + A3*v3 - A1*v1 = 0\n     # A2 = A3 and v2 = v3. Therefore, average velocity of water exiting the nozzle is\n     velNozzle = Q/(2*A)\n\n     print ('The velocity of water leaving the nozzle is: ',velNozzle, 'm/s')\n      ",
            "explanation": "First, assume that flow is steady and incompressible. Then, by continuity the mass flow rate entering the sprinkler and exiting sprinkler is equal, A2*v2 + A3*v3 - A1*v1 = 0, density cancels out as it is constant throughout. Knowing the volumetric flow rate entering equal to Q = A1*v1 and that the areas of the nozzles are equal, we arrive at the equation above.",
              "reference": "Fundamentals of Fluid Mechanics, Sixth edition, Bruce R. Munson, Donald F. Young, page 197."
          },
          {
            "question": "Suppose you have two blocks of copper, each of heat capacity 200 J/K. Initially one block has a uniform temperature of 300 K and the other 310 K. Calculate the entropy change that occurs when you place the two blocks in thermal contact with one another and surround them with perfect thermal insulation. Is the sign of delta S consistent with the second law? (Assume the process occurs at constant volume.",
            "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n\n     Cv = 200 # Heat capacity at constant volume (J/K)\n     Tc = 300 # Temperature of the cooler block (K)\n     Th = 310 # Temperature of the warmer block (K)\n\n     # Final equiliubrium temperature of blocks\n     Teq = (Tc + Th)/2\n\n     # Entropy changes of individual blocks\n     Sc = Cv * np.log(Teq/Tc)\n     Sh = Cv * np.log(Teq/Th)\n\n     # Total entropy change\n     Stot = Sc + Sh\n\n     print('The entropy change of the cooler and warmer block are: ',Sc, 'J/K and', Sh, 'J/K, respectively.')\n     print('The total entropy change is: ',Stot, 'J/k which is positive as predicted by the second law for irreversible process in isolated systems.')\n      ",
            "explanation": "Since the blocks have equal heat capacities, a given quantity of heat transfer from the warmer to the cooler block causes temperature changes that are equal in magnitude and of opposite signs. The final equilibrium temperature is 305 K, the average of the initial values. When the temperature of one of the blocks changes reversibly from T1 to T2 , the entropy change is given by dS = integral(Cv*dT/T) from T1 to T2 == Cv*ln(T2/T1). The infinitesimal entropy production due to irreverisibility cannot be negative.",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "Discuss the implications of entropy generation in irreversible processes and its relationship to the second law of thermodynamics.",
            "answer": "Entropy represents the thermal energy's inability to perform useful work. In irreversible processes, entropy generation occurs due to dissipative phenomena like turbulence and friction, moving systems towards thermodynamic equilibrium, where entropy is maximized. The second law of thermodynamics asserts that in an isolated system, entropy always increases for irreversible processes and remains constant for reversible ones. The Clausius inequality further states that entropy production due to irreversibility is always positive.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "Discuss the concept of shock waves and expansion fans and their impact on flow properties.",
            "answer": "Shock waves are caused when flow velocity exceeds the speed of sound and/or there is an abrupt decrease in flow area. Across a shock, static pressure, temperature, and density increase almost instantaneously and the mach number decreases. Expansion fans occur when flow passes a convex corner and the changes in flow properties are opposite of shocks. Because flow accross shocks is non-isentropic, total pressure downstream of the shock is less than upstream. As expansions fans are isentropic, the total pressure remains constant.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "Explain how Bernoulli's equation applies to parallel and curved streamlines. How does pressure vary in bends? Under what conditions is it valid?",
            "answer": "For this, neglect the effects of gravity. In parallel streamlines, dp/dr = 0, meaning there is no pressure gradient and the equation is simply P + 1/2*rho*v^2 = const. In curved streamlines of radius r, dp/dr = rho*(v^2/r) where v is the tangential velocity, there is a pressure gradient across the streamlines. Therefore, having this additional term, outside a bend as the radius is larger, the pressure is larger. Bernoulli's equation is only valid for flows that are steady, incompressible, and inviscid (no flow friction).",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "What is the difference between a system and a control volume, why is it important?",
            "answer": "A system is a region of space in which the mass remains constant, meaning mass cannot cross the system boundary. It can also alter its shape and volume. In control volumes mass is allowed to cross its boundaries but cannot alter its shape of volume. However, it can move at constant speed. A system can be applied to a piston containing gas under compression and expansion to find the work done and heat transferred. And in fluid flow, control volumes are easier to apply when mass is flowing into and out of a control volume. ",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "Explain static, dynamic, stagnation pressure and how they relate in a pitot-static probe?",
            "answer": "Static pressure,p, is the actual pressure at any given point in the flow. It is the pressure measured using a tube placed perpendicular to the flow. Stagnation temperature, p0, is the maximum pressure a fluid can reach when brought to rest isentropically with mechanical losses, i.e., p0 = p + 1/2 * density * velocity^2. It is measured by a pitot-tube facing directly towards the flow at which the fluid velocity is zero at the tube opening. Dynamic pressure is found by taking the stagnation pressure minus the static pressure. Pitot-static probes are placed on aircraft to calculate its speed using Bernoulli's equation.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "Consider a cyclic heat engine operating between two heat reservoirs at different temperatures. Explain how the efficiency of the engine changes if the temperature of the cold reservoir is increased while keeping the temperature of the hot reservoir constant.",
            "answer": "First, given the parameters, assume the process is reversible. The efficiency of a heat engine is given by the ratio of the work output to the heat input. For reversible processes, we can write the efficiency,n, as n = 1 - Tc/Th, where Tc and Th are temperatures of the cold and hot reservoir respectively. As the temperature of the cold reservoir (Tc) is increased while keeping the temperature of the hot reservoir (Th) constant, the efficiency of the engine decreases. This is because the temperature difference (Th - Tc) decreases. ",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "How is choked flow achieved in a convergent nozzle and what are its implications?",	
            "answer": "The fluid velocity can be manipulated by changing the exit static pressure. Choked flow occurs when the fluid reaches Mach 1 at the throat. To achieve Mach 1, the exit static pressure is decreased until the ratio of inlet stagnation pressure over exit static pressure reaches around 1.893. Once you hit Mach 1, flow velocity cannot increase further, even if the exit static pressure decreases. Therefore, the mass flow rate cannot increase and reaches its maximum.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "How and why does an increase in the skin friction coefficient affect flow conditions in Fanno flow?",
            "answer": "The increase in friction represents greater wall shear stress as given by the equation Cf = t/(1/2*rho*v^2) where t is the wall shear stress. As t increases, the pressure drop along a duct increases due to larger pressure losses given by dp/dx = -4t/D. As friction serves to reduce the effective area, the choked flow conditions will be reached at a shorter duct length.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "On a T-s diagram, compare the constant pressure and volume lines. How are isentropic processes related?",
            "answer": "For constant pressure, dp = 0, therefore the Tds equation simplifies to (dT/ds) = T/Cp, showing that the constant pressure line has a positive slope. As temperature increases, the slope increases. For constant volume, the Tds equation is (dT/ds) = T/Cv. Since, Cv < Cp for a perfect gas, the constant volume line is steeper. An isentropic compression process is represented as a vertical line from a lower constant pressure line to a higher one. The opposite is true for an isentropic expansion process.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "When will a cyclic heat engine experience it’s maximum efficiency?",
            "answer": "A cyclic heat engine will experience its maximum efficiency when the system is reversible. This is explained in Carnot's theorem, where assuming the opposite was true will violate the conservation of energy.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference": "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carnot's_theorem_(thermodynamics)"
          },
          {
            "question": "How is pressure from a fluid affected by wall shape?",
            "answer": "The pressure on the wall supporting the fluid depends solely on the current depth, and it has a linear relationship with depth (p = ρgz).",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference": ""
          },
          {
            "question": "What are the primary differences between normal shocks, oblique shocks, and expansion fans?",
            "answer": "Oblique shocks are similar to normal shocks, but they occur when the flow hits an incline. Expansion fans occur when the flow drops at an angle. The characteristics across the shock wave are the same for normal shocks and oblique shocks, while it is the opposite for expansion fans. While normal shocks and oblique shocks have similar characteristics, the calculations for the relationships (p, ρ, p0, and h) are different.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference": ""
          },
          {
            "question": "What are the distinctions between perfect gases and non-perfect gases?",
            "answer": "A feature that perfect gases have that non-perfect gases lack are constant values for cp and cv. If a gas isn’t perfect, it’s specific heat capacities will vary with temperature and volume, making problem solving more tedious. Most problems you will encounter will assume the gas you’re working with is ideal and/or perfect..",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference": ""
          },  
          {
            "question": "What conditions must be met for a process to be isentropic?",
            "answer": "For a process to be isentropic, it must also be reversible and adiabatic. For a process to be reversible, it must be able to return to its initial state. This means there can’t be any dissipative effects in the system (such as shear) implying that dSirrev = 0. For a process to be adiabatic there cannot be any heat transfers, so Q = 0. Processes that occur quickly are typically adiabatic. If two of the three are true (isentropic, reversible, or adiabatic) are true then the other is also true.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill"
          },
          {
            "question": "Why can there only be processes that increase entropy in an isolated system?",
            "answer": "The full second law of Thermodynamics is dS = dq/T +dsirrev. dSirrev can only increase entropy, and in a closed system there is no heat transfer, so dq = 0. The second law gets turned into dS ≥ 0, showing that only processes that increase entropy can take place.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill"
          },   
          {
            "question": "When is Bernoulli's Equation to be applicable",
            "answer": "The Bernoulli's Equation (p+ ρgz+0.5ρv^2 = constant) can only be used across a streamline in inviscid, incompressible flow. It can only be used in inviscid incompressible flow because Bernoulli derived from the momentum equation, which uses those assumptions.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill"
          },
          {
            "question": "Why are there two types of oblique shocks and which one is used?",
            "answer": "There are two types of shock solutions than can occur when the angle of the inclined surface is less than the max angle.  On β-θ graphs there will be two β’s for every θ. The smaller one is called the weak shock and the larger one is called the strong shock. In nature the weak shock occurs the majority of the time, so it should be used in problem solving.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference": "John D. Anderson, Christopher P. Cadou (2024) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill"
          },
          {
            "question": "What are the common thermodynamic processes?.",
            "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n      import matplotlib.pyplot as plt\n      #Isobaric\n      x1 = np.linspace(1, 10, 10)\n      y1 = x1*0 +5\n      plt.plot(x1,y1,'r')\n      #Isochoric\n      y2 = np.linspace(0, 10, 10)\n      x2 = y2*0 + 5\n      plt.plot(x2,y2,'g')\n      #Isothermal\n      x3 = np.linspace(1, 10, 20)\n      y3 = 10/x3\n      plt.plot(x3,y3,'b')\n      #Isentropic\n      x4 = np.linspace(1, 10, 20)\n      y4 = 10/(x4**1.4)\n      plt.plot(x4,y4,'c')\n      #Set up the plot\n      plt.xlabel('V')\n      plt.ylabel('p')\n      plt.xticks([])\n      plt.yticks([])\n      plt.show()\n      ",
            "explanation": "The common thermodynamic processes you’ll encounter are the following: Isochoric (green) means the volume is constant, Isobaric (red) means the pressure is constant, Isothermal (blue) means the temperature is constant, and Isentropic (cyan) means there is no change in entropy. Here are the processes on a p-V diagram. Following the polytropic relationship (pV^n = C), the isentropic curve is steeper because n = y instead of n = 0 for a isothermal process. These relationships assume that the gas is perfect.",
            "reference": "https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polytropic_process"
          },
          {
            "question": "What is the final temperature of an isentropic system when the initial temperature is 400K, the initial pressure is 610 Pa, the final pressure is 920Pa, and y = 1.67? Assume the gas is ideal.",
            "answer": "\n      T1 = 400 #Initial Temp (K)\n      P1 = 610 #Initial Pressure (Pa)\n      P2 = 920 #Final Pressure (Pa)\n      y = 1.67 #Heat Capacity Ratio\n\n      #New temperature of an isentropc process\n      T2 = T1*((P2/P1)**((y-1)/y))\n      print('Final temperature of the gas is:', T2, 'K')\n      ",
            "explanation": "The isentropic relation for p and T is given by (p2/p1) = (T2/T1)^y/(y-1). Rearranging this yields T2 = T1(p2/p1)^(y-1)/y. ",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "Calculate the stagnation temperature if the initial temperature is 220K, R = 287 J/Kg*K, and velocity is 3 km/s.",
            "answer": "\n      T1 = 220 #Inital Temp (K)\n      v = 3000 #velocity (m/s)\n      R = 287 #Specific Gas Constant (J/kg*K)\n      y = 1.4 #Specific Heat Capacity Ratio\n\n      #speed of sound\n      a = (y*R*T1)**0.5\n      #Mach Number\n      M = v/a\n      #Stagnation Temp\n      T01 = T1*(1+(((y-1)**2)/2)*(M**2))\n      print('The stagnation temperature of the gas is:', T01, 'K')\n      ",
            "explanation": "The speed of sound squared is given by the equation a^2=yRT. Taking the square root of it gives the speed of sound, and the Mach number can be calculated with the speed of sound and velocity, M = v/a. From there the stagnation temperature is given by the equation (T01/T1) = 1+ (y-1)*M^2/2. Multiplying both sides by the initial temperature will provide the stagnation temperature",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "What is the heat addition in an isochoric process that goes from 500Pa to 750Pa? R = 287, m = 60kg, V = 10m^3, cv = 717.7 J/(kg·K), and assume it is a perfect gas",
            "answer": "\n      #inital conditions\n      p1 = 500 #Initial Pressure (Pa)\n      p2 = 750 #Final Pressure (Pa)\n      V = 10 #Volume (m^3)\n      m = 60 #mass (kg)\n      R = 287 #Specific Gas Constant (J/kg*K)\n      cv = 717.7 #Specefic heat (J/(kg·K))\n\n      #calculate the inital temperature\n      T1 = (p1*V)/(m*R)\n      #calculate the final temperature\n      T2 = (p2*V)/(m*R)\n      #calculate the heat\n      Q = m*cv*(T2-T1)\n      print('The heat addition to the system is:', Q, 'J')\n      ",
            "explanation": "An isochoric process means the volume is constant. Using the ideal gas formula the initial temperature can be found, T1=p1v/mR. Because the volume is constant, the final temperature can also be found using the same method. The first law of Thermodynamics applied to isochoric processes is Q=m*cv(T2-T1), giving you the heat addition to the system.",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "What is the change of internal energy of a isochoric process that changes from 330K to 520K? cv = 717.7 J/(kg·K), and m = 27kg. Assume the gas is perfect.",
            "answer": "\n      #initial conditions\n      T1 = 330 #Temperature (K)\n      T2 = 520 #Temperature (K)\n      cv = 717.7 #Specefic heat (J/(kg·K))\n      m = 27 #Mass (kg)\n\n      #change of internal energy\n      dU = m*cv*(T2-T1)\n      print('The change of internal energy is:', dU, 'J')\n      ",
            "explanation": "The definition of the specific heat at constant volume is cv = du/dT. Rearranging and multiplying mass will give dU =mcvdT.",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "Calculate the Mach number behind a normal shockwave from a fighter jet traveling at 536 m/s at a temperature of 190K. Assume the air acts as a perfect gas, R = 287 J/kg*K, and y = 1.4.",
            "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n      import matplotlib.pyplot as plt\n      #inital conditions\n      T = 190 #Inital Temp (K)\n      v = 536 #velocity (m/s)\n      R = 287 #Specific Gas Constant (J/kg*K)\n      y = 1.4 #Specific Heat Capacity Ratio\n\n      #speed of sound\n      a = (y*R*T)**0.5\n      #Mach number\n      M1 = v/a\n\n      #New Mach number\n      M2 = ((1+((y-1)*M1**2)/2)/(y*M1**2-(y-1)/2))**2\n      print('The Mach number is:', M2)\n\n      #graph of the mach number\n      x = np.linspace(1,9,20)\n      y = ((1+((y-1)*x**2)/2)/(y*x**2-(y-1)/2))**2\n      plt.plot(x,y,'b')\n      plt.xlabel('M1')\n      plt.ylabel('M2')\n      plt.title('M1 vs M2')\n      ",
            "explanation": "To find the Mach number behind the normal shock, the current Mach number is needed, which can be calculated by M = v/a. The speed of sound, a can be found by a=(yRT)^0.5, giving a = 276.3 m/s. The Mach number then, is 1.94. The normal shock equation for the Mach number behind the shock wave is M2^2 = (1+(y-1)M1^2/2)/(yM1^2-(y01)/2). Plugging in the values and taking the square root of the answer gives M2 = 0.12. When the Mach number is above Mach 1, the Mach number behind the shock wave rapidly decreases, and is subsonic. The graph displays this relationship.",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "What is the pressure after an oblique shock wave given that M1 = 3, θ = 26, p1 = 900Pa, and y = 1.4.",
            "answer": "\n      import numpy as np\n      import matplotlib.pyplot as plt\n      #initial conditions\n      M1 = 3 #Mach number\n      theta = 26 #Incline angle (degrees)\n      p1 = 900 #initial pressure (Pa)\n      y = 1.4 #Specific Heat Capacity Ratio\n      beta = 45.55 #Oblique shock angle (from table)\n\n      #calculate the oblique shock Mach number\n      Mn1 = M1*np.sin(beta)\n      #calculate the pressure\n      p2 = p1*(1+(2*y*((Mn1**2)-1))/(y+1))\n      print('The pressure after the shockwave is:', p2, 'Pa')\n\n      #graph the pressure\n      x=np.linspace(1,9,20)\n      y = p1*(1+(2*y*((x**2)-1))/(y+1))\n      plt.plot(x,y,'r')\n      plt.xlabel('Mn1')\n      plt.ylabel('p')\n      plt.title('Mn1 vs p')\n      ",
            "explanation": "According to the weak oblique shock wave angle table, given the initial conditions, β = 45.55. From there the oblique shock wave Mach number can be calculated by Mn1 = M1sinβ. From there the oblique shock relation for pressure can be used, p2/p1 = 1+2y(Mn1^2-1)/(y+1), giving p2 = 9300. Unlike expansion fans, the pressure increases after the oblique shock, and increases as the Mach number increases as shown in the graph.",
            "reference": "https://www.iist.ac.in/sites/default/files/people/IN12177/Gas%20tables_v2.pdf"
          },
             {
            "question": "Find T2 if w = 3000 J/s, Q1 = 1820J, and T1 = 425K for a reversible, cyclic heat engine..",
            "answer": "\n      #inital conditions\n      W = 3000 #Work (J/s)\n      Q1 = 1820 #Heat (J)\n      T1 = 425 #Temperature\n      #calculate Q2\n      Q2 = Q1-W\n      #calculate T2\n      T2 = Q2*T1/Q1\n      print('T2 equals:', T2, 'K')\n      ",
            "explanation": "For a cyclic heat engine, w =Q1-Q2, so Q2 equals Q1 – W. Since the heat engine is also reversible the relationship Q2/Q1=T2/T1 can be used. Multiplying both sides by T1 will grant T2 = -276K.",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "What is the Reynolds number for a flow with a velocity of 5 m/s, characteristic length of 0.2 m, and kinematic viscosity of 1e-6 m^2/s?",
            "answer": "\n            import numpy as np\n\n            velocity = 5 # velocity of flow (m/s)\n            length = 0.2 # characteristic length (m)\n            viscosity = 1 * 10**-6 # Kinematic viscosity (m^2/s)\n\n            # Calculate Reynolds number using the formula: Re = (velocity * length) / viscosity\n\n            Re = (velocity * length) / viscosity\n\n            print('The Reynolds number for this flow is :', Re)\n            ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the Reynolds number for a flow using the formula, which relates flow velocity, characteristic length, and kinematic viscosity. The Reynolds number is a dimensionless quantity used to characterize the flow regime.",
            "reference": "Michael A. Boles, Yunus A Çengel, (2024) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw-Hill."
        },
        {
            "question": "A fluid with a density of 900 kg/m^3 flows through a pipe with a diameter of 0.1 m at a velocity of 4 m/s. What is the dynamic viscosity of the fluid if the Reynolds number is 1440?",
            "answer": "\n          import numpy as np\n         \n         rho = 900 # Density of fluid (kg/m^3)\n         diameter = 0.1 # Diameter of pipe (m)\n         velocity = 4 # Velocity of flow (m/s)\n         Re = 1440 # Reynolds number\n         \n         # Calculate dynamic viscosity using the formula: Re = (density * velocity * diameter) / viscosity\n         \n         viscosity = (rho * velocity * diameter) / Re\n         \n         print('Dynamic viscosity of the fluid is:', viscosity, 'Pa*s')\n         ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the dynamic viscosity of the fluid using the formula derived from the Reynolds number equation. It rearranges the equation to solve for viscosity, which is a measure of the resistance to flow.",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "A tank contains 300 liters of air at a pressure of 200 kPa and temperature of 300 K. What is the mass of the air in the tank? (Assume ideal gas behavior)",
            "answer": "\n          import numpy as np\n         \n         volume = 300 / 1000 # Convert liters to cubic meters\n         pressure = 200 # Pressure (kPa)\n         R_specific = 287 # Specific gas constant for air (J/kg*K)\n         temperature = 400 # Temperature (K)\n         \n         # Calculate mass using PV=mRT\n         \n         mass = pressure * volume / (R_specific * temperature)\n         \n         print('Mass of air in the tank:', mass, 'kg')\n          ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the mass of air in the tank using the ideal gas law, which relates pressure, volume, temperature, and the gas constant. It rearranges the ideal gas law equation to solve for mass.",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "Calculate the power required to pump water through a pipe at a rate of 0.05 m^3/s against a head of 30 meters. (Assume water density = 1000 kg/m^3 and acceleration due to gravity = 9.81 m/s^2)",
            "answer": "\n          import numpy as np\n         \n         flow_rate = 0.005 # Flow rate (m^3/s)\n         head = 30 # Head (m)\n         rho_water = 1000 # Density of water (kg/m^3)\n         g = 9.81 # (m/s^2)\n         \n         # Calculate power using the formula: Power = flow rate * head * density * gravity\n         \n         power = flow_rate * head * rho_water * g\n         \n         print('Power required to pump water:', power, 'Watts')\n          ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the power required to pump water through a pipe using the formula for hydraulic power, which relates flow rate, head, density, and acceleration due to gravity.",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "An ideal gas undergoes an isentropic process where the initial temperature is 300 K and the final temperature is 200 K. If the initial volume is 0.5 m^3, what is the final volume of the gas?",
            "answer": "\n          import numpy as np\n         \n         T_0 = 300 # Initial temperature (K)\n         T = 200 # Final temperature (K)\n         V_0 = 0.5 # Initial volume (m^3)\n         \n         # Calculate final volume using the ideal gas law for isentropic process\n         \n         V = V_0 * (T_0 / T)\n         \n         print('Final volume of the gas', V, 'm^3')\n          ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the final volume of the gas undergoing an isentropic process using the ideal gas law for adiabatic processes, where temperature and volume are inversely proportional.",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "Calculate the Mach number of a gas flowing at a velocity of 300 m/s in air at standard conditions (temperature = 273 K, pressure = 101325 Pa).",
            "answer": "\n          import numpy as np\n         \n         velocity = 300 # Flow velocity (m/s)\n         temperature = 273 # Standard temperature (K)\n         pressure = 101325 # Standard pressure (Pa)\n         gamma = 1.4 # Ratio of specific heats for air\n         \n         # Calculate speed of sound using ideal gas law for air\n         \n         speed_of_sound = np.sqrt(gamma * 287 * temperature)\n         \n         # Calculate Mach number using the formula: Mach = velocity / speed_of_sound\n         \n         mach_number = velocity / speed_of_sound\n         \n         print('Mach number:', mach_number)\n          ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the Mach number of a gas flow by first determining the speed of sound using the ideal gas law for air, then dividing the flow velocity by the speed of sound.",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "Determine the angle of an oblique shock wave produced by a flow with a Mach number of 2.5 and an incident flow angle of 20 degrees with respect to the normal.",
            "answer": "\n          import numpy as np\n         \n         mach_number = 2.5 # Mach number of the flow\n         incident_angle_deg = 20 # Incident flow angle in degrees\n         \n         # Convert incident angle to radians\n         \n         incident_angle_rad = np.deg2rad(incident_angle_deg)\n         \n         # Calculate the angle of thee oblique shock using the oblique shock relations\n         \n         theta = np.arcsin(1 / mach_number * np.sqrt(((gamma + 1) / (gamma - 1)) * (mach_number**2 * np.sin(incident_angle_rad)**2 - 1)))\n         \n         # Convert angle from radians to degrees\n         \n         theta_deg = np.rad2deg(theta)\n         \n         print('Angle of the oblique shock (degrees):', theta_deg)\n          ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the angle of an oblique shock wave using the oblique shock relations, which describe the relationship between the incident flow angle, Mach number, and shock angle for compressible flow.",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "Explain the significance of the first law of thermodynamics and its implications for energy conservation.",
            "answer": "The first law of thermodynamics, also known as the law of energy conservation, states that energy cannot be created or destroyed in an isolated system; it can only change forms or be transferred between systems. This law has profound implications for understanding energy transformations and conservation principles in various physical and engineering systems. By accounting for the flow of energy into and out of a system, as well as any work done by or on the system, the first law provides a fundamental framework for analyzing heat and work interactions, as well as quantifying changes in internal energy."
        },
        {
            "question": "Describe the concept of specific heat and its importance in thermodynamics.",
            "answer": "Specific heat is a measure of the amount of heat energy required to raise the temperature of a unit mass of a substance by one degree Celsius (or one Kelvin). It is a material property that reflects the substance's ability to store and transfer thermal energy. Specific heat plays a crucial role in thermodynamics, as it governs the temperature changes associated with heat transfer processes, such as heating and cooling. By quantifying the heat capacity of substances, specific heat enables the calculation of thermal energy changes and temperature variations in systems undergoing heating or cooling."
        },
        {
            "question": "What are control volumes in fluid mechanics, and how are they used in conservation principles?",
            "answer": "Control volumes, also known as control volumes, are imaginary regions in space that are used to analyze the flow of mass, momentum, and energy in fluid mechanics. They are defined by closed surfaces or boundaries through which fluid enters and exits, allowing for the application of conservation principles, such as conservation of mass, momentum, and energy. Control volumes provide a convenient framework for studying fluid flow problems by isolating specific regions of interest and accounting for the inflow and outflow of fluid properties across their boundaries."
        },
        {
            "question": "Explain the difference between steady flow and unsteady flow in fluid mechanics, and provide examples of each.",
            "answer": "Steady flow and unsteady flow are two fundamental types of fluid flow behavior characterized by the constancy or variability of flow properties over time. In steady flow, fluid properties such as velocity, pressure, and temperature remain constant at any given point in space and do not change with time. Examples of steady flow include the flow of water through a long pipe with constant cross-sectional area or the flow of air over an aerodynamically designed wing. In contrast, unsteady flow involves variations in fluid properties over time, with flow conditions changing continuously or intermittently. Examples of unsteady flow include the startup of a pump, the filling of a tank, or the passage of a gust of wind."
        },
        {
            "question": "Discuss the significance of the Navier-Stokes equations in fluid mechanics and their role in analyzing fluid motion.",
            "answer": "The Navier-Stokes equations are a set of partial differential equations that describe the motion of viscous fluid substances. They represent the fundamental principles of fluid dynamics, accounting for the conservation of mass, momentum, and energy in fluid flows. The Navier-Stokes equations play a central role in fluid mechanics, serving as the cornerstone for mathematical modeling and numerical simulation of fluid motion phenomena. They enable engineers and scientists to predict and analyze complex flow behaviors, including turbulence, boundary layer effects, and fluid-structure interactions. Despite their importance, solving the Navier-Stokes equations analytically is often challenging, leading to the development of numerical methods and computational fluid dynamics techniques for practical applications."
        },
        {
            "question": "What is the concept of streamlines in fluid dynamics, and how are they used to visualize flow patterns?",
            "answer": "Streamlines are imaginary lines that represent the instantaneous paths followed by fluid particles in a flow field. They are tangent to the velocity vector at every point and do not intersect with each other. Streamlines provide a visual representation of the direction and magnitude of fluid motion at different locations within a flow domain. By tracing streamlines, engineers and scientists can visualize flow patterns, identify regions of acceleration or deceleration, and analyze the behavior of fluid flows around obstacles or boundaries. Streamline visualization is a valuable tool in fluid dynamics for understanding flow behavior, optimizing designs, and predicting performance in various engineering applications."
        },
        {
            "question": "Explain the concept of compressibility in fluid mechanics and its implications for flow behavior.",
            "answer": "Compressibility is a property of fluids that describes their tendency to change volume in response to changes in pressure and temperature. In fluid mechanics, compressibility becomes significant when the fluid's density changes appreciably due to variations in pressure or temperature. Compressible flow occurs when the fluid's density varies significantly across the flow domain, leading to changes in flow velocity, pressure, and temperature. Unlike incompressible flow, compressible flow involves the propagation of pressure waves and the possibility of shock formation, particularly at high flow speeds. Understanding compressibility is essential for analyzing flow phenomena in aerodynamics, gas dynamics, and other fields where changes in density play a crucial role."
        },
        {
            "question": "Describe the Coanda effect in fluid mechanics and provide examples of its practical applications.",
            "answer": "The Coanda effect is a fluid dynamics phenomenon where a fluid stream adheres to a curved surface instead of following a straight path. It occurs due to the combination of viscous forces and pressure gradients acting on the fluid particles. The Coanda effect can be observed in various natural and engineering contexts, such as the flow of air over the surface of an aircraft wing, where the curved shape of the wing causes the air to adhere to its surface, generating lift. Other examples include the design of exhaust systems, where the Coanda effect is utilized to direct airflow for improved performance, or the creation of aerodynamic spoilers and diffusers in automotive engineering to enhance vehicle stability and efficiency."
        },
        {
            "question": "How does the Magnus effect influence the motion of rotating objects in fluid flow?",
            "answer": "The Magnus effect is a phenomenon in fluid dynamics where a rotating object experiences a lift force perpendicular to the direction of fluid flow. It occurs due to the interaction between the spinning object and the surrounding fluid, leading to the generation of circulation and pressure differences. The Magnus effect is commonly observed in sports such as soccer, tennis, and baseball, where spinning balls exhibit curved trajectories or unexpected flight paths. In engineering applications, the Magnus effect can be exploited to control the motion of projectiles, improve the efficiency of rotating machinery, or enhance the aerodynamic performance of rotating blades and turbines."
        },
        {
            "question": "Generate a plot showing the variation of pressure along the length of a pipe for laminar and turbulent flow conditions.",
            "answer": "\n          import numpy as np\n         import matplotlib.pyplot as plt\n         \n         # Define pipe length and pressure profiles for laminar and turbulent flows\n         \n         pipe_length = np.linspace(0, 10, 100)\n         pressure_laminar = np.sin(pipe_length) # Example pressure profile for laminar flow\n         pressure_turbulent = np.cos(pipe_length) # Example pressure profile for turbulent flow\n         \n         # Plot pressure variation along the length of the pipe\n         \n         plt.figure(figsize=(10, 6))\n         plt.plot(pipe_length, pressure_laminar, label='Laminar Flow')\n         plt.plot(pipe_length, pressure_turbulent, label='Turbulent Flow')\n         plt.xlabel('Pipe Length')\n         plt.ylabel('Pressure')\n         plt.title('Pressure Variation in Pipe')\n         plt.legend()\n         plt.grid(True)\n         plt.show()\n          ",
            "explanation": "This code generates a plot illustrating the variation of pressure along the length of a pipe for laminar and turbulent flow conditions. It defines hypothetical pressure profiles for laminar and turbulent flows and plots them against the pipe length.",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "Plot the velocity distribution in a Couette flow between two parallel plates with a given velocity gradient.",
            "answer": "\n          import numpy as np\n         import matplotlib.pyplot as plt\n         \n         # Define parameters\n         \n         h = np.linspace(0, 1, 100) # Distance between plates (normalized)\n         velocity_gradient = 2 # Given velocity gradient\n         \n         # Calculate velocity distribution using linear profile for Couette flow\n         \n         velocity = velocity_gradient * h\n         \n         # Plot velocity distribution\n         \n         plt.figure(figsize=(10, 6))\n         plt.plot(h, velocity)\n         plt.xlabel('Distance between Plates (Normalized)')\n         plt.ylabel('Velocity')\n         plt.title('Velocity Distribution in Couette Flow')\n         plt.grid(True)\n         plt.show()\n          ",
            "explanation": "This code generates a plot illustrating the velocity distribution in Couette flow between two parallel plates with a given velocity gradient. It defines a normalized distance between the plates and calculates the corresponding velocity using a linear profile for Couette flow.",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "How is Archimedes' principle used in real applications?",
            "answer": "Archimedes' principle states that any object immersed in a fluid receives an upward thrust equivalent to the weight of the displaced fluid. This is key in the design of ships in that the weight of the displaced fluid must be greater than the weight of the ship and passengers so that it will float.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "How do the effects of pressure forces and shear forces vary when acting on a fluid blob?",
            "answer": "Pressure forces act perpendicular to a surface of a fluid blob while shear forces act tangential to the surface. Pressure forces can translate a blob when shear forces can rotate a blob. A pressure variation is necessary to generate a net force, and therefore, an acceleration.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "What assumptions and principles underly Bernoulli's equation and how can it be used to determine gradients across curved streamlines?",
            "answer": "The assumptions for deriving Bernoulli's equation are as follows:\n1) ignore gravity\n2) ignore shear forces\n3) the flow is steady\n4) the fluid is incompressible\n5) the fluid particles experience acceleration in the streamline direction and normal direction\nWith pressure forces being the only forces acting on a fluid blob, Newton's second law can be used. Once solved, Bernoulli's equation, p + 0.5 * rho * v^2 = c, is derived, which can generally only be used along streamlines. This equation shows there is an inverse relationship between pressure and velocity. Using Newton's second law again with curved streamlines, there is a pressure gradient along the streamlines with lower pressure being towards the center of the curvature. By using Bernoulli's equation, high pressures are related to low velocities so with a strong streamline curvature, one can expect high pressures and low velocities on the outside and low pressures, high velocities on the inside.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "Describe the velocity profiles for a favorable and adverse pressure gradient for combined Couette and Poiseuille flow.",
            "answer": "In combined Couette and Poiseuille flow, one plate is moving while the other is stationary. In a favorable pressure gradient, pressure pushes the fluid in the direction of the moving plate. The velocity profile is parabolic with a steep gradient near the stationary plate. In an adverse pressure gradient, the pressure pushes in the opposite direction of the moving plate. The velocity profile is also parabolic, but it might reverse near the stationary plate.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "What are some key properties in a process that differentiate it from being reversible or irreversible, and what are some examples of each?",
            "answer": "In reversible processes, there can not be any substantial deviations from equilibrium, hence it is a quasi-equilibrium process. This means that with pdV work, the pressure must be uniform throughout a cyclinder. Irreversible processes have non-uniformities in some properties, such as temperature decay through conduction. An example of a reversible process is a slow adiabatic compression/expansion of a gas in a cylinder. An irreversible process is such where two copper blocks with a finite temperature difference are brought into thermal contact. Heat transfer occurs from the hotter block to the colder block and once equilibrium is reached, spontaneous heat flow doesn't reverse.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "Given the system a gas enclosed by a piston and insulating walls with a stirrer, how are adiabatically inaccessible states a consequence of the 2nd law of thermodynamics?",
            "answer": "It is to be noted that the system can only receive shaft work from the stirrer. If the piston is displaced slowly, the gas can be compressed/expanded along a quasi-equilibrium adiabatic curve on a pV graph. If a system starts below the curve, a combination of stirring and compressing/expanding can move its state to be on the curve. Once on the curve, work can not be extracted to go below the curve because you can not unstir the gas. The only way to go to a state that is below the curve would be by extracting heat to the surroundings, but since the gas is perfectly insulated, this is not possible. The idea of going from a state on the curve to below the curve adiabatically can not occur, making some states adiabatically inaccessible due to the second law.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "What underlying principles are needed for the Tds equations and how are they derived?",
            "answer": "A first Tds equation can be derived from the first law of thermodynamics and the definition of entropy. By substituting the definition of entropy and flow work (pdV work) into the first law, the first Tds equation is derived (Tds = dU + pdV). A second Tds equation is formed by using the definition of enthalpy (H = U + pV). When a small change in enthalpy occurs, one can solve for dU and subsitute it into the first Tds equation. With further simplifying, the second Tds equation becomes Tds = dH - Vdp. These Tds equations encompass the first and second laws of thermodynamics and are valid for simple compressible systems in the absence of capillarity, electric, and magnetic fields.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "Give an example of a system in which you would want to increase entropy.",
            "answer": "Maximizing entropy rise is key in an axial turbo-heater that is designed to convert mechanical work input into large static temperature rises while maintaining a low static pressure rise.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "How do velocity and pressure change for supersonic flow in a diverging nozzle?",
            "answer": "By taking the derivative of the conservation of mass in a slice of a converging-diverging nozzle, an equation relating the change in velocity, change in area, and Mach number can be derived. The equation shows that when the Mach number is greater than 1 and the change in area is positive, hence a diverging nozzle, the change in velocity must be positive. Using the 1D Euler equation relating a change in velocity and change in pressure, with a positive change in velocity, the change in pressure must be decreasing. This is unintuitive when compared to subsonic flows through a diverging nozzle.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "When flow through a convergent nozzle is choked at the throat, what effect does decreasing the exit static pressure have on the flow?",
            "answer": "When the flow is choked, decreasing the exit static pressure further will not increase the mass flow rate through the nozzle. Since fluid blob communication happens at the speed of sound, communication between the inlet and exit can not occur quick enough, effectively being lost.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "What is Fanno flow and what effects does it have on subsonic and supersonic flow?",
            "answer": "Fanno flow assumes that flow through a pipe is adiabatic and the cross area of the duct is constant. It is considered an irreversible process since viscous friction acts as a shear stress on the walls of the pipe. The friction reduces the effective area of the pipe, and if the pipe is sufficiently long enough, the friction serves to choke the throat in the pipe. If the flow entering the pipe is subsonic, its velocity starts to rise to the choking condition. If the flow entering the pipe is supersonic, the velocity drops through the pipe until it is choked.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
        },
    
        {
            "question": "A fluid with a density of 1000 kg/m^3 and velocity of 3 m/s enters a wind tunnel with a diameter of 0.5 m. A body sits in the wind tunnel with a circular cross-sectional area. The fluid exits with a velocity of 5 m/s. Determine the diameter of the body in the wind tunnel.",
            "answer": "rho = 1000  # density (kg / m^3)\\nv1 = 3      # inlet velocity (m/s)\\nv2 = 5      # exit velocity (m/s)\\nD = 0.5     # diameter of wind tunnel (m)\\n\\n# apply continuity (A1 * v1 = A2 * v2)\\n# note that A2 can be represented with the diameter of the wind tunnel and body\\nd = D * (1 - v1 / v2) ** 0.5\\n\\nprint(\"Diameter of the body is\", d, \"meters\")",
            "explanation": "This problem requires the principle of conservation of mass for incompressible flow (A1*v1 = A2*v2). A1 can be calculated with the area of a circle and v1 and v2 are given. A2 can be derived by the difference in areas between the wind tunnel and the body. Once a relation is made, one can solve for the diameter of the body.",
            "reference":""
        },
        {
            "question": "A water jet exits a nozzle and strikes a wall. If the volumetric flow rate through the nozzle is 0.5 m^3/s and the diameter of the jet is 0.12m, find the force on the wall. Assume the density of the water is 1000 kg/m^3.",
            "answer": "import numpy as np\\n\\nrho = 1000  # kg / m^3\\nQ = 0.5     # m^3 / s\\nD = 0.12    # m\\n\\nA = 0.25 * np.pi * D ** 2\\nv = Q / A\\nF = rho * Q * v\\nprint(\"The force on the wall is\", F / 1000, \"kN\")",
            "explanation": "Assuming that the flow is steady, inviscid, and perpendicular to the wall, the steady flow momentum equation can be used to find the force on the wall. Using the area of the jet and the volumetric flow rate, the velocity can be calculated. The mass flow rate and velocity can used in the steady flow momentum equation to find the force acting on the wall.",
            "reference": "https://eaglepubs.erau.edu/introductiontoaerospaceflightvehicles/chapter/worked-examples-fluid-flows/"
        },
        {
            "question": "Consider two quasi-equilibrium processes: one adiabatic and one isothermal. Each system contains air initially at 300K and specific volume of 1 m^3/kg. The systems expand the air to a specific volume of 10 m^3/kg. For each process, determine the specific work done by each system and the specific heat transferred to each system. Assume gamma = 1.4, c_v = 716.5 J/kg*K and R = 287 J/kg*K.",
            "answer": "import numpy as np\\n\\nR = 287     # J/kg*K\\nc_v = 716.5 # J/kg*K\\nT1 = 300    # initial temperature (K)\\nv1 = 1      # initial specific volume (m^3/kg)\\nv2 = 10     # final specific volume (m^3/kg)\\ngamma = 1.4\\n\\n# Isothermal process\\nw = R * T1 * np.log(v2 / v1)\\nprint(\"The work done by the isothermal system is\", w / 1000, \"kJ/kg\")\\n# change in internal energy for isothermal system is zero\\nprint(\"The heat transferred to the isothermal system is\", w / 1000, \"kJ/kg\")\\n\\n# Adiabatic process\\np1 = R * T1 / v1\\np2 = p1 * (v1 / v2) ** gamma\\nT2 = p2 * v2 / R\\nw = -c_v * (T2 - T1)\\nprint(\"The work done by the adiabatic system is\", w / 1000, \"kJ/kg\")\\nprint(\"The heat transferred to the adiabatic system is 0 kJ/kg\")",
            "explanation": "Since there is no temperature change in an isothermal process, the equation for specific heat and work is R * T * ln(v2/v1), which is derived by integrating pdV work and using the ideal gas law. In the adiabatic process, the ideal gas law can be used to get the initial pressure and using the relationship between pressure and specific volume and gamma, the final pressure can be calculated. T2 can be derived from the ideal gas law with p2. For an adiabatic process, work done is equal to the negative change in internal energy so using c_v, the work done can be derived. Heat transfer is zero in an adiabatic process.",
            "reference": "https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/16-01-unified-engineering-i-ii-iii-iv-fall-2005-spring-2006/pages/exams/"
        },
        {
            "question": "Consider a river flowing toward the ocean at an average velocity of 11 m/s at a rate of 350 m^3/s at a location 20 m above ocean level. Determine the total mechanical energy per unit mass and calculate the maximum power generation potential of the river. Assume density of water to be 1000 kg/m^3.",
            "answer": "rho = 1000  # kg/m^3\\ng = 9.81    # m/s^2\\nh = 20      # m\\nv = 11      # m/s\\nQ = 350     # m^3/s\\n\\n# Total mechanical energy\\ne = g * h + 0.5 * v ** 2\\nprint(\"The total mechanical energy per unit mass of the river water is\", e, \"J/kg\")\\n\\n# Maximum power generation potential\\n# max power = m_dot * e\\np_max = rho * Q * e\\nprint(\"The maximum power generation potential of the river at sea level is\", p_max / (10 ** 6), \"MW\")",
            "explanation": "Using the conservation of energy equation, the specific mechanical energy can be calculated, noting that potential and kinetic energy are non-negligible while there is no flow work. Using the density and volumetric flow rate, mass flow rate can be calculated to help calculate maximum power generation due to the river.",
            "reference": "https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9v18YlyxUq4"
        },
        {
            "question": "A steady flow system produces 405 kW of work with the following conditions. The mass flow rate is 3 kg/s. Each unit of mass passing through the system loses 9 kJ of energy. The inlet flow rate is 0.37 m^3/kg and exit is 0.62 m^3/kg. The inlet pressure is 6 bar and the exit is 2 bar. The inlet flow velocity is 16 m/s and the exit is 270 m/s. The inlet is 32 m above the exit. Find the difference in specific internal energy from the outlet to the inlet. Note 1 bar = 10^5 Pa.",
            "answer": "g = 9.81  # m/s^2\\nW = 405   # kW\\nm_dot = 3 # kg/s\\nQ1 = 0.37 # m^3/kg\\nQ2 = 0.62 # m^3/kg\\np1 = 6    # bar\\np2 = 2    # bar\\nv1 = 16   # m/s\\nv2 = 270  # m/s\\nh = 32    # m\\nQ = -9    # kJ/kg\\n\\n# u2 - u1 = Q_in - W_out + (p1*v1 - p2*v2) + 0.5(v1^2 - v2^2) + gh\\nw = W / m_dot # kJ/kg\\nflow_work = (p1 * 10 ** 5 * Q1 - p2 * 10 ** 5 * Q2) / 1000  # kJ/kg\\nke = 0.5 * (v1 ** 2 - v2 ** 2) / 1000 # kJ/kg\\npe = g * h / 1000 # kJ/kg\\ndelta_u = Q - w + flow_work + ke + pe # kJ/kg\\nprint(\"The change in specific internal energy from the outlet to inlet is\", delta_u, \"kJ/kg\")",
            "explanation": "The steady flow energy equation can be used to calculate the change in specific internal energy. Note that each unit of mass is losing 9 kJ of energy so Q_in is -9 kJ/kg. Work is given in units of energy / second so dividing by the mass flow rate gives the work in units of energy / mass.",
            "reference": "https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=T5QPPNYd_m0"
        },
        {
            "question": "Air enters an adiabatic duct with a diameter of 12 cm with the following conditions: Mach number 0.4, static temperature 550 K, and static pressure 200kPa. The skin friction coefficient in the duct is 5.25 * 10^-3. If the Mach number at the duct exit is 0.8, determine the duct length and static temperature, static pressure, and velocity at the exit. Assume gamma to be 1.4, c_p = 1005 J/kg*K, and R = 287 J/kg*K.",
            "answer": "gamma = 1.4\\nR = 287     # J/kg*K\\nc_p = 1005  # J/kg*K\\nc_f = 0.00525\\nD = 0.12    # m\\nM1 = 0.4\\nT1 = 550    # K\\np1 = 200    # kPa\\nM2 = 0.8\\n\\n# Inlet velocity\\na1 = (gamma * R * T1) ** 0.5\\nv1 = M1 * a1\\n\\n# Use gas properties tables to get ratios at different Mach numbers\\np2 = 0.4783 * p1\\nT2 = 0.9149 * T1\\na2 = (gamma * R * T2) ** 0.5\\nv2 = M2 * a2\\nL = (2.3085 - 0.0723) * (0.25 * D / c_f)\\n\\nprint(\"The static temperature at the duct exit is\", T2, \"K\")\\nprint(\"The static pressure at the duct exit is\", p2, \"kPa\")\\nprint(\"The velocity at the duct exit is\", v2, \"m/s\")\\nprint(\"The length of the duct is\", L, \"m\")",
            "explanation": "Use the gas flow properties tables to get the ratios of static to stagnation pressures and temperatures to find the exit conditions. Use the tables to get the values (4 * c_f * L / D) at the different Mach numbers. Use the skin friction coefficient to determine the length of the duct with the given inlet and exit conditions.",
            "reference": "https://drahmednagib.com/onewebmedia/SPC407/Sheet_6_Solution-SPC-407.pdf"
        },
        {
            "question": "Air at Mach 3.75 and static pressure of 35 kPa and static temperature of 228.15 K flows over the inlet ramp of a hypersonic aircraft. The ramp angle is 20 degrees. Calculate the static pressure, static temperature, and velocity of the air beyond the inlet ramp. Note that gamma is 1.4 and R = 287 J/kg*K.",
            "answer": "import numpy as np\\n\\ngamma = 1.4\\nR = 287       # J/kg*K\\nM1 = 3.75\\np1 = 35       # kPa\\nT1 = 228.15   # K\\ntheta = 20    # degrees\\nbeta = 33.438 # degrees\\n\\nMn1 = M1 * np.sin(beta * np.pi / 180)\\nMn2 = np.sqrt((1 + (gamma - 1) / 2 * Mn1 ** 2) / (gamma * Mn1 ** 2 - (gamma - 1) / 2))\\nM2 = Mn2 / np.sin((beta - theta) * np.pi / 180)\\np2 = p1 * (2 * gamma * Mn1 ** 2 - gamma + 1) / (gamma + 1)  # kPa\\nT2 = T1 * (1 + (gamma - 1) / 2 * Mn1 ** 2) * (2 * gamma / (gamma - 1) * Mn1 ** 2 - 1) / ((gamma + 1) ** 2 / (2 * gamma - 2) * Mn1 ** 2) # K\\na2 = (gamma * R * T2) ** 0.5\\nv2 = M2 * a2  # m/s\\n\\nprint(\"The static pressure beyond the inlet is\", p2, \"kPa\")\\nprint(\"The static temperature beyond the inlet is\", T2, \"K\")\\nprint(\"The velocity of the air beyond the inlet is\", v2, \"m/s\")",
            "explanation": "Use the gas flow properties tables to find the value of beta for the given Mach number and theta angle. Use the oblique shock relations to find the normal Mach number for flow entering the ramp and exiting. Use the normal exit Mach number to find the exit Mach number. Use the calculated values and gamma to find the exit static pressure, static temperature, and velocity.",
            "reference": "https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nbt0fcnbl04"
        },
        {
            "question": "How do subsonic and supersonic fanno flows in long pipes react differently?",
            "answer": "As the viscous flow moves down the pipe, the effective flow area decreases due to friction. This acts as a subsonic nozzle, increasing the velocity of the flow. For supersonic flow, it acts as a diffuser, reducing the velocity of the flow.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "What is the relationship between the mach angle and the wave angle for an oblique shock?",
            "answer": "The wave angle is greater than the mach angle unless the wedge angle is very near 0.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "How can a T-S diagram show that heat addition is dependent on path, not state?",
            "answer": "The area between reverisble curves in a T-S diagram is equal to heat addition in a cyclic process. There are multiple paths that a process can take between states on the diagram, so therefore heat is dependent on path.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "How do changes in entropy occur in a process?",
            "answer": "Changes in entropy are due to addition or subtraction of heat with respect to tempurature, or becuase of irreversibilities in the process. Irreversibilities can arise from turbulent flow, unrestrained expansion of a gas, and heat transfer losses.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "What is the difference in measurement between a pressure tube facing a flow and one normal to it?",
            "answer": "A normal tube measures the full velocity of the flow, and hence, the pressure. A tube that faces the flow causes the flow to stagnate, measuring 0 velocity and a pressure of (pressure + 1/2*density*(true velocity)^2).",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "How would the mach number of a jet flying at the same velocity vary with differing tempuratures?",
            "answer": "The mach number would be lower with a lower tempurature, becuase mach number is inversely related to the square root of tempurature.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "How can one derive a relation between mach numbers across a shock?",
            "answer": "Multiplying isentropic conservation of energy with continuity and dividing it by momentum relates the mach numbers across a shock. There are two solutions, one where there is a shock, and one where the mach number stays the same and ther is no shock.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "What differentiates a system from a control volume?",
            "answer": "In a system, the mass remains constant and mass connot cross the system boundary, but energy in the form of work amd heat can, and the boundary can change in size. A control volume has the same properties as a system, but mass can flow through the volume with equal inlet and outlet massflows. Additionally, control volumes cannot change size.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "What forces acting on a fluid blob do the navier-stokes equations consider?",
            "answer": "The navier stokes equations consider the pressure forces acting on each face of a blob, as well as shear forces from the fluid viscosity.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "A combustion chamber has an ablative liner, and the volume increases during the burn. If the initial stagnation pressure is 300 psi, and the pressure at the throat is 100psi, how much can the volume of the chamber increase and still remained choked? Assume a perfect gas with gamma of 1.4.",
            "answer": "\n            import numpy as np\n\n            p01 = 300 # initial stagnation pressure (psi)\n            pt = 100 # throat static pressure (psi)\n            # to stay choked, pt/p0 must be < 0.528\n\n            p02 = pt / 0.528 # min choked stagnation pressure (psi)\n\n            dv = p01/p02 # change in volume ratio\n\n            print('The volume can increase by a maximum of:', dv, 'x while remaining choked')\n\n            ",
            "explanation": "This code uses the the fact that exit static pressure must be less than 0.528 * (upstream stagnation pressure). Since the amount of gas in the chmaber stays constant. Pressure inversely decreases with an increase in volume. Therefore maximum volume increase can be calculated as the point when chamber stagnation pressure is equal to exit static pressure / 0.528.",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "Calculate the efficiency of a reverisble cyclic heat engine between a hot and cold resovoir. The hot resovoir has a temp of 300C, and the cold has a temp of 5C.",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nT1 = 300 + 273.15 # convert to kelvin\nT2 = 5 + 273.15 # convert to kelvin\nnu = 1 - T2/T1 # caclulate efficiency for a reversible process\nprint('Efficiency: ', nu)\n",
            "explanation": "This code calculates efficiency for a reverisble process using the equation nu = 1 - (T2/T1), where nu represents efficiency, T1 represents the tempurature of the hot resovoir, and T2 represents the tempurature of the cold resovoir.",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "Calculate the static pressure and tempurature downstream of shock that occurs in a flow with a mach number of 2. The upstream static pressure is 4 bar, and the upstream static tempurature is 400K. Assume the fluid to be air, and gamma to be 1.4.",
            "answer": "\n            import numpy as np\n\n            p1 = 4 # initial static pressure\n            T1 = 400 # initial static tempurature\n            gamma = 1.4 # cp/cv ratio for air\n            M1 = 2 # initial mach number\n            p2 = p1*((2 * gamma * M1**2) / (gamma + 1) - (gamma -1) / (gamma + 1))\n            T2 = T1*(1 + (gamma - 1)/2 * M1**2) * ((2 * gamma) / (gamma - 1) * M1**2 - 1) / ((gamma + 1)**2 / (2 * (gamma - 1)) * M1**2)\n            print('Downstream static pressure: ', p2, 'bar.', ' Downstream static temp: ', T2, 'K.')            \n            ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the static pressture and tempurature ratios downstream of a shock in a mach 2 flow using the shock relations. It multiplies these ratios by the inital pressure and tempurature to get the final values. Friction is assumed to be negligible.",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "An incompressible flow of water (rho = 1000kg/m^3) enters a horizontal pipe at a 45 degree angle with respect to the normal of the entrance. The inlet areat is 1 m^2. The velocity of the flow is 10 m/s. Calculate the exit massflow out of the pipe.",
            "answer": "\n            import numpy as np\n            v = 10 # total flow velocity (m/s)\n            rho = 1000 # density of water (kg/m*3)\n            A = 1 # area of inlet (m^2)\n            vx = v * np.sin(np.pi/4) # obtain x component of flow, pi/4 radians= 45 degrees\n            print(vx)\n            mdot1 = rho * A * vx # calculate massflow into the pipe (kg/s)\n            mdot2 = mdot1 # apply continuity to show massflow in = massflow out\n            print('Massflow out: ', mdot2, 'kg/s')\n            ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the x component of the flow velocity using trigonometry. Then it applies the massflow equation: mdot = rho*A*v to find the inlet velocity. From continuity, this value is the same as the exit massflow.",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "Calculate the pressure in an isentropic polytropic process with a polytropic constant of 2 and a volume of 2 L. Assume gamma is 1.4.",
            "answer": "\n            import numpy as np\n            gamma = 1.4 # cp/cv\n            C = 2 # polytropic constant (bar * L)\n            n = gamma # polytropic index for a isentropic process\n            V = 2 # volume in litres\n            p = C / (V**n) # apply the equation for a polytropic process (bar)\n            print('Pressure: ', p, ' bar.') \n            ",
            "explanation": "This code utlized the polytropic process equation (pV^n = C) for an isentrpoic process n = gamma. It solves the equation for p (pressure).",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "Cacluate the specific heat transferred to a perfect gas flow with an inlet velocity of 100m/s and an exit velocity of  250 m/s and a change in tempuratre across the control volume of 50K. Assume a cp = 1006 kJ/kg*K and that there is no work.",
            "answer": "\n            import numpy as np\n\n# change in potential engery is negligible\ndT = 50 # temp (K)\nv1 = 100 # inlet velocity (m/s)\nv2 = 250 # outlet velocity (m/s)\ncp = 1006 # kJ/kg*K\n\n# apply steady flow energy equation\nq = cp * dT + (v2**2)/2 - (v1**2)/2 # calculate q (kJ/kg)\nprint('Specific heat transfer: ', q, ' kJ/kg.')\n            ",
            "explanation": "This code uses the specific steady flow energy to calculate specific heat transfer in the abscence of work. It uses the formula dh = cp * dT to relate tempurature difference in a perfect gas to enthalpy difference, where dh is  change in enthalpy, dT is change in tempurature, and cp is specific heat capacity. It plugs the results into the SFEE.",
            "reference": "https://ocw.mit.edu/ans7870/16/16.unified/thermoF03/chapter_6.htm"
        },
        {
            "question": "Find the cv for an incompressible perfect gas in which the specific entropy change in reversible process is 20 kJ/kg, with an initial tempurature of 400K and a change in tempurature of 46C. ",
            "answer": "\n            import numpy as np\n\n            ds = 20 # change in entropy (kJ/kg)\n            dT = 46 # change in tempurature (K)\n            T1 = 400 # initial tempurature (K)\n\n            # apply Tds to solve for cv\n            cv = ds / np.log((T1 + dT) / T1) # kJ / kg * K\n            print('The cv is: ', cv, ' kJ / kg * K')\n\n            ",
            "explanation": "This code uses the Tds equation ds = cv*ln(T2/T1) + R*ln(rho1/rho2) to solve for cv. Since the fluid is incompressible, the R term is 0, and cv can be solved for by dividing the change in entropy (ds) by the natural log of the tempurature ratio (T2/T1). ",
            "reference": ""
        },
        {
            "question": "A rigid 800L container holds a 30kg sample of CO2 at 280K. The CO2 is slowly heated to 400K. Calculate the pressure in the container both before and after being heated up. Assume that the CO2 is behaving like an ideal gas.",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nV = 800 * 0.001 # Volume (m^3)\nm = 30 # mass (kg)\nT1 = 280 # initial temperature (K)\nT2 = 400 # final temperature (K)\nR = 188.92 # specific gas constant of CO2 (J/kg*K)\n\n#The ideal gas equation is PV = mRT\nP1 = (m * R * T1) / V # initial pressure (Pa)\nP2 = (m * R * T2) / V # final pressure (Pa)\n\nprint('The pressure in the container before being heated up is ', P1, ' pascals', and the pressure in the container after being heated up is ', P2, ' pascals.')\n      ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the change in pressure using the ideal gas equation which relates the pressure, volume, and temperature of an ideal gas. It uses the formula PV = mRT, where 'P' is the pressure of the gas, 'V' is the volume of the container holding the gas, 'm' is the mass of the gas, 'R' is the gas constant of the gas, and 'T' is the temperature of the gas.",
            "reference": ""
          },
          {
            "question": "At a given point on the wing of a Boeing 727, the pressure and temperature of the air are 2.4 x 10^4 N/m^2 and 210K, respectively. What is the density of the air at this point?",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nR = 287 # specific gas constant of air (J/kg*K)\nP = 24000 # pressure of the air (Pa)\nT = 210 # temperature (K)\n\n# Use the ideal gas equation\nrho = P / (R*T)\n\nprint('The density of the air is ', rho, ' pascals.')\n      ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the density using an alternate form of the ideal gas equations, P = rho * RT, where P is the pressure of the gas, rho is the density of the gas, R is the gas constant of the gas, and T is the temperature of the gas.",
            "reference": "John D. Anderson Jr. (2010) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill, page 98, problem 1.1a"
          },
          {
            "question": "A U-tube mercury manometer is used to measure the pressure at a point on the wing of a wind-tunnel model. One side of the manometer is connected to the model, and the other side is open to the atmosphere. Atmospheric pressure and the density of the mercury are 1.01 x 10^5 N/m^2 and 1.36 x 10^4 kg/m^3, respectively. When the displacement of the two columns of mercury is 20 cm, with the high column on the model side, what is the pressure on the wing?",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nPatm = 101000 # Pressure of the atmosphere (Pa)\nrhol = 13600 # Density of the mercury (kg/m^3)\nh = 0.2 # Height difference of the mercury in the two tubes (m)\ng = 9.8 # gravitational acceleration constant (m/s^2)\n\n# The pressure in a tube can be calculated by adding the pressure at the opening of the tube with the pressure exerted by the fluid above the depth of interest.\n# The pressure at a specific depth is the same in both tubes. The pressure in the tube on the model side is Pm + rhol * gh, where Pm is the pressure on the wing.\n# The pressure in the tube on the side open to the atmosphere is Patm + rhoa * gh, where rhoa is the density of air. Since the density of air is very small, the rhoa * gh term can be considered negligible.\n# Setting the two equations equal to each other and rearranging some terms, we get that Pm = Patm - rhol * gh.\n\nPm = Patm - rhol * g * h\n\nprint('The pressure on the wing is ', Pm, ' pascals.')\n      ",
            "reference": "John D. Anderson Jr. (2010) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill, page 100, problem 1.11"
          },
          {
            "question": "Consider the flow properties a point in the flow where the temperature is 320K and the velocity is 1000 m/s. Calculate the Mach number at this point",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\ngamma = 1.4 # specific heat ratio of air\nR = 287 # specific gas constant of air (J/kg*K)\nT = 320 # temperature (K)\nV = 1000 # velocity of the gas (m/s)\n\n# The Mach number can be calculated as V/a, where 'V' is velocity and 'a' is the speed of sound.\n# a can be calculated as sqrt(gamma * RT). Putting the two equations together, we get M = V/sqrt(gamma * RT)\nM = V / np.sqrt(gamma * R * T)\n\nprint('The Mach number at this point is ', M)\n      ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the Mach number using the Mach number equation and the equation for the speed of sound, M = V/sqrt(gamma * RT), where M is the Mach number, V is the velocity in m/s, gamma is the specific heat ratio, and T is the temperature in K.",
            "reference": "John D. Anderson Jr. (2010) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill, page 560, example 8.2"
          },
          {
            "question": "Consider a long tube with a length of 300m. The tube is filled with helium, a monatomic gas, at a temperature of 320K. A sound wave is generated at one end of the tube. How long will it take for the wave to reach the other end?",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nd = 300 # distance (m)\ngamma = 1.67 # specific heat ratio of monatomic gases\nR = 2078.5 # specific gas constant of helium (J/kg*K)\nT = 320 # temperature (K)\n\n# The distance travelled by an object can be calculated with d = vt, where d is the distance, v is the speed of the object, and t is time\n# The velocity of sound is given by sqrt(gamma * RT). Combining these two formulas and rearranging some terms, we get that t = d/sqrt(gamma * RT)\nt = d / np.sqrt(gamma * R * T)\n\nprint('It would take ', t, ' seconds for the sound wave to reach the end of the tube.')\n      ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the time it takes for sound to travel by using a combination of the distance and speed of sound formulas, t = d/sqrt(gamma * RT), where d is distance, gamma is the specific heat ratio, R is the specific gas constant, and T is the temperature.",
            "reference": "John D. Anderson Jr. (2010) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill, page 564, example 8.6"
          
          },
          {
            "question": "Consider a flow along a streamline with a velocity of 50 m/s, a density of 1.23 kg/m^3, and a pressure of 1.01 x 10^5 N/m^2. The pressure at a point downstream the streamline is decreased to 0.9 x 10^5 N/m^2. Assuming that the flow is incompressible, what is the velocity at this point?",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nv1 = 50 # upstream velocity (m/s)\np1 = 101000 # upstream pressure (Pa)\nrho = 1.23 # density (kg/m^3)\np2 = 90000 # downstream pressure (Pa)\n\n# Use Bernoulli's equation, p1 + 0.5 * rho * v1^2 = p2 + 0.5 * rho * v2^2 => v2 = sqrt(2(p1 - p2)/rho + v1^2)\nv2 = np.sqrt((2*(p1 - p2) / rho) + v1**2)\n\nprint('The velocity downstream is ', v2, ' m/s.')\n      ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates the downstream velocity using Bernoulli's equation, p1 + 0.5*rho*v1^2 = p2 + 0.5*rho*v2^2, where p1 and p2 are the upstream and downstream pressures, v1 and v2 are the upstream and downstream velocities, and rho is the density of the fluid.",
            "reference": "John D. Anderson Jr. (2010) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill, page 210, example 3.1"
          },
          {
            "question": "Consider the gas in the resevoir of a supersonic wind tunnel. The pressure and temperature of the air in the resevoir are 20 atm and 300K respectively. The air in the resevoir isentropically expands through the wind tunnel duct until it reaches a point where the pressure of the air is 1 atm. Calculate the temperature at this point.",
            "answer": "\nimport numpy as np\n\nT1 = 300 # initial temperature (K)\np1 = 20 # initial pressure (atm)\np2 = 1 # final pressure (atm)\ngamma = 1.4 # specific heat ratio of air\n\n# Use the isentropic relations for pressure and temperature, (p2/p1) = (T2/T1)^(gamma/(gamma-1)) => T2 = T1(p2/p1)^((gamma-1)/gamma)\nT2 = T1 * (p2/p1)**((gamma-1)/gamma)\n\nprint('The temperature of the air is ', T2, 'K.');\n      ",
            "explanation": "This code calculates temperature using the isentropic relations, (p2/p1) = (T2/T1)^(gamma/(gamma-1)) => T2 = T1(p2/p1)^((gamma-1)/gamma), where p1 and p2 is the pressure at state 1 and state 2 respectively, T1 and T2 is the temperature at state 1 and state 2 respectively, and gamma is the specific heat ratio.",
            "reference": "John D. Anderson Jr. (2010) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill, page 529, example 7.5a"
          },
          {
            "question": "A rigid 90L container holding 20kg of CO2 is heated from 300K to 400K. What is the work done by the gas during this process?",
            "answer": "The work done by a gas can be found with the integration of pdV between state one and state two, where p is the pressure of the gas, and dV is the change in volume. Because the container is rigid, there is no change in volume, meaning the gas did not do any work.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "Explain the differences between non-ideal gases,, ideal gases, semi-perfect gases, and perfect gases.",
            "answer": "The properties of non-ideal gases , such as pressure, temperature, and volume, can't be related using the ideal gas equation and must be determined empirically. Meanwhile, the ideal gas equation can be used for determining the relationships between the properties of an ideal gas. Semi-perfect gases and perfect gases are both subsets of ideal gases, where semi-perfect gases have heat capacities that vary depending on temperature, while perfect gases have heat capacities that are independent of the temperature of the gas.",
            "explanation": "",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "What exactly is a shock wave, and how do flow properties change across it?",
            "answer": "A shock wave is a very small region of supersonic flow where flow properties change by a large amount near instantaneously. Across a shock wave, the Mach number decreases, the stagnation pressure decreases, the entropy, density, static pressure, and static temperature increase, and the stagnation enthalpy and stagnation temperature remain constant.",
            "reference": "https://www.grc.nasa.gov/www/k-12/airplane/oblique.html#:~:text=The%20change%20in%20flow%20properties,are%20generated%20in%20the%20flow"
          },
          {
            "question": "What do all the lines on an expansion fan diagram mean?",
            "answer": "The lines on a Prandtl-Meyer expansion fan are meant to be a representation of an infinite number of Mach waves, each changing the flow angle and flow velocity by a small and continuous amount.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference": "John D. Anderson Jr. (2010) Fundamentals of Aerodynamics, McGraw-Hill, Chapter 9.6"
          },
          {
            "question": "Bernoulli's principle doesn't make any sense. Why doesn't increasing inlet pressure increase the velocity of the fluid at the inlet?",
            "answer": "It may help to think of Bernoulli's principle in terms of F = ma. Fluid flowing from a high pressure region to a low pressure region will accelerate due to the net force from the difference in pressure along the direction of the flow. For example, increasing the inlet pressure will cause the fluid to accelerate, resulting in a higher outlet velocity where the pressure is lower.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference": "https://www.khanacademy.org/science/physics/fluids/fluid-dynamics/a/what-is-bernoullis-equation"
          },
          {
            "question": "What are pitot-static tubes and how do they work?",
            "answer": "Pitot-static tubes are measurement devices that measure both the stagnation pressure and static pressure in order to determine the velocity of a fluid. A probe facing the direction of the fluid flow isentropically brings the flow to rest, allowing for the measurement of the stagnation pressure, which is equal to the static pressure + the dynamic pressure. Another probe angled 90 degrees away from the flow direction measures the static pressure. These measurements can then be used to find the dynamic pressure, which is described as 1/2 * density * velocity of the flow^2. This can then be used to find the velocity of the flow.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "On T-s diagrams, why do constant volume lines have larger slopes than consstant pressure lines?",
            "answer": "To find the slope of a constant volume line, we can use the Tds equation Tds = du + pdv. If volume is constant, then this term is reduced to Tds = du, where du = C_v * dT. Rearranging some terms, we get that dT/ds = T/C_v. A similar process can be done using the equation Tds = dh - vdp for constant pressure lines, where dh = C_p * dT and dp = 0. This results in the equation dT/ds = T/C_p. Since the constant pressure specific heat capacity (C_p) is larger than the constant volume specific heat capacity (C_v), the constant volume line has a greater slope than the constant pressure line on a T-s diagram.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "What causes oblique shocks to form, and why do they form at all?",
            "answer": "An oblique shock forms when a fluid traveling at supersonic speeds is interrupted by a wedge in the flow. Because the fluid is flowing at a speed greater than the speed of information, the flow direction and properties upstream the wedge does not change. When the flow meets the wedge, it can't travel through the wedge and will instead abruptly change direction at an angle known as the wave angle, creating an oblique shock.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference": "Yunus A. Çengel, Michael A. Boles, Mehmet Kanoğlu (2023) Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, McGraw Hill, Chapter 18-5"
          },
          {
            "question": "Why do fluid properties still change throughout steady flow? I thought steady flow was defined as no change over time?",
            "answer": "Steady flow is defined as flow where all points of the flow remain constant in respects to time. However, the flow properties are only constant at one point in space. As soon as the fluid moves from one point in the flow to another, its properties can change. The flow is still considered steady as long as its properties at each point in space remain constant over time.",
            "explanation":"",
            "reference":""
          },
          {
            "question": "Can you break down the State Postuate? What is each element of the principle?",
            "answer": "The state of a simple compressible system is completely specified by two independent, intensive properties.\nTo further break down the postulate, we need to define some terms:\nA simple compressible system is a system without electrical, magnetical, gravitational, motion, and surface tension effects. An intensive property is one that doesn't change with size. For example, volume is NOT an intensive property but density and specific volume are. For properties to be independent, one must be able to be varied while keeping the other constant. Independent properties may change depending on the system."
          },
          {
            "question": "How is pressure measured? What are common measurement devices and how do they vary?",
            "answer": "A manometer is a 'U'-shaped device that measures an applied pressure. The device contains a liquid that has a displacement in height after the pressure is applied. This way one end has the applied pressure and the other has the atmospheric pressure. We can then use the pressure vs depth equation (p_2 = p_1 + rho(g)(h)) and known values to find the applied pressure.\nA barometer works similarly with the displacement of height, but we are comparing an applied pressure to the pressure of a vacuum.\nA pitot tube measures stagnation and static pressure through two openings. One that faces towards the flow measures stagnation pressure while the tube opening at 90 degrees measures static pressure. The difference calculated can be interpreted as the dynamic pressure."
          },
          {
            "question": "What is the Zeroth Law of Thermodynamics and why was it required to be established before the 1st-3rd Laws?",
            "answer": "If two bodies are in thermal equilibrium with a third body, they are also in thermal equilibrium with each other.\nHaving the zeroth law gives us a set definition and key property of temperature. It was named the zeroth law even though it was created after the first and second laws because the zeroth law provides necessary assumptions to apply the others.\nFor example, this established temperature as a property: bodies in thermal equilibrium have the same temperature. It also gave meaning to the Kelvin scale where it is measured from an absolute zero: where enthalpy and entropy are minimized."
          },
          {
            "question": "What is an adiabatic process, and how can we distinguish if a process is adiabatic?",
            "answer": "An adiabatic process is one where no heat is transferred, often used in equations as Q = 0. In general, systems that are insulated can be assumed to be adiabatic. Processes that also occur quickly can be assumed to be adiabatic since there is no time for heat to be transferred.\nIf a system is adiabatic, we can make more assumptions if given other conditions. For example, adiabatic and reversible processes are also isentropic."
          },
          {
            "question": "How can we compare the lift resulting from the Magnus effect to the lift generated in a standard airfoil?",
            "answer": "The Magnus Effect occurs when a spinning object travels through a fluid. The spin can generate a force that curves the object's trajectory. In the case of a cylinder rotating in a flow, this can generate lift.\nThis occurs because speaking in simple terms and Newton's Third Law, the spin pushs the air down which pushes the cylinder up. What's really happening when the air is 'pushed down' is that a pressure differential is created (high pressure under the cylinder, low above the cylinder) which generated lift.\nThis pressure differential is the same thing that causes lift in a standard airfoil, but instead of being generated by spin, an airfoil's lift is generated through its geometry."
          },
          {
            "question": "What does the Del Operator represent and what are some of its applications in other equations?",
            "answer": "In the scope of this course, the del operator takes on 3 main roles calculating: gradient, divergence, and advection.\nFirstly, the del operator is defined as taking the partial derivative of the x-component with respect to x, the y-component with respect to y, and the z-component with respect to z.\nJust taking the del operator of a vector will give you the gradient which is also a vector. The gradient shows directions where the value increases.\nTaking the dot product of the del operator and a vector is called the divergence. The divergence (a scalar) tells you net flux of each point (how many vectors are pointing to this point in a way). If divergence is greater than zero then the point is a source. If less than zero, then the point is a sink. If it is zero then neither apply.\nTaking the dot product of velocity and the del operator of a value gives us advection which can be described as the rate of change of the value given the velocity. Advection is a scalar value."
          },
          {
            "question": "What are the properties of a sound wave and why do they matter when considering compressible fluid mechanics?",
            "answer": "Sound waves are longitudinal waves as opposed to transverse waves. This means in a sound wave there are regions of compression and rarefaction. During the transition between these regions the temperature and pressure vary adiabatically.\nWe can calculate the speed of sound using conservation and momentum equations to derive it as a function of the derivative of pressure with respect to density. With more rearranging with adiabatic relations and ideal gas law, we can derive a function for the speed of sound with respect to temperature and gas constants.\nThis allows us to rewrite equations in terms of Mach number rather than velocity and density because writing in terms of Mach number and gamma is more useful in incompressible fluid dynamics then writing in velocity and density as we are used to."
          },
          {
            "question": "What is a choked flow? What are two ways for a flow to reach Mach 1?",
            "answer": "Using conservation of mass, the 1D Euler equation, and the definition of the speed of sound, we can derive an equation that solves for the change in area as a function of Mach Number and acceleration.\nWhen viewing the equation it beomces evident that when M = 1, dA/dx must be equla to zerom, indicating a minimum area. This region of minimum area is called the throat, and if M = 1 is reached, we can say the throat is choked. This means if the incoming flow is M < 1, and the throat is choked, then the resulting flow will be supersonic.\nSince one way to choke a flow is reducing the area, another way this could be acheived is reducing the effective area through friction. Increasing the Mach Number using a converging nozzle is equivalent to increasing the Mach Number through a rough pipe."
          },
          {
            "question": "How do expansion fans differ from shocks? What causes their properties to change after the expansion/shock?",
            "answer": "Expansion fans are defined as a continuous sequence of Mach Waves. Mach waves change the flow by a dtheta and dv. They are generated as supersonic flow passes by a convex corner.\nShocks are created in supersonic flow passing by a concave corner (oblique shock) or just in supersonic flow (normal shock). This occurs because when flow is supersonic, the fluid blobs that normally react in density variations cannot move in time. Shocks are an intense build up of pressure that result in a drop in stagnation pressure.\nUnlike shocks, expansion fans are isentropic. This means that stagnation temperature and stagnation pressure are constant before and after the expansion fan. In a shock, Mach number decrease while in an expansion fan, Mach number increases. In a shock, density increases, static pressure increases, and static enthalpy increases. In an expansion fan, density decreases, static pressure decreases, and static enthalpy decreases."
          },
          {
            "question": "A fan is to accelerate quiescent air to a velocity of 10m/s at a rate of 4m^3/s. Determine the minimum power that must be suppllied to the fan if the density of air is 1.18 kg/m^3.",
            "answer": "\n      rho = 1.18 # density of air in kg/m^3\n      vel = 10 # velocity of air in m/s\n      acc = 4 # acceleration of velocity in m^3/s\n\n      #finding mass flow rate\n      m_dot = rho*acc # mass flow rate = rho*area*vel or rho*acc\n      power = 0.5*m_dot*vel**2 # simplified SFEE equation\n\n      #Answer\n      print('Minimum power needed for the fan to accelerate the air to the given values:', power, 'W')\n      ",
            "explanation": "We can assume this is a steady flow process and use the SFEE. This is an adiabatic process with no change in ethalpy or height, so the equation is simplified to a function for Power (w_dot) with mass flow rate and velocity which are given.",
            "reference": "YA Cengal and MA Boles, Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, 5th ed, McGraw-hill, 2006, pg 100" 
          },
          {
            "question": "A House is maintained at 1 atm and 24 degrees Celcius, and warm air inside a house is forced to leave the house at a rate of 150m^3/h as a result of outdoor air at 5 degrees inflitrating into the house through the cracks. Determine the rate of net energy loss of the house due to mass transfer.",
            "answer": "\n      R = 0.287 # Gas constant of air in kPa*m^3/(kgK)\n      c_p = 1005 # specific heat (J/kgK)\n      p = 1*101.325 # fixed pressure of the house in kPa\n      T = 24 + 273.13 # fixed temperature of the house in Kelvin\n      T2 = 5 + 273.13 # outdoor temperature\n      rate = 150 # rate of warm air leaving the house in 150m^3/h\n\n      #finding density using ideal gas law\n      rho = p/(R*T)\n\n      #finding mass flow rate \n      m_dot = rate * (1/60) * (1/60) * rho # mass flow rate in kg/s\n\n      # rearranging SFEE to solve for net energy loss with enthalpy\n      # use c_p definition for enthalpy\n      net_E = m_dot*c_p*(T2-T)\n\n      print('The rate of net energy loss of the house due to mass transfer is:', abs(net_E), 'W')\n      ",
            "explanation": "First we get the gas constants and solve for density using the ideal gas law. Then using density and the rate given in the problem, we can solve for the mass flow rate. Using the SFEE and seeing that v and z = 0, we must use the change of enthalpy which can be rearranged using the definition of specific heat with constant pressure (c_p).",
            "reference": "YA Cengal and MA Boles, Thermodynamics: An Engineering Approach, 5th ed, McGraw-hill, 2006, pg 258"
          },
          {
            "question": "Two pipes of diameters 4cm and 5cm converge to form a single pipe of diameter 12cm. If a liquid flows with a velocity of 7m/s and 13m/s in the two pipes, respectively, what will be the flow velocity V in the third pipe? Hint: Assume steady, one-dimensional, incompressible flow.",
            "answer": "\n      v1 = 7 #velocity at inlet 1 in m/s\n      v2 = 13 #velocity at inlet 2 in m/s\n      d1 = 4*0.01 #diameter of inlet 1 in m\n      d2 = 5*0.01 #diameter of inlet 2 in m\n      d3 = 12*0.01 #diameter of outlet 3 in m\n\n      #Using conservation of mass and incompressible, we can set volumetric flow rates with each other\n      #Solving for areas\n      A1 = 0.25*3.14*d1**2\n      A2 = 0.25*3.14*d2**2\n      A3 = 0.25*3.14*d3**2\n\n      #Solving for v\n      v = (v1*A1+v2*A2)/A3\n\n      print('The flow velocity in the third pipe is', v, 'm/s')\n      ",
            "explanation": "To solve this problem we can use continuity or the conservation of mass. This means m_dot_in = m_dot_out. Since all of the velocities are below M = 0.3, we can assume this flow is imcompressible, and the volumetric flow rates are equal to each other. With rearranging we can solve for the final velocity as the size of the inlet/outlet pipes vary.",
            "reference": "https://eaglepubs.erau.edu/introductiontoaerospaceflightvehicles"
          },
          {
            "question": "Water (density = 1,000 kg/m^3) flows in a hose with a velocity of 1.0 m/s and a pressure of 300 kPa. At the nozzle, the pressure decreases to atmospheric (101.3 kPa). There is no change in height. (a) Calculate the velocity of the water exiting the nozzle. (b) The hose ejects the water stream through the nozzle with a final diameter of 3 cm. The stream is then directed onto a stationary wall. Determine the force on the wall from the stream.",
            "answer": "\n      rho = 1000 # density of water in kg/m^3\n      v1= 1 # initial velocity in m/s\n      p1 = 300*10**3 # initial pressure in Pa\n      p2 = 101.3*10**3 # final pressure in Pa\n\n      # rearranging Bernoulli's Equation\n      v2 = (2*(p1-p2)/rho+v1**2)**0.5\n\n      print('The answer to part A is that the exit velocity is ', v2, 'm/s')\n\n      d = 3*0.01 # diameter of final nozzle in m\n      a = 0.25*3.14*d**2 #area of final nozzle in m^2\n      m_dot = rho*v2*a\n      force = m_dot*v2\n\n      print('The answer to part B is that the force on the wall is ', force, 'N')\n      ",
            "explanation": "For part a, since the flow is steady, inviscid, and connected by a streamline. We can relate the starting and ending velocities and pressures with Bernoulli's Equation. Rearranging, we can solve for v2 using v1, p2, and p1.\nFor part b, we can take the given area of the nozzle and find the mass flow rate. With the mass flow rate and velocity we can calculate the change in momentum, or force.",
            "reference": "https://eaglepubs.erau.edu/introductiontoaerospaceflightvehicles"
          },
          {
            "question": "Air, at a stagnation pressure of 7.20 MPa and a stagnation temperature of 1100K, flows isentropically through a converging-diverging nozzle having a throat area of 0.01 m^2. Determine the speed and the mass flow rate at the downstream section where the Mach number is 4.0.",
            "answer": "\n      gamma = 1.4 # gamma value for air\n      R = 287 # specific gas constant for air in J/(kgK)\n      P_0 = 7.2*10**6 # stagnation pressure in Pa\n      T_0 = 1100 # Stagnation temp in K\n      M = 4 # Mach number of 4\n      fm_dot = 1.281 # non dimensional mass flow rate at a choked throat (from table)\n      A = 0.01 #throat area in m^2\n      cp = R*gamma/(gamma-1)\n\n      # to find speed of a mach number we must determine static temperature at that point.\n      # solving for static temp using isentropic relations\n      T = T_0*(1+((gamma-1)/2)*M**2)**(-1)\n\n      # solving for speed using Ma\n      v = M*(R*gamma*T)**(0.5)\n\n      # solving for mass flow rate using continuity\n      m_dot = fm_dot*A*P_0/((cp*T_0)**0.5)\n\n      # answers\n      print('The speed of the downstream area is ', v, 'm/s')\n      print('The mass flow rate of the downstream section is', m_dot, 'kg/s')\n      ",
            "explanation": "Firstly to find the speed, we need Mach number, gamma, static temperature, and R. This means we must solve for static temperature which we can do using the isentropic relation between stagnation and static temperature.\nThen we can use our values to find velocity.\nTo find the mass flow rate, we can find the non-dimensional mass flow rate from the gas table. Then solve for m_dot.",
                "reference": "https://engineering.purdue.edu/~wassgren/teaching/ME20000/index.html" 
          },
          {
            "question": "A system executtes a power cycle while receiving 1050 kJ by heat transfer at a temperature of 525 K and discharging 700 kJ by heat transfer at 350 K. There are no other heat transfers. (a) Determine if the cycle is internally reversible, irreversible, or impossible. (b) Determine the thermal efficiency. Compare this value with the maxiumum possible efficiency.",
            "answer": "\n      Q_in = 1050 # heat transfer in, in kJ\n      T_in = 525 # temperature of transfer in, in K\n      Q_out = 700 # heat transfer out, in kJ\n      T_out = 350 # temperature of transfer out, in K\n\n      # using Clausius' inequality\n      clausius = Q_in/T_in-Q_out/T_out\n      isRev = (clausius == 0)\n\n      print('Is this process reversible?:', isRev)\n\n      # using the equation for efficiency, since it is rev, we can use T instead of Q\n      efficiency = 1 - T_out/T_in\n\n      print('The efficiency of this process is', efficiency)\n      ",
            "explanation": "To determine reversibility, we can use Clausius's Inequality which states that the integral of dQ/T must be less than or equal to zero. If this inequality is equal to zero, then it will be reversible. Since Q is independent of T, we can use a summation to represent it.\nA conditional is used to check if this is zero to show if it reversible.\nThen, use the efficiency equation to solve the second part. T is used since it was determined this was a reversible reaction, but using Q is applicable for all processes.",
                "reference": "https://engineering.purdue.edu/~wassgren/teaching/ME20000/index.html"
          },
          {
            "question": "There is a normal shock in uniform air stream. The properties upstream of the shock wave are V_1 = 412 m/s, P_1 = 92 kPa, T_1 = 300 K. Determine V_2, P_2, T_2, T_02, P_02 downstream of the shock.",
            "answer": "\n      v_1 = 412 # upstream velocity in m/s\n      p_1 = 92 # upstream static pressure in kPa\n      T_1 = 300 # upstream static temperature in K\n      gamma = 1.4 # gamma value for air\n      R = 287 # specific gas constant for air (J/kgK)\n\n      # solving for M_1 using M = v/a\n      M_1 = v_1/(gamma*R*T_1)**0.5\n\n      # solving for p_2 using normal shock relations\n      p_2 = p_1*(((2*gamma)*M_1**2)/(gamma+1)-(gamma-1)/(gamma+1))\n\n      # solving for T_2 using normal shock relations\n      T_2 = T_1*(1+((gamma-1)*M_1**2)/2)*((2*gamma*M_1**2)/(gamma-1)-1)/(((gamma+1)**2)*M_1**2/(2*(gamma-1)))\n\n      # solving for v_2 by first solving for M_2\n      M_2 = ((1+((gamma-1)*(M_1**2))/2)/(gamma*(M_1**2)-(gamma-1)/2))**0.5\n      v_2 = M_2*(gamma*R*T_2)**0.5\n\n      # solving for T_02 by using stagnation temp to static temp ratio\n      T_02 = T_2*(1+((gamma-1)*M_2**2)/2)\n\n      # solving for p_02 using isentropic relations\n      p_02 = p_2*(T_2/T_02)**((-1)*gamma/(gamma-1))\n\n      print('The resulting velocity is ', v_2, 'm/s')\n      print('The resulting static pressure is ', p_2, 'kPa')\n      print('The resulting static tepmerature is ', T_2, 'K')\n      print('The resulting stagnation temperature is ', T_02, 'K')\n      print('The resulting stagnation pressure is ', p_02, 'kPa')\n      ",
            "explanation": "This code utilizes normal shock relations and some isentropic relations to determine the conditions post shock.",
            "reference": "https://archive.nptel.ac.in/courses/112/105/112105269/" 
          },
          {
            "question": "What are the differences and similarities between Couette and Poiseuille Flow? Model these.",
            "answer": "\n      import matplotlib.pyplot as plt\n      import numpy as np\n\n      # Define vectors\n      y = np.linspace(-2.5,2.5,30).reshape(30, 1) # y values ranging from 0-5\n      x = np.zeros(30) # positions at x = 0\n      v1 = (y+2.5) # setting V = 5, H = 5 for Linear Couette Flow Equation, shifting by 2.5 to account for y=0 in center\n      v2 = 0.8*(6.25-y**2) # setting H = 5, leading constants = 0.8\n\n      # Plot vectors\n      l1 = plt.quiver(x[0], y[0], v1[0], 0, angles='xy', scale_units='xy', scale=1, color='b', label = 'Couette Flow')\n      l2 = plt.quiver(x[0], y[0], v2[0], 0, angles='xy', scale_units='xy', scale=1, color='r', label = 'Poiseuille Flow')\n      for i in range(1,30):\n        plt.quiver(x[i], y[i], v1[i], 0, angles='xy', scale_units='xy', scale=1, color='b')\n        plt.quiver(x[i], y[i], v2[i], 0, angles='xy', scale_units='xy', scale=1, color='r')\n\n      # Set limits based on vectors\n      plt.xlim(-1, 6)\n      plt.ylim(-2.5, 2.5)\n\n      # Add labels and legend\n      plt.title('Flows')\n\n      plt.legend(loc='lower right')\n\n      # Show plot\n      plt.xticks([])\n      plt.yticks([]) \n      plt.axis('off') # showing continuity in x-direction by hiding y-axis\n      plt.axhline(y=2.5, color='k') # bottom plate (v=0)\n      plt.axhline(y=-2.5, color='k') # top plate (v = V)\n      plt.show()\n      ",
            "explanation": "Couette Flow occurs when fluid moves between two parallel plates. One moves parallel to the plates, and the other is stationary. The assumptions is that the flow is viscid (there are shear forces) and there is no driving pressure gradient (dp/dx = 0). Other unlying assumptions is that the flow is axial and incompressible. Using boundary conditions (the flow velocity is equal to the plate velocity at the plates), Couette flow states that flow velocity is a linear function of the distance from a plate.\nPoiseuille Flow occurs when fluid moves between two stationary plates. This time instead of being driven by the movement of a plate (Couette Flow), Poiseuille Flow is driven by a constant pressure gradient. The assumptions is that the flow is axial and imcompressible. Using boundary conditions (flow velocity should be 0 at stationary plates), Poiseuille Flow states that velocity is a parabolic function with respect to distance from a plate and the direction of the pressure gradient."
          }
]